<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Sions svveets, or, The spouses spikenard; and mysticall myrrhe / by Thomas Barnes, preacher of Gods vvord at St Margretts in New-fifth-street. London..</title>
            <author>Barnes, Thomas, Minister of St. Margaret's, New Fish Street, London.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1624</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 211 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 43 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B07186</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1477.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S124289</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">71305100</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 71305100</idno>
            <idno type="VID">183854</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B07186)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 183854)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2203:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Sions svveets, or, The spouses spikenard; and mysticall myrrhe / by Thomas Barnes, preacher of Gods vvord at St Margretts in New-fifth-street. London..</title>
                  <author>Barnes, Thomas, Minister of St. Margaret's, New Fish Street, London.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 77 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by I.D. for Nathaniell Newbery: and are to be sold at his shop at the signe of the Starre vnder St Peters Church in Corn-hill, and in Popes head Alley.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1624..</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A² B-L⁴ (last leaf blank)</note>
                  <note>Title vignette; head-pieces; engraved initials.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Birmingham Reference Library (Birmingham, England).</note>
                  <note>Bibliographical references in marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>To the right vvorshipfull, the Lady Barrington ... -- The spouses spikenard -- Mysticall myrrhe.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Song of Solomon I, 12-14 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:183854:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:183854:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>SIONS SVVEETS: <hi>OR</hi> THE SPOVSES SPIKENARD; <hi>AND</hi> MYSTICALL MYRRHE. <hi>BY</hi> THOMAS BARNES.</p>
            <p>Preacher of Gods VVord at S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Margretts</hi> in <hi>New-Fiſh-ſtreete.</hi> LONDON.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed by <hi>I. D.</hi> for <hi>Nathaniell Newbery:</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop at the ſigne of the <hi>Starre</hi> vnder S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Peters</hi> Church in <hi>Corn-hi l,</hi> and in <hi>Popes</hi> head Alley. 1624.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:183854:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:183854:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>TO THE RIGHT VVORSHIPFVLL, the Lady <hi>Barrington,</hi> Wife to Sir <hi>Francis Barrington;</hi> the Lady <hi>Eliott,</hi> Wife to Sir <hi>T. E.</hi> the Lady <hi>Barnardiſton,</hi> Wife to Sir <hi>Nathan. B.</hi> and M<hi rend="sup">ris</hi> 
                  <hi>Ioanna Mildmay,</hi> of <hi>Tarling</hi>-hall in <hi>Eſſex;</hi> the ioy of the juſtified, in <hi>Chriſt</hi> the juſtifier, wiſhed.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen firſt I conſulted with my ſelfe, vnder whoſe protection I might ſend abroad theſe <hi>Sweets of Sion, [THE SPOU<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SES SPIKENARD,</hi> and <hi>MYSTI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CALL MYRRHE]</hi> my thoughts fell <hi>(Right Worſhipfull)</hi> vpon you foure. And, after ſome conflicts with inward cauills, I did reſolue to make bold with <hi>all</hi> your names; and ſo much the rather, both becauſe, in <hi>another</hi> Treatiſe ſent forth with <hi>this,</hi> I haue made as bold with your Worſhipfull yoake-fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes: as alſo in regard, the <hi>matter</hi> handled in theſe <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> is ſuch, as be vſefull to <hi>your</hi> ſoules, as well as any of <hi>theirs,</hi> who are true members of <hi>that</hi> CHVRCH, and by faith made one with <hi>that</hi> SPOVSE, whom the whole Booke of <hi>Salomons Songs,</hi> (out of which I haue cull'd <hi>theſe</hi> Sweets) in a moſt ſweete, and heauenly ſtreine
<pb facs="tcp:183854:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> doth treat of. I dare ſay, that were it not for the Authors wants, here you ſhould finde, and meete with <hi>that,</hi> which would be both for <hi>direction,</hi> and <hi>conſolation; Directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> in your carriage, in reſpect of what you <hi>owe</hi> to Chriſt; <hi>conſolation,</hi> for your conſcience, in regard of what you <hi>reape</hi> by Chriſt. For I am ſure, <hi>that</hi> parcell of Scripture, vpon which theſe <hi>Meditations</hi> are, doth afford <hi>ſuch Rules, ſuch comforts</hi> pregnantly, plentifully. In <hi>it</hi> we haue <hi>Chriſt</hi> his <hi>loue,</hi> the <hi>Church</hi> her <hi>loyaltie. Chriſt his loue</hi> vnto his Church, ſitting as a <hi>King</hi> at Table with her, communicating his grace, and fauour vnto her, in the <hi>Ornaments,</hi> and <hi>Ordinances</hi> wherewith he hath endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her. The Church her <hi>loyaltie</hi> vnto her Chriſt: first, <hi>preſenting</hi> him with her <hi>Box of Spikenard,</hi> her <hi>faith</hi> and <hi>good</hi> Workes: ſecondly, <hi>prayſing</hi> him for his <hi>Bundle of Myrrhe,</hi> the <hi>pardoning of her ſinnes,</hi> the <hi>refreſhing of her ſoule:</hi> thirdly, profeſsing ſhee would neuer forget the <hi>greatnes</hi> of his loue, and would endeuour to keepe the <hi>ſence</hi> of his kindnes. This loue of that <hi>great husband</hi> I wiſh you the ſweet of, with a daily encreaſe of it, more and more. This loyaltie of the Spouſeſſe I doubt not but hath beene yeelded by your Worſhips ere now, to Chriſt the head. The bleſsing vpon theſe labours, I craue of God; the Patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage, the acceptance, of theſe endeuours I beg of you. Which <hi>(RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL)</hi> may I but obtaine: <hi>GOD,</hi> for <hi>that his bleſſing,</hi> ſhall haue my <hi>prayſes, YOV for your acceptance</hi> ſhall haue his <hi>prayers,</hi> who is</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your <hi>Worſhips</hi> to be commanded in any Chriſtian ſervice to his power; <hi>THOMAS BARNES.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:183854:3"/>
            <head>THE SPOVSES SPIKENARD.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Canticles 1.12.13.14.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p n="12">
                     <hi>12.</hi> While the King ſitteth at his Table, my Spike<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard ſendeth forth the ſmell thereof.</p>
                  <p n="13">
                     <hi>13.</hi> A bundle of Myrrhe is my welbeloved vnto me, he ſhall lie all night betweene my breaſts.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hree Workes did <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> Write, that the Church of GOD might be the better for that Wiſedome which the God of Wiſedome beſtowed vpon him, <hi>Prover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biall Sentences, Powerfull Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons,</hi> and <hi>Patheticall Songs:</hi> which Workes in Canonicall Scriptures, are knowne by theſe names, <hi>Proverbs, Eccleſiaſtes, Canticles,</hi> each of which
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:183854:4"/> conteineth in it moſt excellent and heavenly matter, but the ſweeteſt of all the reſt is this Booke of the <hi>Canticles.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, vnder a continued <hi>Allegorie</hi> in the forme of a <hi>Paſtorall Elegie,</hi> this heavenly inſpired Poet doth breath out the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lodious ſtraines &amp; paſſages of loue mutually interchanged betweene the great Spouſe <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> and his beſt beloued Bride the <hi>Church.</hi> Amongſt which ſtraines this Text is one, being a part of that heavenly Dialogue betwixt Chriſt and his Church, comprehended in this Chapter. In which Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue, two things (to make the parts of this Chapter) are conſiderable; firſt, the Prologue or Entrance into the Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue, in the firſt ſix verſes. Secondly, the Dialogue it ſelfe, from the ſeaventh verſe to the end of the Chapter. In the Prologue, the Church doth two things; firſt, ſhe expreſſeth her ardent deſire of a coniugall communion with her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band Chriſt Ieſus, in the ſecond, third, and fourth verſes. Secondly, ſhe taketh away the ſcandall, partly, of the croſſe which ſhe is expoſed vnto, partly, of thoſe infirmities which ſhe is inclined vnto, both which might be caſt in her teeth by falſe brethren, to vpbraid her for too much ſaucineſſe, that ſhee ſeeming ſo blacke, dares be ſo bold as to deſire communion with ſo beautifull an husband as Chriſt is; and this ſhe doth in the fifth and ſixth verſes.</p>
            <p>The Dialogue it ſelfe comprehends in it three particulars. Firſt, a queſtion that the Church maketh where ſhee might find her Chriſt as a comforter in the time of affliction, as an helper in the time of temptation, in the ſeaventh verſe. Secondly, Chriſt his anſwere to this queſtion, in the eight verſe. Thirdly, the excellent praiſes which they doe mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally conferre each vpon the other, from the ninth verſe to the end of the Chapter. Chriſt praiſing the Church in the ninth, tenth, eleventh, fifteenth, ſixteenth, and ſeaventeenth verſes. And the Church commending her Chriſt, in the words of this Text, and that from two properties which ſhee perceived in him,
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Greatneſſe</hi> in the 12. verſe.</item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> in the 13. verſe.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:183854:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The firſt of theſe, Order requireth wee ſhould firſt deale withall.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>12.</hi> While the King ſitteth at his Table, my Spikenard ſendeth forth the ſmell thereof.</q>
            <p>BEcauſe the royaltie of perſonage,<note place="margin">Parts of the Text. The reaſon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the diviſion, becauſe <hi>King</hi> in the 12. ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is a ſtile of <hi>Greatnes,</hi> and <hi>Welbeloued</hi> in the 13. verſe a title of <hi>good<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi>
               </note> coſtlines of proviſion for his Bride, and ſtatelineſſe of preſence with his Bride, doe much ſet forth the <hi>Greatneſſe</hi> of a Bridegroome: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Church here commendeth the Greatnes of HER ſpirituall Spouſe, from theſe three particulars. 1.<note n="*" place="margin">Regem non ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trà magnificen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nota appel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latum ſponſum Mercer. ad locum. <hi>The firſt cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance in the firſt part. The mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</hi>
               </note> the royal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of his perſon by the ſtile (KING) that ſhee giveth him. <hi>While the King.</hi> 2. The coſtlines of proviſion for her, by the Table which ſhee ſpeaketh of, calling it <hi>His Table.</hi> 3. The ſtatelines of his preſence, by his ſitting at this Table, <hi>While the King ſitteth at his Table,</hi> amplified by the adiunct <hi>ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> which her Spikenard did ſend vnto him, while he was thus preſent with her; <hi>My Spikenard ſendeth forth the ſmell thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>TO begin with the ſtile royall which ſhee giueth him, <hi>While the King.</hi> Howſoever<note n="a" place="margin">Brightns.</note> One by <hi>King</hi> here, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandeth King <hi>Aſa,</hi> ſpoken of 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 15. and others in the hyſtoricall ſenſe, King <hi>Salomon,</hi> yet with<note n="b" place="margin">Mercer. Piſcat.</note> others I doe rather myſtically vnderſtand Chriſt Ieſus, the ſpirituall <hi>Salomon,</hi> and<note n="c" place="margin">Iſa. 9.6.</note> 
               <hi>Prince of peace.</hi> And ſo our Obſervation muſt be this; <hi>That the husband of the Church Chriſt Ieſus is a King.</hi> This is a knowne Maxime, in the proofe whereof the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is no whit barren. The Pſalmiſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Doct.</hi> 1. Chriſt the Churches Spouſe is a King.</note> ſpeaking in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Church, calleth him<note n="d" place="margin">Pſal. 47.7.</note> 
               <hi>our King. Daniel</hi> calleth him<note n="e" place="margin">Dan. 9.25.</note> 
               <hi>Meſſiah the Prince.</hi> And<note n="f" place="margin">Chap. 12.1.</note> 
               <hi>Michaell the great Prince.</hi> S. <hi>Iohn</hi> in one place of the <hi>Revelation</hi> ſtileth him the <hi>Prince of the Kings of the earth</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Apoc. 1.5.</note>; and in another, the <hi>King of Kings, the Lord of Lords</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Chap. 19.16.</note>. Herewith ſquareth that of <hi>Ieremy,</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Iere. 23.5.</note> 
               <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the daies come, ſaith the Lord, that I will raiſe vnto Dauid a righteous branch, and a KING ſhall raigne and proſper, and ſhall execute iudgement and iuſtice vpon the earth.</hi> The ſame thing ſpake the Angell to <hi>Mary,</hi> concerning Chriſt,<note n="k" place="margin">Luk. 1.33.</note> 
               <hi>He
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:183854:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſhall raigne over the houſe of David, and of his kingdome ſhall be none end.</hi> All theſe teſtimonies (with many other which might haue beene alledged) doe manifeſtly ſhew this to be a truth, That <hi>Chriſt Ieſus, Sions Spouſe, is a King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">How Chriſt is a King, two wayes.</note>And if we would know how he came by this Kingly of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice (which muſt be anſwered before the poynt be applyed) wee muſt vnderſtand, that he is a King two wayes.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Firſt, By dominion of himſelfe.</item>
               <item>Secondly, By donation from another.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt, by dominion and authoritie of himſelfe, and ſo he is <hi>Iehovah,</hi> God equall with the Father, and the holy Ghoſt, in vnitie of eſſence, equalitie of potency, maieſtie, glory, and ſoveraigntie over all creatures.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He is a King by donation and gift, receiuing the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome (as he is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) or Mediator of the Church from the Father, in which regard he is called <hi>Meſſiah</hi> in the olde Teſtament, and <hi>Chriſt</hi> in the new, which ſignifie <hi>Annoynted,</hi> that is, <hi>Annoynted of the Father,</hi> and ſo much he teſtifieth himſelfe;<note n="l" place="margin">Mat. 11.27.</note> 
               <hi>All things,</hi> and<note n="*" place="margin">Chap. 28.28</note> 
               <hi>All power both in heaven and in earth, are giuen me of my Father.</hi> Thus the poynt is made good and made cleere. It is as vſefull as plaine. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> For, firſt of all it lets vs ſee, the notable dignitie of the Church of Chriſt. To heare the Pſalmiſt calling her <hi>the DAVGH<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TER of the King</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Pſal. 45.13.</note>: to heare <hi>Salomon</hi> ſtiling her <hi>the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces DAVGHTER</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Cant. 7.1.</note>, is to heare her dignitie vnmatcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; but to heare her, her ſelfe (as ſhee is the WIFE of Chriſt) ſtiling him <hi>the King</hi> in my Text, to heare <hi>Chriſt the King</hi> calling her his <hi>Spouſeſſe, his loue, his doue, his vndefiled one, &amp;c.</hi> as he doth in more places of this Booke then one; this is to heare her excellency to be vnutterable. What ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour can be paralelled with it? What dignitie is compara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to it? <hi>Behold</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Iohn</hi>) (to ſtirre vp attention) <hi>what manner of loue the Father hath beſtowed vpon vs, that we ſhould be called the ſonnes of God</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">1 Ioh. 3.1.</note>. <hi>Behold,</hi> (may I ſay, to ſtirre vp admiration) <hi>what ſingular kindnes the ſonne hath ſhowne the Church, that ſhee ſhould be the Wife of God?</hi> If by the grace of adoption, to be the BRETHREN of Chriſt, can command
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:183854:5"/> a <hi>Behold</hi> at our hands, then by the vertue of an holy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunction to be the BRIDE of Chriſt, muſt needs call for a <hi>Behold</hi> and <hi>wonder at our hands.</hi> And (to ſpeake truth) ſo wonderfull is this dignitie, that except by an <hi>Allegorie</hi> I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſet it forth. We know that that Woman which hath an earthly King to her husband, excelleth all other degrees of Women (though great and noble) in the Land where ſhee liueth, in divers particulars. For ſhee hath a more noble Guard to attend her, more royall Garments to array her, more c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſtly Iewels to adorne her, more ſtately Pallaces to inhabite in, more pleaſant Galleries to walke vpon, then they haue, or at leaſt then its fit they ſhould haue. And doth not that<note n="p" place="margin">Apoc. 12.1.</note> 
               <hi>Woman cloathed with the Sunne, I meane the</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">So <hi>Paraeus,</hi> and others ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound it.</note> 
               <hi>Church,</hi> who is contracted to the Heavenly King, excell all other ſorts and ſocieties of people in the like? Out of doubt ſhee doth: Emperors with all their Monarchies, Nobles with all their dignities, Captaines with all their Victories, Papiſts with all their prelacies, Pagans with all their excellencies, are not comparable vnto her. Her guard are the Angels of Chriſt<note n="r" place="margin">Pſal. 34.7. Heb. 1.14.</note>; Her garments are the robes of Chriſt<note n="ſ" place="margin">Apoc. 12.1.</note>; Her iewels are the graces or Chriſt; Her dwelling place is the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Chriſt, of grace here, of glory hereafter; Her wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king places are the wayes of Chriſt, for it is onely the privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Chriſtians to tread in the ſteps of their ſoveraigne and Saviour. Well then might the Pſalmiſt ſay, <hi>Glorious things are ſpoken of thee thou Citie of God</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">Pſal 87.3.</note>. I know what opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion the world hath of the Church, deeming her of all peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to be the baſeſt,<note place="margin">O nunquam ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis expenſam credentium dignitatem. Muſcul. in Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plana. Pſal. <hi>45.</hi> v. <hi>9.</hi> Obſ. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> even the very ſcumme and refuſe of men: I know alſo that her owne members in the time of temptation thinke more hardly of themſelues, then there is either cauſe or warrant; But whatſoever the world thinkes of her, whatſoever poore Chriſtians in the times of diſtreſſe thinke of themſelues, yet it is a certaine thing, that <hi>great honour haue all the Saints</hi>
               <note n="u" place="margin">Pſal. 149.9.</note>; the poynt in hand infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth vs of no leſſe, when it ſaith, that <hi>Iſraels husband is a King.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:183854:6"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> Secondly, this poynt is not without its Vſe, for the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the Church;<note place="margin">For the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of <hi>Sion.</hi>
               </note> For, firſt it may be bent AGAINST them by way of terror. Secondly, it may be directed To them by way of counſell.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1. By way of terror.</note>Firſt, I ſay, it may be a ground of terrour AGAINST them, for the wrongs that they offer to the members of Chriſt. Ah poore wretches, are they aware whom they op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe! conſider they whom they ſet againſt! they perſecute, wrong, oppugne, them who are the Wife of Chriſt Ieſus, a glorious Bride, whoſe husband is a King; King, not onely by donation from the Father, but alſo by dominion of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. Meane men (yee know) if they loue their Wiues, will not ſee them wronged if they can helpe it, much leſſe will Kings brooke the iniuries that are offered their Queenes. That treaſon which is ſpoken or plotted againſt them, they take as done to themſelues, and will be revenged for it. And will the <hi>King of Kings,</hi> that <hi>Great Prince, Christ Ieſus,</hi> doe leſſe for his Wife<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the Church? No, no: he paide too deare a price for her, as not to maintaine her cauſe, and avenge her quarrell: and if he vndertakes to defend her, then woe to thoſe that offend her; <hi>Better a Mill-ſtone were hanged about their neckes, and they caſt into the middeſt of the Sea.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I remember in the Booke of <hi>Ioſhua,</hi> how thoſe<note n="*" place="margin">Ioſ. 10.3-26 verſes.</note> fiue Kings were ſerved for Warring againſt the <hi>Gibeonites,</hi> that were entred into league with <hi>Ioſuah;</hi> the Captaines trod vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their neckes, they were hanged vpon fiue trees againſt the Sunne: And will not the great<note n="x" place="margin">Ioſ. 5.15.</note> 
               <hi>Captaine of the Lords Hoſt</hi> tread vpon THEIR neckes, and puniſh THEM in his wrath, that ſet againſt thoſe that are entred not onely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to league, but alſo into contract with Ieſus, our ſpirituall <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuah?</hi> Be but a man a<note n="y" place="margin">Ioſ. 9.27.</note> Water-bearer to the Congregation of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> or a<note n="z" place="margin">Pſal. 84.10.</note> 
               <hi>Doore-keeper in the houſe of God,</hi> or like <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Mat. 11.11.</note> 
               <hi>leaſt in the Kingdome of heaven,</hi> his wrongs ſhall be righted, his cauſe ſhall be avenged. What became of them that ſet againſt <hi>Daniel?</hi> were not their bones broken, and their bodies eaten with the teeth of Lyons<note n="b" place="margin">Dan. 6.24.</note>. How fared it
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:183854:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> with thoſe that bound the three Children, and caſt them into the fiery Furnace? were they not ſcorched to death with the fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me of the fire<note n="c" place="margin">Chap. 3.22.</note>? Did not<note n="d" place="margin">Act. 12.23.</note> Lice gnaw out the bowells, and doth not a curſe lie vpon the name of <hi>Herod,</hi> who murthered <hi>Iames,</hi> and impriſoned <hi>Peter,</hi> the<note n="e" place="margin">Iam 1.1. 1 Pet. 1.1.</note> ſervants of the Lord Ieſus Chriſt? What end came <hi>Nero</hi> vnto, that vnnaturall Monſter, who imbrued his hands in the blood of his owne mother, wife, kindred, and others<note n="f" place="margin">Sueton in vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta Neronis. cap. <hi>34. 35.</hi>
               </note>; that cruell Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as <hi>Paul</hi> calls him<note n="g" place="margin">2 Tim. 4.17.</note>, who murthered and maſſacred the poore Chriſtians? If that be true, which is ſtoried of him, his owne ſword did he ſheath in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>his owne blood, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came his owne Butcher<note n="*" place="margin">Auſon de <hi>12.</hi> Caeſar Matrici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Nero pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prio ſe perculit enſe.</note>. In times of later perſecution a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs, what fearefull endes did thoſe butchers come vnto, that ſlew the Saints. Some had their gutts carried a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the ſtreets vpon Bulls hornes<note n="h" place="margin">Fox Martyr: Olog. edit. Anno <hi>1596.</hi> Pag. <hi>712.</hi> Idem ibid.</note>; others dyed madde<note n="i" place="margin">Pag. <hi>1904.</hi> Melanct. chron. l. <hi>11</hi> p. <hi>20.</hi>
               </note>; others were ſtrucke dead with the immediate hand of God<note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Fox. Mart.</hi> 1908. &amp; 1417</note> as they haue<note n="l" place="margin">3 Ioh. 9.</note> 
               <hi>Diotrephes</hi>-like beene prating and inveighing againſt the members of Chriſt, in their Pulpits. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I tell thee, tis dangerous medling againſt the Saints, it is fearefull to flout at them, to backbite them, ſlander them, hate them, deviſe &amp; practiſe miſchiefe againſt them. What? longeſt thou to haue <hi>Sions King</hi> to breake thee in pieces, and the<note n="m" place="margin">Revel. 5.5.</note> 
               <hi>Lyon of the tribe of Iudah</hi> about thy eares? Alas man, if the rage of an earthly King (as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſpeaketh) <hi>be like the roaring of a Lyon</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Pro. 19.12.</note>, what ſhall Chriſt his wrath be againſt his owne and his Brides adverſaries? Is he thinkeſt thou a King onely IN his Church, and To his Church, to rule it by his Word, and guide it by his Spirit, and not as well a King FOR his Church, to auenge the wrongs thou ſhalt dare to offer vnto it? Oh, fond wretch, doe not deceiue thine owne ſoule; <hi>Vengeance belongs to him and he will repay.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That therefore I may vſe this point by way of counſell,<note place="margin">Deut. 32.35. 2. Part of the vſe to <hi>Sions</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, <hi>viz.</hi> Counſell or perſwaſion.</note> let me perſwade a little with thee; Doe no wrong to the Church of Chriſt, or any member of the ſame. Remember the charge that the Lord himſelfe giueth; <hi>Touch not mine annointed, and doe my Prophets no harme</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">Pſal 105.15.</note>. Touch them not with thy tongue, ſhoote not out <hi>bitter words</hi> againſt them.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:183854:7"/> Touch them not with thy Pen, frame no bitter writings a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them; touch them not with thy hand, offer no vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence vnto them; touch them not with thy head, invent no ill againſt them. For what ſhall it availe thee to wrong them, when as their husband Chriſt is a King.<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Motiue</hi> 1. Againſt this crueltie the King Chriſt bendes his wiſedome and his power. <hi>Ledere ſervos Dei &amp; Chriſti tuis perſecutio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus deſine; quos laeſos vltio divina defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit. Cypr. Tract. contra Demetr. fol.</hi> 72. <hi>Motiue</hi> 2. To wrong the Church is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equall and vniuſt dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling. 1. With Chriſt himſelfe.</note> A King, I ſay, and therefore wants no wiſedome, but is able to goe beyond thee, beeſt thou as craftie in thy fetches as the Serpent was; A King, I ſay, who wants no power, but is able to confound thee, wert thou as mightie in thy courſes as euer proud <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacherib</hi> was: and both his Princely policy, and Kingly po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency, ſhall concurre and meete together for thy ruine, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then his Wife ſhall ſuffer at thy handes any more then what ſhall turne to her eternall well-fare. Is it not a vaine thing for thee to attempt that which both the wiſedome and power of Chriſt oppoſeth it ſelfe againſt?</p>
            <p>Beſides, there is little reaſon, nay it is againſt all reaſon, that thou ſhouldeſt doe harme vnto the Saints, for neither doth the Husband nor the Wife giue any iuſt cauſe vnto thee. Firſt, for the husband and King himſelfe. What wrong did he ever doe thee? Hath he ever dealt vnmercifully and cruelly with thee? Is it not by HIS patience that thou art kept out of hell, ſo long agoe, ſo many wayes deſerved by thee? Is it not by HIS goodneſſe and providence, that thou haſt health, libertie, peace, proſperitie, &amp;c? Nay, doth He not in the motions of his Spirit, which thou quencheſt, in the miniſtry of his Word, which thou deſpiſeſt, make moſt free and gracious offers of his owne precious blood, to ſaue thy ſoule from euerlaſting damnation, &amp; ſaued thou migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt be, if thine impenitent and vnbeleeuing heart did not reiect and ſet light by theſe offers? Anſwere me, by whom haſt thou, thy beeing, life, and moouing, and euery good thing that thou doeſt enioy? and is this the recompence of his kindneſſe, to abuſe and deſpiſe his Wife, his beloued Wife, and perſecute him in his members? What an vniuſt and vnequall thing is this? What? Muſt HIS Wife of all other in the world, be accounted factious, ſeditious, trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble-States, traytors, that ſpeake againſt <hi>Caeſar,</hi> not worthy to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:183854:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> liue in a Common-wealth, &amp;c? Serueſt thou this King thus indeed for his goodneſſe? Oh iniury moſt horrible, Oh wrong moſt intollerable, which thou wilt neuer be able to anſwere, when he ſhall<note n="p" place="margin">Apoc. 1.7. Mat. 24.30.</note> come in the Clouds to avenge the blood of the Saints.</p>
            <p>Againe,<note place="margin">2. It is iniuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice to the Church alſo.</note> As Chriſt himſelfe on <hi>his</hi> part giues thee no iuſt cauſe to hurt his Church, no more doth ſhee on <hi>her</hi> part; for what iniury doth ſhee doe thee? Shee refuſeth indeed to run to the ſame exceſſe of ryot with thee. Accounteſt thou <hi>this</hi> a wrong. In <hi>this</hi> (if thou hadſt but eyes to ſee) ſhee is more thy friend then thine enemy, becauſe ſhee would not by any bad example hearten and harden thee in the way to damnation; contrarily, by her good example ſhee would al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lure thee TO, and invre thee IN the way to ſalvation. Beſides, By HER meanes thou doeſt enioy much good. Were it not for HER, thy houſe would be burned over thy head; for when there ſhall ceaſe to be a Church vpon the earth, all things thereon ſhall be melted by fire<note n="*" place="margin">2 Pet. 3.12.</note>. Many a time doth ſhee confer with her Kingly Spouſe for thy good; ſhee entreateth him (if it be his bleſſed will) to turnr thee from thy ſinnes, to ſaue thee in the heavens; By her pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers ſhee ſtopps many a iudgement from lighting vpon thee, ſhe fetcheth many a bleſſing from heaven for thee. For Gods ſake then be not ſo vniuſt, as to harme thoſe, for whoſe ſake the very world it ſelfe is vpheld &amp; preſerued, and by whoſe meanes thou thy ſelfe doeſt enioy a great deale of good. Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture condemnes iniuſtice againſt the beſt friends. Let me then beſeech thee, (if thou beeſt not altogether inexorable, inflexible) for this cauſe not to offer ſuch iniury to the children of God, ieſt not at them, rayle not vpon them, bend neither thy craft, nor thy crueltie againſt them.<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mot.</hi> 3.</note> They haue buffettings and temptations enough <hi>within,</hi> they had need be ſpared and freed from troubles <hi>without;</hi> Hath thy malice then added to the meaſure of their afflictions? Get thee vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thy knees for it, powre out the ſongs of complaint againſt thy ſelfe before the Lord fot it, meete her husband the King in the way, make thy peace with him for the abuſes thou
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:183854:8"/> haſt offred her his Wife, be not ſayd nay vntill a bill of paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, and reconciliation be ſealed for thee; purpoſe thou and promiſe him neuer to ſerue him ſo in his members any more; learne to loue them as much as euer thou haſt hated them: and doe this ſpeedily too, leaſt that this great King and Bridegroome of the Church, like a<note n="q" place="margin">Hoſ. 13.7.8.</note> 
               <hi>Leopard in the way,</hi> and a <hi>Beare robbed of her whelpes,</hi> riſe vp againſt thee,<note n="r" place="margin">Pſal. 50.22.</note> 
               <hi>teare thee in pieces and there be none to deliuer thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>3</label> Thirdly, is Chriſt a King? This iuſtly taxeth the folly of a great many in the world,<note place="margin">Reproofe of thoſe that neglect an vnion with Chriſt.</note> who care not for, who ſeeke not after, who like not of a matching and marrying with Chriſt Ieſus. He comes vnto vs as a Wooer, in his Word, with his mercies, offring a large ioynture vnto vs in the poſſeſſions of grace here, in the portion of glory hereafter, and faine would he haue entertainment at our handes, but we will none of him; iuſt like <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> (againſt whom he takes vp a bill of complaint by S. <hi>Luke) I would haue gathered you together as an henne gathereth her chickens vnder her wings, but you would not</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">Luke 17.37.</note>? All the day long <hi>ſtretcheth he forth his hand</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">Rom. 10.21. Iſa. 65.2.</note>, but we are a gainſaying people. If now and then we afford him a good looke, and a faire word, by <hi>hearing a Sermon vpon the Saboth,</hi> by <hi>receiuing the Sacrament at Eaſter,</hi> by a little ſuperficiall attendance vpon his ordinances, (when we are vrged to it) thats all he gets at our hands: To giue him our conſent, to be content to be inuiſibly contracted vnto him, and to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake all other onely to cleaue to him, this we will not by any meanes grant him, the greateſt number of vs. Oh that ſo roiall a Suter, ſhould be ſo baſely ſerued at the hands of ſuch baſe creatures. Would any poore mans daughter ſerue a rich mans ſonne after ſuch a faſhion? Would a meane ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects childe deale thus with a Prince, with a King? Shee would not, except ſhee were a foole, or franticke. Ah fooles then, &amp; vnwiſe that WEE are, to giue this Princely Wooer ſo cold a well-come. Haue we no regard to our owne good? can we not ſee when we are well offred? What? thinke wee that we are well enough, rich enough of our ſelues? Alas we, (<hi>Laodicea</hi>-like)<note n="u" place="margin">Apoc. 3.17.</note> 
               <hi>are wretched, miſerable, poore, blind, and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:183854:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> naked,</hi> ſtript and robbed of all the wealth which once we had in our innocent condition; ſo meane, ſo beggerly, that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept we get him into vnion with vs, to be our husband, and inrich vs, it had beene good for vs if wee had neuer beene: Why then ſhould we be ſo ſottiſh, ſo enuious to our owne weale, as to reiect thoſe treaties of marriage with himſelfe, that he proffers vs. I gueſſe at the cauſe of this,<note place="margin">Cavills of ſome (now a reproouing) that care not for Chriſt.</note> &amp; (I thinke) not amiſſe. We (like to ſome Wiues that loue to play rex, and are loth to be vnder rule) deeme the conditions too ſtrict, which his Spouſe muſt conforme vnto, &amp; this marr's the match. Oh! Oh!<note n="*" place="margin">1. That he ties to vnreaſonable conditions.</note> Firſt, he requires ſpirituall chaſtitie at our hands. His Wife muſt be a Virgin,<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 45.14. Iſa. 37.22.</note> 
               <hi>haue doues eyes,</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Cant. 1.15.</note> ſingle and ſimple, not to admit of any Mate with him, <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zechiel's</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">Ezech. 23.5.</note> 
               <hi>harlot,</hi> and <hi>Iames</hi> his<note n="z" place="margin">Iam. 4.4.</note> 
               <hi>adultereſſe,</hi> he cannot away with. That we ſhould part our loue betwixt Mammon and him, him and <hi>Belial,</hi> him and Satan, he will not tolerate, the whole man muſt be kept chaſt wholly for him: If wee entertaine either ſenſuall pleaſures, or ſinfull profits, as our Paramours, we are no Bride for his fellowſhip.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, He muſt haue obedience at our handes; a like ſubiection as was impoſed vpon<note n="a" place="margin">Gen. 3.16.</note> 
               <hi>Eue</hi> to her husband, doth he looke for indeed; he tells vs if wee will match with him, our deſire muſt be to him, he muſt rule ouer vs, and of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie wee muſt<note n="b" place="margin">Pſal. 45.11.</note> 
               <hi>reuerence,</hi> (that is) be in ſubmiſſion vnto him.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, He would haue vs<note n="c" place="margin">Pſal. 45.10.</note> 
               <hi>forget our owne people, and our fathers houſe too.</hi> Looke as Iſraell muſt forſake her idols which ſhee worſhipped in the time of Pagan idolatry<note n="d" place="margin">As <hi>Cyrill</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounds it. <hi>Catech.</hi> 7.</note>; as the <hi>Gentiles</hi> muſt <hi>forget</hi> and leaue the Iewiſh rites and cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies vnder the Goſpell<note n="e" place="margin">So <hi>Lyranus.</hi>
               </note>; ſo muſt we <hi>forget</hi> our old <hi>coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try manners whatſoever</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Iuſt. Mart. in Dialog. cum Trypho. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Luk. 14.26.</hi>
               </note>. Our teeth muſt not be ſet on edge with the ſoure grapes that our fathers haue eaten. That we ſhould retaine any dregs of the vaine ſuperſtition, or keepe any ſmacke of the vile converſation of our forefathers, that we ſhould follow the euill cvſtomes of euill people amongſt whom we liue, will not he at any hand yeeld vnto: He that forſaketh not father, mother, children, friends, and all for
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:183854:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> Chriſts ſake; he that preferreth the pleaſing and imitating any of them before him, is not worthy of him. Here is ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther condition.</p>
            <p>There is another yet, which is not the leaſt. They that fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low and follow him, muſt take vp their croſſe<note n="g" place="margin">Luk. 9.23.</note>: He tells vs the hardeſt in Wooing time: if we be his Diſciples, we ſhall be<note n="h" place="margin">Io. 15.19.21 Luk. 21.17.</note> 
               <hi>hated for his name ſake,</hi> ſcoffed at with <hi>Iſaac</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Gen. 21.9. Gal. 4.29.</note>, oppreſſed with <hi>Iſrael</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Ex. 5.5.6 &amp;c.</note>, accuſed<note n="l" place="margin">1 Sam. 2.19.</note>, hunted<note n="m" place="margin">1 Sam. c. 24, 26. &amp;c.</note> with <hi>Dauid,</hi> impriſoned with <hi>Ieremy</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Iere. 32.2.</note>, ſtocked with <hi>Ioſeph</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">Gen. 39.20.</note>, fettered with <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">Act. 16.23.</note>, fed with the bread of affliction with <hi>Micha</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">1 Kin. 22.27</note>, carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into Captivitie with <hi>Ezechiel</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Ezek. 1.1.</note>, plunged into the den of Lyons with <hi>Daniel</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">Dan. 6.16.</note>, fired in the brazen Bull with <hi>Antipas</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">See <hi>Paraeus</hi> in Apoc. 2.13.</note>, robbed of goods, ſpoyled of life with <hi>Polycarpus</hi>
               <note n="u" place="margin">Apoc. 2.9.</note>. In a word, perſecuted and oppoſed, &amp; men of ſorrowes with himſelfe<note n="*" place="margin">Iſa. 53.3.</note>. Theſe indeed, are the conditions He tyes his Wife vnto, and theſe things, He propounds vnto vs when he comes a Wooing vs, and hence it is we are ſo loath to be contracted vnto him. Hard termes indeed to meere naturaliſts, who haue no eye to ſee the royaltie of the perſon, nor the recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of reward that he brings with him: But to a man that hath any ſound iudgement in ſpirituall matters, theſe <hi>Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles</hi> are eaſie and reaſonable enough, if wee may take the Bridegroomes owne word<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat. 11. laſt.</hi> My yoake is ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, &amp; my bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den light. <hi>The cavills quelled.</hi>
               </note>. Let vs examine the caſe a little. Is it more then reaſon, that, a great Prince (making choice of a peaſants daughter to Wife) ſhould requeſt and require a reſervation and preſervation of her chaſtitie, loue, and loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altie for himſelfe? Muſt <hi>Pharaohs</hi> daughter<note n="x" place="margin">So literally the word <hi>reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence him,</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porteth. Pſal 45.11.</note> obey <hi>Salomon,</hi> and is it much for the Church to obey her <hi>Salomon,</hi> Chriſt Ieſus? <hi>To him onely it is meete</hi> (ſaith<note n="y" place="margin">
                  <hi>Beza. Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſe</hi> vpon Pſal. 45.</note> one) <hi>thou ſhouldeſt be ſubiect, as to thy Lord; I would haue thee to know</hi> (ſaith<note n="z" place="margin">Iohan. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſ ibid. Paraphraſticè. Eſt autem vt ſcias hic rex dominus tuus dignus cuitu in genua prouolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta ſupplex fias.</note> ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) <hi>that this King thy Lord is worthy to haue bended knees, and a bowing heart.</hi> Againe, ſhall <hi>Valeria,</hi> the wife of <hi>Seruius</hi> (of whom<note n="a" place="margin">Hier. li <hi>1.</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſus Iovin.</note> one of the Fathers reporteth) not conſent to marry another, ſaying;<note n="b" place="margin">Seruium ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per viuere.</note> 
               <hi>Seruius my husband liueth ſtill:</hi> and ſhall <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> play the Harlot, ſuffering Egypt, Aſſyria, the world, the Deuill, and corruption to<note n="c" place="margin">Ezek. 23.3.</note> 
               <hi>preſſe and bruiſe the teates of her Virginitie;</hi> as though her husband Chriſt were
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:183854:9"/> quite dead, and without being? Muſt <hi>Sarah</hi> forſake her owne <hi>Country</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Gen. 12.5.</note>, <hi>Rachell</hi> leaue her fathers familie<note n="e" place="margin">Gen. 31.14.</note>, to follow their husbands? and may <hi>Sion</hi> ſtay in Sodom ſtill, not leaue the rotten errors, &amp; corrupt manners, of her old fathers houſe? May ſhee ſay as the Romaniſts doe at this day, <hi>I beleeue as the Church beleeueth,</hi> though they know not how the Church beleeues; or as the Libertines doe, <hi>We will doe as our fathers haue done, as our neighbours doe, we will play on Sundayes, keepe merry company, loue good fellowſhip, ſuch doe ſo, wee will none of theſe preciſe orders in our families, our fathers neuer taught vs this, nor did this;</hi> ſhall ſhee (I ſay) ſay thus? Shall <hi>Michol</hi> incur the diſpleaſure of <hi>Saul</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">1 Sam. 19.12.17.</note> for <hi>Dauids</hi> good; and ſhall the Church be loth to beare rebuke for Chriſt his ſake, and flinch backe becauſe of troubles? Is it too hard, for Chriſt to require conſtancie and patience at her hands? <hi>What great thing I pray is required,</hi> (ſaith<note n="g" place="margin">Muſc. in Pſal. p. <hi>357.</hi> A. Quaeſo quid magni exigitur cum idem con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iugi ſuo debeat vxor.</note> one) <hi>when euery Wife owes the like to her husband!</hi> What want of equitie is in theſe conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons? let any man iudge. Or put caſe theſe termes were vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable. Yet this husband is an <hi>heauenly King</hi> (you ſee) and that makes amends for all, lighteneth the burden, and qualifieth the ſeeming tartnes of theſe Articles. But its come to <hi>Calvins</hi> ſaying;<note n="h" place="margin">In Pſal. 45. v. 11.</note> 
               <hi>Hereupon groweth it, that we be ſo ſtately and proud</hi> (we will none of Chriſt) <hi>becauſe we conſider not how precious a treaſure God offreth vs in his onely begotten ſonne. If this vnthankefulneſſe letted not, it would not grieue vs after the example of Paul,</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Phil. 3.8.</note> 
               <hi>to account whatſoeuer we ſet moſt ſtore by, to be but dung, and right nought, that Chriſt might enrich vs with his riches.</hi> Worthy therefore to be blamed, are all thoſe, who, (becauſe they muſt keepe themſelues chaſt from whooring after their owne pleaſures, and profits, yeeld obedience to Chriſts will<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſuffer troubles for his name, renounce their ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitions and corruptions for his ſake) cannot, will not accept thoſe treaties of communion with himſelfe, which in loue he tendereth vnto them. What ſayd I? Worthy to be blamed? Nay (their contempt of the royaltie of his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and richnes of his portion being conſidered) they are worthy to be excluded from euer hauing ſhare in that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:183854:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> GLORY, which he hath prepared for his owne.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>4</label> Fourthly, Is <hi>Iſraels</hi> Spouſe an heauenly King? What re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerent regard and good well-come ought we (then) to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford Gods Miniſters,<note place="margin">Exhortation to make much of <hi>Levi,</hi> who labours in matching vs to Chriſt.</note> who come vnto vs and deale with vs about a Match with Chriſt Ieſus. Wee know what reſpect <hi>Rebeccah</hi> gaue <hi>Eliezer, Abrahams</hi> ſervant<note n="k" place="margin">Gen. 24.31.32.33.</note>, when hee came vnto HER about a Match with the Patriarch <hi>Iſaack</hi> his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters ſonne: how much made on a Princes meſſenger to a poore mans daughter, about ſuch a matter ſhould be, wee may eaſily coniecture; and ſhall not we account the<note n="l" place="margin">Iſa. 52.7. Rom. 10.15.</note> 
               <hi>feete of them beautifull, that bring vnto vs the glad tydings of peace;</hi> and that tell vs, that the ſonne of God would faine be married vnto vs? God forbid, but we ſhould. Alas, alas then what an heauie inditement at the day of iudgement, will be brought IN againſt the vnthankfull world, for the bad en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainement that it yeelds vnto the Lords Levites, and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourers in this buſines. We come from the King of heauen, as his Ambaſſadors, we talke with people about this Spouſe, and (according to the talent which the Lord hath lent vs) we acquaint them with the comelines of his feature, the ſtatelines of his perſon, the greatnes of his portion, we direct them how to entertaine him, ſhew them the way how to obtaine him, &amp;c. And yet (lamentable it is to conſider) ſome deride vs, ſome diſgrace vs, and many deale vniuſtly with vs. Men and brethren, what ſhall wee doe? Shall we deſiſt? Hath the Lord taken an oath of vs (as <hi>Abraham</hi> of his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant) that wee ſhall ſeeke out a Wife for his ſonne, and ſhall we deale falſely and faithleſly in our errand? Oh, let vs la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to ioyne ſtill, even heaven and earth, Chriſt and the Church. We haue not our names<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and offices of<note n="m" place="margin">Levi <hi>ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth</hi> ioyned.</note> 
               <hi>Levi</hi> for nought. Pray we for a bleſſing vpon our trauaile, as<note n="n" place="margin">Gen. 24.12.</note> 
               <hi>Elie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zer</hi> did; ſhun we not to <hi>declare all the counſell of God</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">Act. 20.27.</note>, for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny by-reſpect whatſoeuer; and then albeit our meſſage be not entertained by All, as we doe deſire, yet a good <hi>Rebeccah</hi> will make vs well-come for the tydings that we bring her of this heauenly <hi>Iſaac,</hi> and the comfort wee ſhall reape in this, will countercheck the diſcomforts that may be occaſioned
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:183854:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> by the contrary. And as for the Egyptian Dames, <hi>Philiſtins Dalilahs, daughters of Heth,</hi> and wicked ones, who care the leſſe for vs, by how much the more wee vrge them to this Bridegroome; let them liue ſingle from Chriſt if they liſt; one day they will curſe the time, that euer they ſet ſo light by ſo weightie a meſſage, ſo Princely a marriage.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>5</label> Fiftly, I may vſe this poynt as a Motiue to ſtirre vp Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, to ſolicite Chriſt for the good of their brethren,<note place="margin">Adviſe to pray for the church in affliction.</note> a part of his Bride, who are vnder the rod, and the flaile, for the Goſpells ſake. His Kingly office, is an argument, that there is neither want of wiſedome, nor defect of power, to bring to nought, the ſubtile policies, and cruell practiſes of thoſe Romiſh<note n="p" place="margin">The Ieſuits.</note> blood-hounds, and heatheniſh Atheiſts, who hunt after the ruine of Gods <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Hauing then ſuch an one to ſpeake to, why ſhould our prayers be either few or cold? Nay, why not more then ordinary in extraordinary times of need? What an heauie caſe is it, that in the<note n="q" place="margin">Iſa. 22.12.</note> 
               <hi>day when the Lord calls vs to mourning, to weeping, to baldneſſe, and girding with ſackcloth,</hi> there ſhould be<note n="r" place="margin">Verſ. 13.</note> 
               <hi>ioy and gladnes, ſlaying Oxen, and killing ſheepe, eating fleſh and drinking Wine!</hi> Oh, that this principle could learne vs better things. Needfull it is (now if euer) for vs that wee <hi>ſhould;</hi> well it would be with vs, if we <hi>would</hi> euen importune this Bridegrome for his church, with the Prophet <hi>Dauids</hi> argument; <hi>Thou art my King, O God, command deliverances for Iacob</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">Pſal. 44.4.</note>.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>6</label> Finally, what a number of ſweet rills doe flow from this fountaine, to comfort and atcheere the children of God.<note place="margin">Comfort to the faithfull.</note> Speake thou afflicted Chriſtian, what is it that troubleth thee? The Deuill dogges thee, doth he not? Corruption clogs thee, doth it not? Peradventure thou thinkeſt, thou ſhalt not hold out to the end: It may be the reproches of neighbours, the malice of enemies, the feare of death, and the like, doe diſquiet thee. Well, whatſoever it be that grieueth thee, proue but thou that Chriſt Ieſus hath wooed thee, and won thee to himſelfe, and this poynt will glad thee and comfort thee.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:183854:11"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Comfort,</hi> 1. Againſt Satan.</note>What though that Arch-adverſary to thy peace, and thy ſoule, the Devill, will not let thee alone, but is euer and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non moleſting of thee, with ſuch and ſuch aſſaults, ſetting vpon thee. Remember, thy husband is a King: and this<note n="t" place="margin">Gen. 3.15.</note> 
               <hi>ſeed of the Woman hath broken the head of that ſerpent,</hi> and vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toriouſly conquered this <hi>Prince of darkenes,</hi> inſomuch, that though he doth nibble at thy heele, yet this Prince, this God of Peace, ſhall<note n="u" place="margin">Rom. 16.20.</note> 
               <hi>tread him downe ſhortly vnder thy feete;</hi> And then all his darts that he hath ſhott out againſt thee, ſhall be retorted vpon himſelfe, to the wounding of his own pate. Yea, and this be thou ſurely perſwaded of too, for thy husband, the great King, <hi>will</hi> haue it ſo, ſuch is his <hi>pleaſure,</hi> and <hi>can</hi> haue it ſo, ſuch is his <hi>power.</hi> So that the Devill can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſo violent againſt thee, but Chriſt will be as valiant againſt him for thee<note n="*" place="margin">Quo impetu venerat, eodem impetu pulſus eſt, &amp; quantum fotmidinis, &amp; terroris attulit, tantum forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudinis inuenit &amp; roboris. Cyp. Epiſt. l. <hi>1.</hi> Ep. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note>.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. Againſt the rebelling of nature againſt grace.</note>Secondly, Feareſt thou that thy <hi>corruptions</hi> will ſubiugate thee to their former yoake, and prevaile over thee, becauſe they are continually ſtirring againſt the worke of the Spirit in thee? Conſider ſtill thy husband is a King; and by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent, he hath maſtered ſinne for thee, even in thine owne fleſh,<note n="x" place="margin">Pſal. 68.19.</note> he hath led captiuitie captiue, he hath layd chaynes vpon thy luſts, and hath taken ſuch order for the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all decreaſe of euill in thee, that (like as it was fore-prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſied, the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> ſhould the <hi>Babylonians</hi>) ſo thou ſhalt take thoſe <hi>Corruptions captiues, whoſe captiue thou wert, and thou ſhalt rule ouer thoſe thy ſpirituall oppreſſors, and reſt ſhalt thou haue from this thy ſorrow, and thy feare, and from the hard bondage, wherein</hi> (before converſion) <hi>thou wast made to ſerue</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">Iſa. 14.2.3.</note>.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <note place="margin">3. Againſt doubting of perſeverance.</note>3. Standeſt thou in doubt, whether thou ſhalt haue grace e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to bring thee to heaven, and is this a diſcomfort vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee? ſtill keepe the memoriall of this poynt in thy thoughts. In this thy King<note n="a" place="margin">Coloſſ. 1.19. Chap. 2. v. 9.</note> 
               <hi>dwells the fulnes of the God-head bodily,</hi> and the abſolute <hi>riches of all graces,</hi> which graces are the iewells that he mindes to furniſh and fill thee withall continually. Will a Princely wooer be ſparing in <hi>his</hi> gifts? will he marry himſelfe with one, whom he meanes to make
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:183854:11"/> a bill of divorce againſt, after there hath paſſed a moſt ſweet Communion betwixt them for a time? Or what? Can he not for want of <hi>might,</hi> or <hi>loues</hi> he not for want of <hi>will,</hi> to make that good which he promiſed, when he ſayd,<note n="b" place="margin">Hoſ. 2.19.20.</note> 
               <hi>I will marry thee to my ſelfe FOR EVER?</hi> yea, and that <hi>in righteouſnes, in iudgement, in faithfulnes,</hi> and <hi>knowledge?</hi> When tookeſt thou him euer <hi>tardy,</hi> or faithles? He would not be <hi>thy Prince, thy Soveraigne,</hi> if he meant not to guide thee by his law, and governe thee with his Spirit, vntill he even bringeth thee to glory. Wherefore, if here be thy feare, comfort thy heart with that which the Apoſtle hath, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.28. the <hi>kingdome which thou haſt received</hi> (yea, haſt receiued alreadie) <hi>cannot be ſhaken.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, Doth the world powre contempt vpon thee?<note place="margin">4. Againſt contempt.</note> Art thou ſet at nought? canſt not haue that eſteeme amongſt men, which thou deſireſt and deſerveſt? I ſee little reaſon why this ſhould trouble thee; If it <hi>doth,</hi> here is comfort a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt IT alſo. Thou haſt a KING, whom thou art mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried vnto, yea, the KING of heaven and earth, which if the world knew (as it doth not, in which thou liueſt as a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and vnknowne vnto thee) it would be twice adviſed, ere it would dare ſo much as to haue any baſe thought, or contemptuous conceit of thee. But the world knowes none but her owne bratts; and thou (being of the of-ſpring of God<note n="*" place="margin">Act. 17.20.</note>, a member of <hi>Iehovahs</hi> familie, yea, a Spouſe made fit for the King himſelfe) ſhee knowes not thee, eſteemes not thee, any more then a foole doth a prize, put into his hand. Which contempt thou needeſt no more care for, and at which thou needeſt be no more caſt downe, then a Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans Wife, or a Princes Bride, when (being in a ſtrange Countrey, and vnknowne what her houſe and husband is) ſhee is either deſpiſed, or not eſteemed, according to her owne, and Spouſe his worth.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, Art thou not onely deſpiſed,<note place="margin">5. Againſt perſecution.</note> but alſo miſ-vſed in the world? Doe the perſecuters of the truth,<note n="c" place="margin">Ioh. 8.4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>who are of the Deuill their Father,</hi> goe about to wrong thee any kinde of way, in thy <hi>name, ſtate, perſon, life,</hi> or <hi>libertie.</hi> Here is thy
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:183854:12"/> Shield ſtill againſt diſcomfort. Thy husband is a <hi>King;</hi> and the time will come, when He will be knowne to be a <hi>King</hi> in the middeſt of thine enemies: Told I not thee, that he is<note n="d" place="margin">Dan. 12.1.</note> 
               <hi>Michaell the great Prince, that STANDETH for the people of God.</hi> Never louing husband ſtood more ſtout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for his Wife, then he hath ſtood and doth ſtand for his <hi>Well-beloued.</hi> Remember what he did for his ancient <hi>Iſrael,</hi> he reproved <hi>even Kings for their ſakes</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Pſ. 135.136.</note>. What is become of <hi>Og,</hi> the King of <hi>Baſan,</hi> and <hi>Sehon,</hi> King of the <hi>Amorites,</hi> who were great and mightie Princes? Are they not periſhed long agoe? Felt they not the heauines of his revengefull hand? And what is <hi>His hand ſhortned</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Iſa. 50.2.</note> now, that <hi>it cannot redeeme?</hi> or <hi>hath it no power to deliuer</hi> now as well as then? Yes, yes,<note n="g" place="margin">Iſa. 43.13.</note> 
               <hi>Before the day was I am he,</hi> (ſaith the LORD, ſpeaking of deliuering <hi>Iſraell</hi> from the handes of <hi>Babylon,</hi> and <hi>Babylon</hi> into the handes of <hi>Chaldea) and there is none can deliuer out of my hand. I will worke, and who ſhall let it?</hi> The Lord<note n="h" place="margin">Pſal. 110.5.6</note> 
               <hi>at thy right hand,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Dauid</hi> ſpeaking of <hi>Chriſt) ſhall ſtrike through Kings in the day of his wrath, and wound the heads ouer divers Countryes.</hi> Wherefore comfort thy ſelfe with theſe things, againſt trouble and perſecution, be it verball and <hi>Iſmaell</hi>-like, or reall and <hi>Ieſabell</hi>-like. For<note n="i" place="margin">Iſa. 43.15.</note> 
               <hi>I am</hi> (ſaith <hi>Chriſt) the Lord, your holy one, the Creator of Iſraell, your King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">6. Againſt the feare of death.</note>Laſtly, if <hi>Death</hi> be the King of <hi>terrors vnto thee:</hi> and thou doubteſt how thou ſhalt well-come, and away with <hi>this</hi> pale Sergeant when he comes with heavens fore-decreed Writt to arreſt thee, conſider, that this thy Chriſt, thy King, hath like a ſtout Commander, and vnvanquiſhable conquerour, charged this Sergeant to doe thee no hurt, trod this enemy in the dirt. He told thee he <hi>would</hi> doe it long <hi>before</hi> he came;<note n="k" place="margin">Hoſ. 13.14.</note> 
               <hi>Oh death, I will be thy death; O graue, I will be thy deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:</hi> according to his promiſe, he <hi>did doe</hi> it <hi>when</hi> he came; for<note n="l" place="margin">Col. 2.15.</note> 
               <hi>he hath ſpoyled principalities and powers, made a ſhew of them openly, and triumphed ouer them.</hi> And now, <hi>ſince he is gone into heauen,</hi> he hath left thee a Writt of aſſurance for it, enrolled in the Writings of that famous Doctor of the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles;</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:183854:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <note n="m" place="margin">1 Cor. 15 25.26.</note> 
               <hi>He muſt raigne, till he hath put all things vnder his feete; the laſt enemy that ſhall be deſtroyed is death.</hi> God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid then that this<note n="n" place="margin">Apoc. 6.7.</note> 
               <hi>Rider vpon the pale horſe,</hi> ſhould vpon the thought of his comming, either driue <hi>colour</hi> out of THY face, or <hi>courage</hi> out of THY heart. Let them feare death, who are out of Chriſt, who feare not this King. But as for thee, whom Chriſt hath linked to himſelfe, inſult thou ouer Death, as Death doth ouer the ſonnes of vnbeliefe,<note n="o" place="margin">1 Cor. 15<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 55.57.</note> 
               <hi>O death where is thy ſting? O graue where is thy victorie? Thankes be vnto God which giueth me victory through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord.</hi> Thus (I ſay) whatſoeuer the temptations be that trouble thee, the diſcomforts be that moleſt thee, ariſing either from the thought of the <hi>Deuils ſubtiltie,</hi> from the ſight of <hi>thine owne infirmitie,</hi> from <hi>ſuſpition of the want of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancie,</hi> from the <hi>contempt of neighbours, malice of enemies,</hi> or <hi>feare</hi> of <hi>death,</hi> tune but this Text with the voice of faith; in this Text, ſtrike but vpon <hi>this</hi> ſtring, harpe vpon <hi>this</hi> poynt with the finger of faith, <hi>(That Chriſt the Spouſe of the Church is a King;)</hi> and it will make ſuch Muſicke to thy ſoule, that like as (when <hi>Dauid</hi> played before <hi>Saul</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">1 Sam. 16<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>23.</note>) the <hi>wicked ſpirit</hi> went from him, ſo the <hi>troubled ſpirit</hi> will goe from thee, or els at leaſt that diſconſonant, and diſconſolate, noiſe betwixt <hi>faith</hi> and <hi>feare,</hi> to diſquiet thy conſcience, will be well qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified, and allayed. And ſo an end of the firſt poynt in the firſt part, let vs now ſet vpon the ſecond. Which is the royall proviſion that this royall perſon makes for his beloued Bride. For as he is a <hi>King,</hi> ſo he hath a <hi>Table,</hi> which <hi>Salomon</hi> here in my Text, calleth</p>
            <p>
               <hi>His Table.]</hi> Or (as ſome Tranſlations haue it) <hi>his repaſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The ſecond circumſtanc in the firſt part. The Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation.</note> Either of which readings (as the learned obſerue) the ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall will beare; but the former doe I follow.</p>
            <p>A Table, we know, in the proper, and natiue ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, is a frame of Wood, made to eate meate vpon, in which ſenſe we cannot take it here; nor yet for corporall meate, ſet vpon the Table to refreſh our bodies withall. For the Kingdome of God conſiſts neither in meates nor drinkes, as the Apoſtle ſheweth<note n="q" place="margin">Rom. 14.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>. We muſt therefore vnderſtand it
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:183854:13"/> 
               <hi>Metaphorically,</hi> and taking it ſo, I find varietie and diverſitie of Expoſitions amongſt <hi>Interpreters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b. Selomoh. Fol. <hi>117.</hi> fac. <hi>2</hi>
               </note>Some of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> whom <hi>Genebrard</hi> quoteth, ſ thinke it to be <hi>Sinai,</hi> the mount where the Law was deliuered to <hi>Moſes,</hi> and whence he deſcended in haſt when the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> erected and worſhipped the golden Calfe<note n="*" place="margin">Exod. 32.</note>: But this cannot be, becauſe it is a confining of this Text to the ſtate of the <hi>Iewiſh Synagogue</hi> at <hi>that</hi> time; when as yet the holy Ghoſt hath a larger ayme then at that.<note n="*" place="margin">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Brightman.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>One</hi> of our owne <hi>Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> thinkes it to be meant particularly of the <hi>Congregation of Iudah, Beniamin, Ephraim, &amp;c.</hi> who gathered themſelues together at <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> in the third moneth of the fifteenth yeare of the raigne of<note n="*" place="margin">2 Chron. 15.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.10.</note> 
               <hi>Aſa.</hi> This opinion I will not cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, yet I dare not ſubſcribe to it. For <hi>this</hi> alſo I take to be a ſetting too ſhort boundes to the Text. We will walke in a broader way, and allow larger limits (with other ſound and learned Writers). I know Saint <hi>Luke</hi> ſpeaketh of a<note n="*" place="margin">Luk 22.30.</note> Table, whereat Chriſt promiſed his Diſciples to ſit and eate; and that intimates the <hi>heauenly dainties</hi> they ſhould partake off in his <hi>Celeſtiall Paradiſe,</hi> the Kingdome of glory: which ſome<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>As</hi> Piſcator. Merc.</note> doe vnderſtand in this place. But with * others, I vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the Word and Sacraments, the dyet of the Church; wherewithall ſhee is fed and refreſhed ſpiritually, as men are corporally with meates and drinkes ſet vpon their Table; Neither doth this ſwerue from the <hi>Canon</hi> of <hi>Scripture:</hi> For is not the Kingdome of heauen, that is, the <hi>Word</hi> of the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> compared to a <hi>Supper,</hi> and to<note n="*" place="margin">Ioh. 6.27.</note> 
               <hi>Meate that periſheth not?</hi> And doth not the Apoſtle call the <hi>Sacrament</hi> of his laſt Supper, <hi>A Table</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 19.21.</note>? And whereas it is called here, <hi>HIS Table,</hi> it intimates, that HE is the Founder of this Feaſt. For who giueth the <hi>Word,</hi> the <hi>meate that endureth to eternall life,</hi> if not<note n="*" place="margin">Ioh. 6.21.</note> 
               <hi>the ſonne of man, whom the Father hath ſealed:</hi> And the Sacramentall Table, is called the <hi>Table of the LORD</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">In that place <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>recited out f the <hi>Corinths.</hi>
               </note>. I know indeed that Chriſt feedeth and feaſteth his Church with the internall graces, and comforts of his Spirit, but becauſe theſe follow to be conſidered off in His <hi>Sitting</hi> at this Table, therefore my intent is in this onely, to
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:183854:13"/> inſiſt on the externall diſhes of his Ordinances: And ſo make this the Doctrine.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>2</label> 
               <hi>That this King Chriſt, ſpreades a Table, and makes proviſion of the Word and Sacraments for his Church.</hi> This is one of the things which the Church ſetteth his greatneſſe forth by in my Text, in ſo much that now, with the Prophet <hi>Dauid,</hi> euery member of the ſame may ſay,<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 23.2.</note> 
               <hi>He maketh me to feed in greene paſtures.</hi> This is that which our <hi>Author</hi> ſignifieth els<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, when he brings in <hi>Chriſt</hi> in <hi>Wiſedomes</hi> name, not onely <hi>building</hi> her an <hi>houſe,</hi> and erecting a Church, but alſo making proviſion for the inhabitants of <hi>that</hi> houſe.<note n="b" place="margin">Pro. 9.2.</note> 
               <hi>Shee hath killed her victualls, ſhee hath mingled her wine, ſhee hath prepared her Table.</hi> In another place, he is brought in vnder the ſimilitude of a <hi>King,</hi> making a marriage dinner for his ſonne, and ſending forth his ſervants, the <hi>Miniſters</hi> of the <hi>Goſpell,</hi> to toll in gueſts, and tell them of the feaſt, both how bountifull it is, and how ready it is; <hi>Behold I haue prepared my dinner, my Oxen and my Fatlings are killed, and all things are ready</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Mat. 22.23.</note>. And that this feaſt is peculiarly provided for the Church, it is plaine in the ſame Parable<note n="d" place="margin">Verſes 5.10.</note>. Where we may ſee, that they which did ſet light by the ſeruants <hi>call,</hi> the Miniſters invitation (as they that are out of the Church doe) are threatned, not to taſte of that Supper; and onely thoſe are admitted as fit gueſts, whom the ſervants gathered out of the high wayes, whom the Miniſters of the Goſpell are made inſtruments to turne out of the high way of ſinne that lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to hell, through the Preaching of the Word. And who are they, but the Church? Herewith accordeth that of <hi>Eſay,</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Iſa. 25.6.</note> 
               <hi>Vpon this mountaine</hi> (meaning the Church) <hi>ſhall the Lord make a feaſt of fat things, a feaſt of Wines on the lees, of fat things full of marrow, of Wines on the lees well refined.</hi>
               <note place="margin">See <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.13.</note> So then deny it we cannot, (truth evincing it) that Chriſt hath a board ſpread for his Bride, richly furniſhed with ſuch ſpirituall dainties, as his Word and Sacraments be. And not without cauſe.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>
               </label> For why, he would haue his Church to grow, and thriue. And how grow? Two wayes in addition of mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:183854:14"/> in augmentation of graces; in multitude, and in mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. As therefore there is need of temporall foode for cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall growth, ſo of theſe ſpirituall Ordinances, for this ſpirituall growth.</p>
            <p>Firſt, He would haue it to grow in multitude: he would haue ſuch daily added to the Church, as are ordained to be ſaued, that like as <hi>Ephraim, Manaſſeh, Simeon</hi> and <hi>Beniamin</hi> fell from <hi>Iſrael</hi> vnto <hi>Aſa</hi> in abundance<note n="f" place="margin">2 Chron. 15.9.</note>; ſo there may be an acceſſe of Elect ones vnto him out of Satans hands, euery day more and more: and this cauſeth him to giue<note n="g" place="margin">Epheſ. 4.8.11.</note> 
               <hi>gifts vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to men, and to appoint ſome to be Prophets, ſome to be Apoſtles, ſome teachers, ſome Paſtors,</hi> with this Commiſſion,<note n="h" place="margin">Pſal. 50.5.</note> 
               <hi>Gather my Saints vnto me,</hi> for the<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> augmentation of my body, or addition of members therevnto.</p>
            <p>Secondly, He would haue his Church grow in meaſure, his Will is, that they which are added to the Church, ſhould haue grace augmented in their hearts, to be more <hi>fat, flouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing, and well liking in their age</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Pſal. 92.14.</note>; therefore he giues them the<note n="k" place="margin">1 Pet. 2.2.</note> 
               <hi>ſincere milke of the Word, that they may</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Dicimus qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem cibum om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem perficere ea quae aluntur, &amp;c. Dyoniſ. Areop. libro Epiſtol. fol. <hi>183.</hi> b.</note> 
               <hi>grow thereby.</hi> And giues he not alſo, not onely Baptiſme, as the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Initiation, but alſo, <hi>The Lords Supper</hi> for confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? Nay, by the adminiſtration of the one, and commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication at the other, doth he not ſeale vp remiſſion of ſins by his blood, to the conſcience of the beleever, for the ſtrengthening of his faith, increaſing of his loue, and bette<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of his obedience? So that the beleever may haue equall recourſe to Water in Baptiſme by meditation, Bread and Wine in the Lords Supper, by participation, to ſtay his faith on, to ſtrengthen his faith by, when either the malice of Sathan againſt him, or the reliques of vnbeliefe in him, ſhall raiſe any ſtormes of Deſpayre, to weaken the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> This being ſo, makes firſt of all againſt thoſe that care not for the Word, that contemne the Sacraments; vnto whom if the Miniſters cry in the Prophets termes, (<note n="l" place="margin">Iſa. 55.1.</note>
               <hi>Hoe, euery one come yee to the Waters, Come, buy, Wine and Milke with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out money, and without price,</hi>) they ſtoppe their eares againſt this <hi>call,</hi> make excuſes when they are bidden. One hath a
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:183854:14"/> Farme, another hath Oxen, another hath a Wife to pleaſe, another his Market to follow, another his Dice, another his Dogs; one cannot tarry in the Church while the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Baptiſme is adminiſtring; another is at oddes with his neighbour, and he cannot come to the Communion this yeare: And thus while one feedes vpon his pleaſures, another vpon his profits, another on his beaſtly and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vengefull luſts, the moſt hauing <hi>the broth of abhominable things in their veſſells</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Iſa. 65.4.</note>: This Table of <hi>Chriſts</hi> ſpreading is not ſo frequented, ſo regarded as it ought to be. Which contempt of Gods Ordinances, how worthy of reprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it is, this poynt declareth.</p>
            <p>Should ſome Prince, or Peere of a Kingdome,<note place="margin">A ſimilie.</note> make a great feaſt, furniſh his Table with all manner of dainties, yea, with ſuch coſtly delicates, as he feedeth his owne Queene, or Spouſe withall, and ſhould ſend forth his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, to invite gueſts to that feaſt, bidding to come who haue a liſt and well-come; and they that are thus bidden, ſhould make excuſe, and ſay; <hi>Alas, I haue a poore neighbour dwells by me, he hath invited me to a cold Sallet, or a diſh of herbes, in which regard I cannot come:</hi> were he not worthy to be Chronicled for a man without wiſedome? Might not his friends that loue him, well reproue him, for ſo careleſſe contemning a Princes call, and for preferring a diſh of Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons at a poore mans houſe, before the royall dainties of a great mans Table? they might very well: In like manner, may not they be as deſervedly ſhent, that ſhall preferre their earthly commodities, their fleſhly vanities, nay, their diabo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall impieties, before theſe ſupernaturall meates, and ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall bitts of the Word and Sacraments? Knoweſt thou of whoſe providing they are? art thou aware for whom they be prepared? are they not of the <hi>King, Chriſt?</hi> are they not for the Church? and can that be courſe fare, which is of ſo royall a preparer, and for ſo royall partakers? Verily, I may ſay to thee, as <hi>Elihu</hi> to <hi>Iob; Thy ſoule abhorreth daintie meate</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Iob 33.22.</note>. Let me expoſtulate a little with thee. Why can the doctrine of ſalvation, reliſh no better in thy pallate? How is it that the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:183854:15"/> Temple cannot hold thee, while the Childe is a Baptizing, but out thou muſt be running, as if it were an Ordinance concerned thee not? Why wilt thou chuſe rather to liue in wilfull malice with thy brother, then come and partake of the Lords Supper? Or wherefore art thou ſo ſeldome at it, when as thou maieſt ſo often haue it? If I were but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with thy maladie, I would apply a remedy, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the skill the Lord hath giuen me. Oh that I knew but what would get thee a better ſtomacke. If thou woul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt but provoke thy ſelfe, to vomit out the loue of the world, and of thy luſts, which like poyſonous crudities lie cloddering vpon thy ſtomacke, thou wouldeſt haue a better appetite; and this honey-combe would not be loathed by thee. But if thou beeſt paſt cure, then I haue done with thee; Goe thy wayes to thy huskes with the filthy Swine, to thy Veniſon with prophane <hi>Eſau;</hi> ſell thy birth-right for pottage; make excuſes; frame pretences to keepe thee from this Feaſt, yet I muſt be terrible in my wordes vnto thee, This <hi>King</hi> that makes this Banquet, will be wroth with thee,<note n="o" place="margin">Mat. 22.7.</note> and <hi>will ſend forth his Armies to deſtroy all ſuch as</hi> thou <hi>art.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> But now in the ſecond place, as for <hi>thee</hi> whom counſell is like (by the bleſſing of God) to prevaile withall, <hi>thee</hi> doe I perſwade, yea, earneſtly entreate, to frequent this Table, theſe Ordinances; neither thy age, ſex, condition, gifts, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward or outward, can excuſe thy abſence, or preiudice thy admittance. Hither thou <hi>muſt</hi> come, the King doth en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyne thee; hither thou <hi>maieſt</hi> come, he will accept thee; on theſe dainties thou <hi>maieſt</hi> feed, thy <hi>meanneſſe</hi> need be no impediment to thee; on theſe dainties thou <hi>muſt</hi> feed, thy <hi>greatneſſe</hi> can be no plea for the contrary. And for thy en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement hereto, know thou:</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Motiue</hi> 1.</note>Firſt, That Chriſt will ſet no <hi>baſe</hi> fare vpon his Board, for his beſt beloued Bride. If the Cookes doe marre it ſometimes in the dreſſing, (as Fryer-like Preachers doe, powdering the Word with the duſt of their owne inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; or as the Papiſt-like Prelates doe, adding creame, ſalt,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:183854:15"/> oyle, ſpittle, and the like traſh to Water in Baptiſme, and defiling the Lords Supper with that abhominable idoll of the Maſſe) yet the fault of that is not in the King, and <hi>Kezar</hi> of the Church. It is ſweet, it is excellent as it comes out of his handes,<note n="p" place="margin">Pſal<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 19.10.</note> ſweeter then the honey; of<note n="q" place="margin">Iob 28.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> price aboue Rubies; more to be deſired then gold, yea, then much fine gold: The coſtlieſt meates, the delectableſt drinkes that are, are but courſe in compariſon of it. God forbid then thou ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt abhorre it. Get thee to a good Cooke; abhorre the Maſſe; Baptize not thy Childe by a Seminary; and come but to this Table, ſtay but at this Table with a reverent re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard, and thou ſhalt finde that I tell thee no lie, ſuch ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ſhalt thou taſte, ſuch goodneſſe ſhalt thou ſee in the meaneſt of theſe Ordinances, euen by thine owne experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Conſider,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Motiue</hi> 2.</note> that it cannot be ſayd of this foode as <hi>Paul</hi> ſpake of indifferent meates and drinkes,<note n="r" place="margin">1 Cor. 8.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> 
               <hi>Neither if we eate, are we the better, nor if we eate not, are we the worſe.</hi> For thy admiſſion to the Church, if thou beeſt not yet cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, thy growing vp in grace, if thou beeſt converted, hangs vpon theſe Ordinances, as vpon ſecondary <hi>neceſſary</hi> helpes; Sayd I not before, this meate the Feaſt-maker provideth for the growth of the Church? How can the Church then grow in number one the more for thee, if thou deſpiſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſying? How canſt thou grow in meaſure, if thou careſt not for Preaching, makeſt no vſe of thy Baptiſme, proueſt a ſuperficiall and ſeldome gueſt at the Lords Table. As then thou tendereſt thy converſion to grace, thy confirmation in grace, ſo delight to be a gueſt at this Board which Chriſt ſpreadeth, take pleaſure to make vſe of thoſe Ordinances, which like ſpirituall proviſion, he hath made readie for his Church, in the Sermons which are Preached, in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which are adminiſtred amongſt vs; knowing that to be a truth, which a Father ſaith;<note n="ſ" place="margin">Chryſoſt. in Math hom. <hi>70.</hi> Cum ſpiritualia, v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cant, nulla occupationis excuſatio eſt.</note> 
               <hi>When ſpirituall things doe call vs, no excuſe of ſubordinate buſines will ſerue the turne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>3</label> Laſtly, Hath Chriſt made ſuch ſpirituall proviſion for his Church? then from hence, to their ſingular comfort,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:183854:16"/> may all Gods people, that are pinched with penury, aſſure themſelues, they ſhall neuer ſtarue, for want of needfull ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtenance. He that can giue the Kingdome, with the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe of <hi>that,</hi> can caſt all other outward neceſſaries vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vs: He that can and doth ſpread his Table for the ſoule, will prepare victualls for the bodie. He can provide a Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for his <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the Wilderneſſe. <hi>Dauids</hi> ſoule can he ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie with Marrow and Fatneſſe, in a dry and thirſtie Land<note n="t" place="margin">Pſal. 63.15.</note>. It is his honour to be franke and royall to his owne. And indeed he that hath bin ſo liberall as to giue himſelfe, muſt needs with himſelfe giue all things elſe. Thou complaineſt thou haſt not ſo full a purſe, ſo ouer-flowing a Table as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers haue; knoweſt thou not that Sheepe, when they goe vp to the belly in paſture, are in danger of rotting, and that barer Common were better for them? Thy Shepheard ſees it is better ſafetie for thy graces, to furniſh thee with a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diocritie, rather then fill thee with a ſuperfluitie of outward bleſſings. Tell me, haſt thou not proviſion for the ſoule, the Word, the Sacraments? If Yea; this is a<note n="u" place="margin">Gen. 43.34.</note> 
               <hi>Beniamins</hi> meſſe, fiue times better then thy brethrens meſſes, which haue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the world in ſtore for the time of life, and wrath in ſtore againſt the day of death. The fruition of the greater and better ſhould alwayes counteruaile the want of the leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer, and worſer. Browne bread and the Goſpell (ſaid M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Bradford</hi>) is good cheere. Say thou poore Chriſtian, Is not thy body as ſtrong to labour, and thy children as well liking as theirs that haue more abundance? thou canſt not deny it. Plucke vp a good heart then, and ſay with <hi>David;</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 23.1.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord is my feeder, therefore I ſhall not want. He lets not my ſoule ſtarue, therefore he will not let my body famiſh.</hi> Reſolue on this, I ſay. For it is a greater diſhonour to his bountie, then thou art aware off, to thinke that he will with-hold any needfull good thing <hi>from any that lead an holy, pure, and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right life</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Pſal. 84. <hi>vlt. ver.</hi>
               </note>.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The third circumſtance in the firſt part.</note>We haue now done with the ſecond thing, which the Church commendeth her husbands greatneſſe by. The laſt remaineth to be handled, which is his preſence and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:183854:16"/> reſidence with HER, implied by HIS <hi>Sitting at Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>While the King SITTETH at his Table, my Spike<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard ſendeth forth the ſmell thereof.</q>
            <p>THis circumſtance ſubdiuideth it ſelfe into two mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers. 1. The fruition the Church hath of Chriſts <hi>ſight</hi> and <hi>ſitting,</hi> couched vnder the terme of <hi>Sitting at Table.</hi> 2. The fruit Shee gets by it, and returneth for it, in the ſmell that her <hi>Spikenard</hi> ſendeth forth.</p>
            <p>We will ſet theſe ioynts together in the meaning, and not handle them a-part, becauſe they come vnder the ſame par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular head.</p>
            <q>While the King Sitteth at his Table, my Spikenard, &amp;c.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>Sitteth].</hi> The <hi>Rabbines,</hi> who (as I remembred before,<note place="margin">The Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation.</note> by <hi>King,</hi> vnderſtand <hi>Iehovah,</hi> and by <hi>Table,</hi> Mount <hi>Sinai</hi>) doe by <hi>Sitting at Table,</hi> take to be meant, the <hi>preſence</hi> or <hi>reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence</hi> of the Lord vpon that Mount with <hi>Moſes,</hi> when he delivered the Law vnto him. Others, referre it to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of<note n="y" place="margin">2 Chron. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> 
               <hi>Aſa,</hi> when he was in the middeſt of the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> congregated and gathered together, to make a Covenant with the Lord. But thou knoweſt (READER) I haue ſhunned theſe paths from the beginning. Others, expound it of the <hi>preſence</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> alluding to the preſence of <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> with his Bride, on the day of his marriage. And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt theſe, I finde ſome difference; one vnderſtanding his glorious<note n="z" place="margin">Piſcator. Dun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> fruitur gaudijs Caleſtibus. Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphora qualis. Mat. <hi>8.11.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>preſence</hi> in <hi>heauen,</hi> where he <hi>Sitteth,</hi> partaking of caeleſtiall ioyes:<note n="a" place="margin">Merc.</note> Another his gracious <hi>preſence</hi> with his Church in this world. Now that the <hi>preſence</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> is here ſignified, it is probable, yea, very probable: Becauſe a man cannot ſit at the ſame Table with another, but they muſt enioy the preſence of one another. But, whither his glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous preſence alone, or his gracious alone, or both be here meant, that's the queſtion. For mine owne part, albeit I dare not peremptorily exclude his preſence in glory, (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe whiles he is at Table with his Saints on earth, he is as
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:183854:17"/> well at repaſt with his Saints in heauen, and whiles the one hath his gracious preſence here, the other hath his glorious there) yet I doe rather encline to his preſence by grace here: And that for theſe reaſons.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The reaſons of the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the word, <hi>Sitting.</hi>
               </note>Firſt, Becauſe it is held generally, that this verſe is the ſpeech of the Church militant, ſpeaking and ſhewing what her husband is to her, and doth for her, euen in this life.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Becauſe of the end of her ſpeech, which is to invite the daughters of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> (that is) them that are without the Church, to come to Chriſt. But what ſtronger argument, to this purpoſe, could ſhee vſe, then one taken from the enioying of his preſence, as well by grace here, as in glory hereafter. For little courage to come to <hi>Chriſt</hi> would men haue, if ſo be there were no comfortable ſight and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of him to be had in this life, as well as in that which is to come. So then by <hi>Table,</hi> being vnderſtood (as hath beene alreadie ſhewed) the Word and Sacraments; by <hi>his Sitting at this Table,</hi> is meant <hi>his preſence by grace with his Church by his Ordinances.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>My Spikenard ſendeth forth the ſmell thereof.</q>
            <p>One of the <hi>Iewes</hi> by <hi>Spikenard</hi> here, vnderſtands the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip which the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> did yeeld vnto the golden Calfe; and by the <hi>ſmell</hi> that it caſt forth, the noyſome ſauour that this Idolatry ſent vp to the Lord, whiles he was with <hi>Moſes</hi> on the Mount, which was ſo ſtrong and loathſome, that the Lord was faine in haſt to ſend <hi>Moſes</hi> downe vnto them. Another, by <hi>Spikenard,</hi> vnderſtandes <hi>the couenant</hi> it ſelfe, which the Tribes made before the Lord, in the 15. yeare of <hi>Aſa's</hi> raigne: and by the <hi>ſending forth the ſmell thereof,</hi> he meaneth the ſounding forth of that<note n="b" place="margin">2 Chron. 15.14.</note> 
               <hi>Vow</hi> with a loud voice, with <hi>Trumpets</hi> and <hi>Cornets,</hi> and ſuch like Inſtruments of <hi>Muſicke.</hi> But letting theſe paſſe,<note n="c" place="margin">Ambroſ in Pſal. <hi>119.</hi> Nunc autem redolet fides: Ideo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> dicit Eccleſia: Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus mea dedit odorem ſuum.</note> others doe by <hi>Spikenard</hi> vnderſtand Faith alone;<note n="d" place="margin">P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſc.</note> others Good workes alone;<note n="e" place="margin">Mercer <hi>and</hi> Geneb.</note> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, both Faith and Good workes. This laſt iudgement I follow, in regard of the reſemblance betwixt <hi>Spikenard</hi> and Faith, betwixt <hi>Spikenard</hi> and Good workes.<note n="*" place="margin">How Faith reſembleth <hi>Spikenard.</hi>
               </note> Firſt, for the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:183854:17"/> reſemblance betwixt Faith and it. <hi>Spikenard</hi> is a very ſweete and fragrant herbe, with a tender roote, full of leaues vpon the top, of which eares ſpring forth, full of fruit; Of this herbe an ointment is made, (which it ſeemes was in much vſe in <hi>Salomons</hi> time) which hath a threefold, or rather foure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold vertue, to comfort the heart, to helpe againſt the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the ſtomacke, defects of the braine and<note n="f" place="margin">Dioſc. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> eyes. And is not faith much like.</p>
            <p>Firſt, It is a very ſweete and fragrant vertue, it perfumes whatſoever we doe, without which it is<note n="g" place="margin">Heb. 11.6.</note> 
               <hi>impoſſible to pleaſe God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, It hath a tender roote, it ſprings vp in a bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken heart, in a conſcience wounded, bruiſed, and prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red<note n="h" place="margin">Perk. Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſ.</note>.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, It comforteth the heart, by the apprehenſion, and application of the promiſes.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, It availeth againſt the diſeaſes of the ſtomacke, it keepeth from caſting vp the ſpirituall food, as<note n="i" place="margin">Dioſ. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Spikenard</hi> from caſting vp the corporall, it helpeth againſt carnall and earthly diſeaſes, it moderates the affections.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, It is full of leaues, he that hath it makes profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Religion.</p>
            <p>Neither is it, in the laſt place, void of fruit, for faith makes a man as well to practiſe as profeſſe.</p>
            <p>Now as Faith in <hi>All</hi> of <hi>theſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">How good Workes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble <hi>Spike<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard.</hi>
               </note> ſo Good workes in <hi>Some</hi> of <hi>theſe</hi> things are like to <hi>Spikenard</hi> alſo: and chiefely in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the comforting qualitie of it. For Good workes doe comfort occaſionally, not onely the hearts of the doers themſelues, as the example of <hi>Iob</hi> proueth (who drew com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort from his holy life, when he was almoſt at the doore of death,) but alſo the hearts of others, who deſire the glory of God, and credit of the Goſpell; as the fruits of loue in <hi>do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> and <hi>patience</hi> in ſuffering, amongſt the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> were a great refreſhing and crowne of <hi>reioycing</hi> to the holy Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, yea, made both <hi>Paul, Siluanus,</hi> and <hi>Timotheus, to glory of them in the Churches</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">2 Theſſ. 1.3.4.</note>. Thus we ſee, what is to be meant by <hi>Spikenard;</hi> ſo that <hi>[My Spikenard]</hi> is as much as, <hi>The
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:183854:18"/> Faith and Good workes of me the Church militant.</hi> Now in that ſhee ſpeakes of <hi>Sending forth the ſmell thereof,</hi> we muſt know that <hi>Salomon</hi> alludes to the cuſtome of his dayes, in the Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterne parts of the world, where the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> were, whoſe manner was at their Nuptialls and Banquetts, for the Brides and Wiues, to beſweeten themſelues with ſweet oyntments, whereof <hi>Spikenard</hi> was one, that they might ſavour all ouer their Boardes, to giue not onely other ſitters by, but alſo (and that chiefely too) their husbands content; and it ſeemes, the abuſe and exceſſe of this the Prophet <hi>Amos</hi> tax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth very ſharply;<note n="l" place="margin">Amos 6.4.6.</note> 
               <hi>Woe to them that eate the Lambes out of the Flocke, and the Calues out of the middeſt of the Stall, that drinke Wine in Bowles, and Annoynt themſelues with the chiefe Oynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi> It ſeemes (I ſay) that <hi>Salomon</hi> alludes to this, to note out vnto vs, that the Faith and Good workes of the Church, doe ſmell ſweetly in Chriſts noſtrills, and caſt forth a ſavour vnto others. Will you now, at length, haue the ſumme of all in a word? take it thus.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Paraphraſe.</note>
               <hi>So long as my Kingly husband, Chriſt Ieſus, is preſent in his Ordinances, with me the Church militant, the faith and good workes of my members, doe ſauour ſweetly before God, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst men.</hi> The poynts that offer themſelues hence to our conſideration, are theſe three.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That in his Word and Sacraments, Chriſt is preſent with his Church.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That whiles he is ſo preſent with her, ſhee ſendeth forth the ſauour of Faith and good Workes.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That they which haue ſound faith, and bring forth good fruit, may lawfully profeſſe, and ſpeake of the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Doct.</hi> 3. Chriſt is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent with his Church in his Ordinances.</note>TO beginne with the firſt; <hi>While the Church enioyeth the Word and Sacraments, ſhee enioyeth the preſence of her Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued.</hi> For as <hi>Table</hi> importes the proviſion he makes for her, ſo doth his <hi>Sitting at Table,</hi> his <hi>preſence with her.</hi> He deales not with his people as a man that invites gueſts to his houſe to a feaſt, who, when they are come goes his way from them, beares them no company; but as He bringeth them <hi>hither,</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:183854:18"/> ſo He is with them <hi>here. Where two or three are gathered to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in my name, I will be in the middeſt amongst them</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Mat. 18.20.</note>. In the Parable before cited, we reade, that the <hi>King came in to ſee the gueſts</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Mat. 22.11.</note>; not onely (as it is likely) to marke their carriage, but alſo to beare them company. It is the ſpeech of the Church, in the mouth of the Prophet;<note place="margin">Hoſ. 6.2.</note> 
               <hi>The third day we ſhall liue in his ſight.</hi> Where, by <hi>the third day,</hi> ſome vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, the time of the Goſpell, and, by <hi>liuing in his ſight,</hi> Chriſt his preſence in the Goſpell, with the Spouſes readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to heare his <hi>ſayings</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">Zarch. in Hoſ. ad loc. Praeſte eius dictis au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dientes. <hi>Ioh.</hi>
               </note>. Looke as Gods preſence was in <hi>Iſrael</hi> with the <hi>Arke,</hi> ſo is it amongſt his people, with his <hi>Word,</hi> and <hi>Sacraments; I am with you to the end of the world,</hi> as he told his Diſciples, and can he be abſent in his Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances?</p>
            <p>But here the onely Queſtion is,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Qu:</hi> 1. How Chriſt is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent in the Word. <hi>Anſw.</hi>
               </note> How he is preſent with his people in theſe Ordinances? <hi>How in the Word? How in Baptiſme? How in the Sacrament of the Lords Supper?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the firſt, follow but me in tracing out the <hi>Metaphor,</hi> and you ſhall haue ſatisfaction.</p>
            <p>A King ſits at Table with his Queene, not onely to feed with her, but alſo to carue to her, to conferre, and to be merry with her. So Chriſt is preſent with his owne, in the Preaching of the Word. 1. as a caruer, 2. as a conferrer, 3. as a comforter. Firſt, (I ſay) as a caruer, for doth not he proportion his Doctrine in the mouthes of his Miniſters, to the capacitie and neceſſitie of his hearers? Cutting ſuch a bit out of ſuch a Text, and ſuch an one out of another, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting his Stewards wiſely, and aptly to apply their ſtudies in private, their Sermons in publique, to the occaſions of their hearers? He carues reſolution to her in her doubts, confutation in her errors, correction for her diſorders, &amp;c. Secondly, doth he not in his Word familiarly confer with his Bride, reuealing his minde plainely to her in thoſe mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters that are myſteries to the world.<note place="margin">A ſimilie.</note> A man that ſits at the vpper end of the Table with his Wife, talkes in her eare, happily the reſt heare the ſound of his voice, but yet know not, conceiue not the ſcope of his ſpeech, ſhee onely vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:183854:19"/> his meaning, and is acquainted with his will; So, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probates heare the Word as well as the elect, but the elect haue Chriſt whiſpering that in <hi>their</hi> eare out of his Word, that the <hi>reprobate</hi> can neuer attaine vnto, though he goes as farre as a temporary faith can carry him, ſo that though <hi>both</hi> haue the ſound, yet but <hi>one</hi> hath the ſence, the ſence (I ſay) in a right apprehenſion of the meaning of it, in a liuely feeling of the operation of it. For (as<note n="p" place="margin">Zanch. Tom. <hi>5</hi> in Epiſt. ad E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſ. p. <hi>152.</hi> Verbum enim ſinceris auribus auditum, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>primitur in corde Electoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> per Chriſtum: b. e. per Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um Chriſti.</note> One ſayth) <hi>The Word which is heard with pure eares, doth take IM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PRESSION in the hearts of the ELECT alone, by Chriſt, or the ſpirit of Chriſt.</hi> Thirdly, Chriſt is preſent in the Preaching of the Word, as a comforter. For whiles the Doctrine of the free fauour of God in Chriſt, of reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with God by Chriſt, of the excellent priviledges of the faithfull, remiſſion of ſinnes, ſalvation in the heavens, &amp;c. is ſounded and preached, are not the ſoules of beleevers many times raviſhed, comforted, refreſhed, by the inuiſible working of the holy Spirit?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Qu:</hi> 2. How Chriſt is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme.</note> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> For the ſecond Queſtion, thus may we anſwere it, that Chriſt is not preſent in Baptiſme, to take away the roote of originall ſinne, as if it could not remaine in the partie Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized; nor to conferre inuiſible grace, ſimply by the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Water, as if grace were neceſſarily tyed to the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, and none could haue it, except they were Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, nor yet thirdly to imprint an indelible Character in the ſoule, that can neuer be blotted out, as the Schooles would haue it. He is not (I ſay) either of theſe wayes preſent in Baptiſme. But, firſt to <hi>ſeale</hi> vnto vs our admiſſion into the couenant of his grace, and communion with himſelfe, and with his Saints<note n="r" place="margin">Act. 2.39. Gal. 3.27.</note>: Secondly, to <hi>repreſent</hi> vnto vs, and <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentally</hi> to <hi>ſhow</hi> vs, by the outward waſhing of Water, the inward cleanſing of our ſoules by his blood, that is, by <hi>iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">Polan. Synt. l. <hi>6.</hi> c. <hi>55.</hi>
               </note>, and by his Spirit, that is, by <hi>ſanctification</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">Id. ibid. Ablutio per ſanguinem Chriſti, eſt iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtificatio. Ablutio per ſpiritum Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti eſt regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio.</note>. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to <hi>put vs in minde</hi> of our repentance, new obedience, cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, and care, to ſhow our ſelues his Souldiers, by warring and fighting againſt the Deuill, the world, and the fleſh. So then, you ſee, that three wayes Chriſt is preſent in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme.
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:183854:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> 1. As a ſealer of the mutuall couenant betwixt Him and his Church. 2. as a repreſenter of the benefits he will beſtow on his Church, if ſhee keepe <hi>her</hi> conditions. 3. as a remembrancer of the duties ſhee owes to him, if ſhee would haue him keepe <hi>his</hi> conditions.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, to anſwere the third Queſtion,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Qu:</hi> 3. How Chriſt is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent in the <hi>Euchariſt.</hi>
               </note> How Chriſt is preſent in the <hi>Lords Supper?</hi> We muſt know, that he is not there <hi>Tranſubſtantially,</hi> as though the Bread and Wine were turned into the body of Chriſt, fleſh, blood, and bones, as our adverſaries the Papiſts hold; nor yet <hi>Conſubſtantially,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Exiſtentia ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> abſconſione corporis inviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilis in, ſub, cum, pane.</note> by an exiſtence or hiding his inuiſible body, in, with, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Bread, as if there were no figure in the Sacrament, as the <hi>Vbiquitarians</hi> hold<note n="u" place="margin">Chemnit Har. Evang. cap. <hi>83.</hi> col. <hi>1586.</hi> At verò hinc in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre velle. Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go in Doctrina Sacramenti, propoſitio (panis eſt corpus me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um) etiam eſt figuratae, hoc verò abſurdiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; Chriſti ingenio prorſus contrarium eſt. Vide etiam. Col. <hi>1587. 1588.</hi>
               </note>; but <hi>theſe</hi> wayes firſt to keepe vs mindfull of his death, which he endured for vs, in which regard, ſome haue called the Lords Supper,<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Sacrificium.</note> 
               <hi>a Sacrifice of remembrance.</hi> Secondly, to <hi>ſtrengthen our faith,</hi> in the aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the continuance of his loue, and to ratifie, the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of our ſinnes, our title of adoption, our intereſt in grace, our right to glory, to our ſoules. Thirdly, <hi>to arme vs againſt Idolatry,</hi> that partaking of the Lords Table, wee may not communicate at the Table of Deuills<note n="¶" place="margin">1 Cor. 10.21.</note>. Fourthly, to <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue vs in the way of obedience.</hi> Fiftly, <hi>to aſſure vs of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of our bodies at the laſt day,</hi> according to Chriſts owne ſpeech;<note n="x" place="margin">Ioh. 6.54.</note> 
               <hi>He that eateth my fleſh, and drinketh my blood, hath eternall life, and I will raiſe him at the laſt day.</hi> And laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to ſignifie vnto vs, and aſcertaine vs of our vnion with himſelfe, as <hi>Paul</hi> declareth, when he ſayth; <hi>The cup of bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing which we bleſſe, is it not the communion of the bodie of Chriſt</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">1 Cor. 10.16.</note>. Thus we ſee, not onely THAT, but alſo HOVV Chriſt is preſent with his Church in his holy and ſacred Ordinances. Let vs now conſider, to what end the Doctrine ſerueth, and what vſes it affoordeth, which are divers.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> Firſt, It informeth vs of the reaſon, why Gods people doe ſo diligently frequent the houſe of God, are ſo often preſent at his Ordinances; (to wit) becauſe they meete their husband, their King, their Sauiour, in <hi>ſuch</hi> places, at <hi>ſuch</hi> exerciſes.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:183854:20"/>
            <p>If a poore man, comming to a great mans houſe, findes the Maſter of the houſe to bid him well come, to beare him company, to entertaine him with good cheere, merry talke, and kind invitations to come oftner; would you wonder to ſee that poore man euer and anon at that rich mans Table? So it is with the children of God. A great many marvaile at them, what they meane to run ſo to Sermons as they doe; <hi>Once a day</hi> (ſay they) <hi>cannot content them, but they muſt heare twice;</hi> (ſay they) <hi>the Saboth cannot ſuffice them, but they muſt out on the weeke day. If Baptiſme be adminiſtred, they will not out of the Church by any meanes; If there be a communion euery moneth, they muſt be at it euery time, as though once, or twice in a yeere, were not ſufficient, wee wonder at it.</hi> Doe you ſo? it is becauſe you know not, <hi>whom</hi> they ſee, <hi>whom</hi> they finde pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, <hi>whom</hi> they meete withall <hi>here.</hi> They ſee the <hi>King</hi> here, even the <hi>King</hi> of heauen and earth. And although they haue his preſence in their houſes, ſhops, fields, walkes, and cloſets, yet they know <hi>here,</hi> He is preſent after a <hi>ſpeciall</hi> and <hi>peculiar</hi> manner, to <hi>conferre</hi> with them about deepe ſecrets, to <hi>carue</hi> bitts to them, according to their neceſſities. If they be <hi>erroneous</hi> in their iudgements, they finde him here to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme them, if <hi>ſcrupulous</hi> in their conſciences, they find him here to reſolue them, if they be <hi>drowſie in his ſeruice,</hi> they finde him here to rowſe them, if <hi>fallen into any ſinne,</hi> they finde him here preſent to rayſe them, if <hi>heauie in their hearts,</hi> here he is to accheere them, if they <hi>haue miſtaken their way,</hi> here he is to direct them. In theſe Ordinances, they finde their faith ſtrengthened, the couenant of Gods grace ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, their vnion with Chriſt ratified, their aſſurance of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſevering in grace, of raiſing from death, and raigning in glory, confirmed; and what not? Marvaile you then, what they doe frequenting ſuch places, where the Word is Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, and the Sacraments adminiſtred?</p>
            <p>What wife that loues her husband, doth not delight dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to converſe with him at his Table? Marvaile therefore at <hi>thy ſelfe,</hi> rather that <hi>thou</hi> and <hi>thy companions</hi> take no more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in <hi>ſuch places,</hi> at <hi>ſuch exerciſes,</hi> then <hi>you</hi> doe: and ceaſe
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:183854:20"/> wondering at <hi>them,</hi> who come hither to be recreated, and accheered with the gracious preſence of their <hi>great Bride-grome.</hi> Albeit, I deny not, but ſome doe (as the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in Chriſts dayes did) follow him for the<note n="z" place="margin">Ioh. 6.</note> 
               <hi>loaues,</hi> ſome for his <hi>miracles,</hi> ſome for <hi>one</hi> corrupt end, ſome for <hi>another,</hi> yet there is an holy and choſen generation, who follow him in his Ordinances, becauſe they know he <hi>Sitteth at Table</hi> in the ſame, and doth communicate vnto them ſuch graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous glaunces of his countenance, as Reprobates are like ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to partake off.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> Secondly; Is Chriſt preſent with his Church in his Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances; What meane the Papiſts then to take vpon them ſo tedious a taske, as to runne to <hi>Compoſtella</hi> to ſee his holy coate (which they ſay is there, though no man knowes how it came there) and to <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> to viſit his Sepulchre? Oh folly to be pittied, if not to be derided. Thinke they to finde Chriſt in his coate, finde his preſence in the graue? Is this one of their meritorious actions? See Chriſtians, ſee their ſimplicitie. Chriſt ſits not <hi>there,</hi> is not <hi>ſo</hi> preſent <hi>there,</hi> as he is <hi>in</hi> his Church, and <hi>with</hi> his Church. If Chriſtians who goe but halfe a mile to heare a Sermon Preached vnto them, to be made partakers of the Sacrament, doe not make a better Pilgrimage then this is, and meete not with their well-beloued Spouſe, Chriſt, ſooner, then <hi>theſe ſimple delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded ſoules,</hi> by making ſuch <hi>ſuperſtitious</hi> Voyages can, then note me for a teacher of lyes?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>3</label> Thirdly, This poynt may be applyed by way of reproofe to a great number, who care neither how <hi>vnpreparedly</hi> they come <hi>to</hi> Gods publique Ordinances, nor how <hi>irreligiouſly</hi> they behaue themſelues <hi>at</hi> the ſame. A man may ſay (and ſay truely too) there is no Table of mortall man more ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken vp with vnmannerly gueſts, with rude, with vnciuill company, then this Table, whereat Chriſt <hi>ſitteth,</hi> and affor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth his preſence.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Concerning the comers to his <hi>Word,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Vnreuerent comers to the Word.</note> it would make a Chriſtian heart to bleed, to conſider what manner of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; and after what manner moſt people come to the Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:183854:21"/> of <hi>that.</hi> One comes with his <hi>eyes ſcarce open,</hi> cloſed vp with that excrementall moiſture of <hi>ignorance,</hi> which the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall ſleepe in ſinne breedeth, with an vnderſtanding ſo darkened, that let the King by his ſervants lay bitts before him, he cannot ſee them, Preach as plainely as they can, he cannot vnderſtand them; Another comes <hi>without his knife,</hi> and when he is at the Table here, his hand is in his Pocket, and ſo benummed, that he cannot pull it out, to take and cut the meate that is ſet before him, I meane he comes <hi>without faith,</hi> without will to beleeue the Word, without an heart to apply the ſame to his neceſſitie, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the nature of the doctrine which is deliuered. A third comes with <hi>the old Grecian diſeaſe,</hi> the <hi>Athenian itch</hi> in his <hi>eares,</hi> that except the Preacher doth amaze his hearers with ſtrange &amp; vncouth ſtraines, aboue the reach of plaine people, or tell of ſome ſtrange thing, he is not for their hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour; If he ſtriues with himſelfe to ſpeake to the capacitie of the meaneſt hearer, and to knocke vpon the conſcience of the wickedeſt liuer, in the plaine euidence and demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the ſpirit, as, that learned Doctor of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> Saint <hi>Paul</hi> did<note n="a" place="margin">1 Cor. 2.1.</note>, how neſtles he, how lookes he on the glaſſe? The itch doth ſo trouble him, his <hi>Athenian</hi> deſires doe ſo diſtemper him, that he thinkes euery quarter an houre till the plaine fellow hath done: and it may be, he will haue the manners (as the manner of ſome is) to riſe from the <hi>Board</hi> while the beſt diſh is a caruing, the beſt point in handling, which might doe him moſt good, if he would but ſtay and take it with him. A fourth comes with <hi>a dirtie face,</hi> and <hi>hands</hi> imbrued in blood, a drunkard, a ſwearer, a lyer, a deceiuer, an Vſurer, a mercileſſe oppreſſor, and <hi>knowne</hi> to be <hi>ſo,</hi> as <hi>manifeſtly</hi> as the dirt is to beſeene vpon the <hi>face,</hi> that it hath defiled, and <hi>blood</hi> on the <hi>handes</hi> (without a gloue) that are beſmeared with it. A fift ſort, come all vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced before (I had almoſt ſaid, with breſts layd out like Whores and <hi>Iezebells</hi>) but I am ſure, with breaſts open, with hearts naked, vnarmed, vnfenced againſt the leaſt aſſault, for want of due preparation; inſomuch, that if the <hi>Deuill</hi>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:183854:21"/> doth but ſhoot the dart of <hi>pleaſure,</hi> the <hi>world</hi> of <hi>vaine pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit,</hi> and the <hi>fleſh</hi> play <hi>its</hi> part, while the Miniſter is ſpeaking and they hearing, they are ſo ſtricken, ſo intoxicated, ſo vainely buſied, that they get no more good to their ſoules, then <hi>they</hi> to their bodies, who, ſitting at a Kings Table, doe ſo dreame of honours and preferments, which ſhall <hi>neuer</hi> be, that they minde nothing leſſe then the bits that are car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued them, and the meate which is before them, and ſo riſe without taſting one bit of the feaſt. A ſixt comes <hi>without his girdle,</hi> without <hi>ſinceritie,</hi> hypocritically, formally, for faſhion, company, and cuſtome. A ſeaventh commeth in the <hi>Deuills habite</hi> (if the Deuill hath any habite) in a ſtrange dreſſe, <hi>proud</hi> like the Deuill, and <hi>craftie</hi> like the Deuill. So <hi>proud,</hi> that he thinkes, he knowes as much as any can teach him; and therefore if the Preacher trips a little, and doth not carry his matter ſmoothly and Scholler-like before him (as all cannot, for all haue not an equall gift of Art and vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terance) he laughs in his ſleeue; or elſe ſo <hi>craftie,</hi> that he comes to catch the Miniſter, as the <hi>Scribes</hi> to trap our <hi>Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our</hi> and entangle him in his talke, not with a ſimple, and honeſt heart, to learne Gods will, and to haue a ſight of Chriſt, to ſupply the neceſſitie of his ſoule. And laſtly, who amongſt vs all doe not come many times with <hi>dirtie feete,</hi> with impure affections, into Gods Sanctuary, bringing a great deale of worldlineſſe, a great deale of drowſineſſe with vs. And albeit, we haue ſmarted for it (in being ſent away from many a Sermon, without the ſweet bits we were wont to haue, as a iuſt deſert of our negligence to prepare our ſelues) yet we haue not ſo ſhaken off our ſlightneſſe of preparation as we ſhould; <hi>Who, who</hi> of vs (I ſay) fayle not this way? If our <hi>husband</hi> were not extraordinarily in loue with vs, and willing ſometimes to beare with vs in our <hi>night-attire,</hi> as well as to reſpect vs in our <hi>handſomer dreſſe,</hi> he might euen ſay to vs that are deareſt vnto him; <hi>What doe you here in my preſence at my Word, ſo diſordered, ſo diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered, ſo vnprepared?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:183854:22"/>
            <p>As thus many come vnmannerly to his <hi>Word,</hi> ſo as many come as rudely <hi>to,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Irreuerence and irreligion at Baptiſme taxed.</note> and carry themſelues as irreverently <hi>at</hi> his <hi>Sacraments.</hi> How many ſimple ſoules bring their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> ſcarce knowing <hi>wherefore</hi> Baptiſme ſerues, <hi>what vſe</hi> it ought to be off to themſelues, what vſe in time it may be off to their littles ones? How many are preſent at <hi>that</hi> Sacrament, when it is adminiſtred, who neither <hi>can,</hi> nor <hi>care to</hi> meditate vpon ſuch things, as <hi>then</hi> and <hi>there,</hi> are to be thought vpon: their <hi>eyes</hi> are ſo taken vp with <hi>gazing,</hi> their <hi>tongues</hi> ſometimes with <hi>talking</hi> with thoſe that ſit next them, and their <hi>hearts</hi> with ſuch <hi>wandering thoughts,</hi> that there is no roome for <hi>diuiner</hi> meditations, ſuiting the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, about the Vow made in Baptiſme, about the benefits offred in Baptiſme, and the ends of Baptiſme; no faith, no prayers ſet a worke for the good of the partie Baptized, and the like.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">3. Abuſe of the Lords Supper.</note>And laſtly, for the Lords Supper, how many come to that, who are partakers at the Table of Devills. It is lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to conſider, what ignorant, vnbeleeuing, irrepentant, diſobedient Communicants, thruſt themſelues vpon this Ordinance, that haue neither skill, nor conſcience, to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine and prepare themſelues before receiuing; that know not what to doe, how to behaue themſelues in the time of receiuing, not how to ſet their <hi>faith</hi> a worke towards <hi>God,</hi> in the apprehenſion of <hi>his</hi> loue, not how to ſet their <hi>loue</hi> a-worke towards <hi>beleevers,</hi> whom they communicate withall, that know not <hi>what</hi> to doe <hi>after</hi> receiuing; frequenting this feaſt for cuſtome and faſhion, partaking after a groſſe and carnall manner, not diſcerning the Lords body, not making any difference betwixt <hi>common</hi> Bread, and <hi>common</hi> Wine, and <hi>Sacramentall.</hi> Well then, (beloued) this irreuerent and irreligious frequenting of Gods publique, ſacred, Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, by ſuch multitudes of people, duely conſidered, can a word of reproofe come out of ſeaſon? I am ſure, here wants no ground for it in the Doctrine wee haue now in hand.</p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:183854:22"/>
            <p>Are we well adviſed, <hi>who</hi> is here? <hi>who</hi> trow we is preſent at the <hi>Word,</hi> at the <hi>Sacraments?</hi> Is not the <hi>King</hi> himſelfe? And what King? Why, the King of glory, the great mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificent <hi>Spouſe,</hi> and <hi>Bride-grome</hi> of the Church; His <hi>royall,</hi> his <hi>ſtately,</hi> his <hi>honourable,</hi> his <hi>comfortable</hi> preſence is <hi>there; There</hi> he <hi>ſits,</hi> and <hi>there</hi> he <hi>communicates</hi> what euer he ſees needfull for his <hi>Brides</hi> ſalvation. Shall wee then dare to come ſo <hi>rudely,</hi> not feare to goe ſo <hi>irreligiouſly</hi> into HIS preſence? Is <hi>he</hi> preſent while his Miniſters Preach? and ſhall we come to the <hi>Word</hi> with ſleepie <hi>eyes,</hi> itching <hi>eares,</hi> dirtie <hi>faces,</hi> proud <hi>conceits of our owne knowledge, craftie in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions,</hi> to catch the Preacher, <hi>naked hearts,</hi> without grace to <hi>beleeue,</hi> without will to <hi>apply</hi> the things that are taught vs? Come we <hi>hither</hi> like <hi>hypocrites?</hi> come <hi>hither</hi> to <hi>ſcoffe,</hi> to <hi>ſleepe,</hi> to <hi>laugh?</hi> Is Chriſt preſent in <hi>Baptiſme?</hi> and ſhall wee preſume to neglect all <hi>meditation</hi> for <hi>our ſelues,</hi> all <hi>inuocation</hi> for <hi>the partie Baptized?</hi> Is <hi>he</hi> laſtly, preſent in the <hi>Euchariſt?</hi> And dare wee to goe to <hi>that</hi> feaſt without our wedding gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, without knowledge, faith, repentance, obedience, and loue? dare we goe to <hi>that</hi> without any due examination of our ſoules before hand, concerning the forenamed gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, whither we haue them or no? dare wee receiue groſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and carnally at <hi>that,</hi> and not ſhew our ſelues thankefull, by our new obedience, after we haue eaten of this Supper? Will <hi>theſe</hi> things (thinke wee) be well taken at our hands? Is it not greatly to the diſhonour of the King? An earthly King will not endure it, that any of HIS gueſts ſhould come with dirtie ſhooes into HIS DINING ROOME, leſſe can he abide, that they ſhould come vnhandſomely, vncomely to his owne TABLE. Doth not <hi>this heauenly King</hi> ſtand as much vpon his honour as an <hi>earthly?</hi> He doth. Oh folly to be reproved, oh impudency to be condemned <hi>then,</hi> to goe ſo <hi>vnpreparedly to,</hi> to be ſo <hi>vnreuerent at,</hi> the Preaching of the <hi>Word,</hi> and partaking of the <hi>Sacraments,</hi> which is the <hi>Table</hi> whereat <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſitteth. Verily, if this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke availes not with vs, to humble vs for the diſhonour thus offered to this <hi>Sitter</hi> at this <hi>Board</hi> with his Church,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:183854:23"/> wee may be ſure he will deale with vs, as the King in the Goſpell did with him whom he found at the feaſt without a wedding garment: <hi>Binde vs hand and foote, and caſt vs into vtter darkeneſſe, where is weeping, and wayling, and gnaſhing of teeth</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Mat. 22.</note>.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>4</label> That I may therefore in the fourth place (and not vnfitly) ſubioyne a word of Exhortation, let the thought of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of Chriſt in theſe Ordinances, ſtirre vs vp to that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence and preparation, that the former reproued number doe want. Be wee to goe but to a feaſt at an ordinary <hi>Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> houſe, if we know the maſter of the family will beare vs company at it, wee are very carefull to bruſh our gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, to robe our ſelues with our holi-day cloathes, to put on cleane linnen, to waſh our face, eyes, and handes, to ſcoure and ſharpen our kniues, that ſo, for want of hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomneſſe in our attire, or by meanes of hackling our meate with blunt kniues, we may neither offend the gueſts that ſit with vs, nor grieue the maſter that bad vs, nor ſhame our ſelues; The like <hi>ſpirituall</hi> care let there be in vs to fit our ſelues when wee come to <hi>Wiſedomes</hi> dainties. When the <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites</hi> were to haue the Lord to <hi>deſcend</hi> amongſt them on Mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> I reade<note n="c" place="margin">Exod. 9.10.</note> 
               <hi>they were to waſh their cloathes, and ſanctifie themſelues. Their</hi> courſe muſt wee imitate when we aſcend to Gods Mount, and goe vp to <hi>his</hi> houſe (where he is preſent) to heare his Word, or receiue the Sacraments. We muſt be cleanſed, and ſanctified, that ſo when wee are <hi>there,</hi> we may giue him the honour of his holy preſence, and neither diſhonour him, nor diſgrace our ſelues.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>4</label> WEE will now proceed to the ſecond poynt, <hi>That while Chriſt is preſent with his Church in his Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, ſhee ſendeth forth the ſauour of Faith and good Workes.</hi> Compare a few places of Scripture together, and you ſhall ſee this to be very firme. In the <hi>Acts</hi> of the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> wee may reade, that Chriſt had beene preſent by the Miniſtry of <hi>Paul</hi> at <hi>Phillippi</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Act. 16.14.</note>, at <hi>Theſſalonica</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Act. 17.2.</note>, at <hi>Rome</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Act. 28.31.</note>. And Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in his writings vnto the Saints, in <hi>theſe</hi> places, ſpeakes
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:183854:23"/> of their <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>good Workes</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Rom. 1.8. Phil. 1.7.9.16.11. 1 Theſ. 1.7.8.</note>, which like a precious oynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, did diffuſe themſelues in their Odour ouer the world.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> I propound this (in the firſt place) for a rule of tryall, whereby to examine our ſelues, whither we be members of the true Church, yea or no. This great Bridegrome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, Chriſt Ieſus, hath ſpread a Table amongſt vs, and a plentifull one too. But, haue wee Faith? What are our fruits? Wee heare much, wee pray oft, wee frequent the Table of the Lord, wee diſcourſe many times; but are all theſe perfumed with beleeuing? Doe wee endeuour ſo to walke, that our Faith may be ſpoken off; and that through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the whole courſe of our liues, wee may ſend forth a ſweete odour to refreſh the noſtrills of the godly, though the wicked (who can thinke well neither of the wayes, nor workers of righteouſneſſe) be offended with the ſame? If yea, then <hi>Chriſt</hi> by his grace hath beene preſent with vs in his Ordinances, hath contracted vs vnto himſelfe, and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen himſelfe as an <hi>husband</hi> vnto vs, betwixt <hi>whom</hi> and <hi>vs,</hi> all the powers of darkeneſſe are not able to force a divorce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. But if otherwiſe; though wee haue beene neuer ſo oft at this Bride-gromes Table, heard hundreths of Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, oft communicated at the Supper of the Lord, yet we are but onely <hi>viſible</hi> members of the <hi>outward</hi> aſſemblyes, no <hi>ſpirituall</hi> limmes of the <hi>miſticall</hi> body.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> Therefore, ſecondly, this doth notably confound the foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh conceit of all them, who brag that Chriſt is <hi>their</hi> hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, and <hi>they</hi> be betrothed vnto <hi>him,</hi> and yet are nothing, but full of <hi>infidelitie,</hi> and <hi>impietie,</hi> of <hi>vnfaithfulneſſe,</hi> and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fruitfulneſſe in their <hi>hearts,</hi> in their <hi>liues.</hi> Our dayes afford ſtore of ſuch, in whoſe veſſels, there is not one dramme of <hi>Spikenard,</hi> to caſt forth any ſweete ſauour, either to GOD, or godly men, but rather (with the people in <hi>Ioels</hi> time<note n="h" place="margin">Ioel 2.20.</note>) <hi>their ſtinke goes vp</hi> (into the noſtrils of God) <hi>and their worme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood ſends forth the bitterneſſe thereof:</hi> The ſtinke of their ſinnes diffuſeth it ſelfe to the <hi>offending</hi> of the children of <hi>God,</hi> to the <hi>infecting</hi> of the children of <hi>men.</hi> A good man can
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:183854:24"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:183854:24"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:183854:25"/> ſcarce in any corner auoyde the ſmell of their impious and vnrighteous fruits, of their lies, ſlaunders, blaſphemies, ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baldries, and other idle ſpeeches; but ſhall be compelled to ſent them in euery place, as ſtrong, as noyſome, as Brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone; to force ſighes from his heart, and teares from his eyes. And how odiouſly their VNBELIEFE doth affect the KINGS ſmell, their diſtruſt in Gods providence, their diſcontentedneſſe in proſperitie, their impatience in adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie, ſenſeleſneſſe <hi>of,</hi> and vtter careleſneſſe <hi>for,</hi> the comforts of the Spirit, doe euidently and woefully declare; And yet theſe people (forſooth) eſteeme themſelues to be the Bride of Chriſt. But to conſider, how they are deceiued, it pitties my heart. What? know they <hi>not,</hi> ſee they <hi>not,</hi> that Chriſt his Bride is not (while her husband ſits at Table) without her <hi>perfume</hi> to pleaſe <hi>him,</hi> and <hi>affect</hi> the <hi>virgins</hi> that be her fellowes? Now alas, theſe vaine-boaſters, are as emptie of this perfume as the fooliſh Virgins lampes were of oyle. They haue nothing but the oyntments of Harlots in their Boxes (their ſoules I meane) and about their bodies. And dare they challenge Chriſt for their Spouſe? As though he will linke himſelfe with <hi>ſuch?</hi> No, no. Let them with <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabas</hi> get to be full of <hi>faith</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Act. 11.24.</note>, and with <hi>Dorcas</hi> to be full of <hi>good Workes</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Act. 9.36.</note>, that God and man may ſmell the ſauour of their <hi>Spikenard,</hi> and <hi>then</hi> they may be beleeved, when they affirme themſelues to belong to Chriſt; but while <hi>then,</hi> they doe but flatter themſelues, and deceiue others.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>5</label> LAſtly, Obſerue, that <hi>Chriſtians may ſometimes lawfully ſpeake of their owne faith and good workes.</hi> The Church had <hi>Spikenard,</hi> and here ſhee ſpeakes of it, and of the ſweet ſmell it caſt forth. How oft doth <hi>Dauid</hi> ſpeake of his faith, and his good fruits, in the Booke of the <hi>Pſalmes,</hi> ſometimes reporting how he truſted in God<note n="l" place="margin">Pſal 64.</note>, ſometimes how he pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vnto him<note n="m" place="margin">Pſal. 3.4.34.4.</note>, ſometimes how he confeſſed his ſinnes vnto him<note n="n" place="margin">Pſal. 32.5.</note>, ſometimes how he loued him<note n="o" place="margin">Pſal. 116.1.</note>, ſometimes how he delighted in the Saints<note n="p" place="margin">Pſal. 16.3.</note>, ſometimes how he pittied his very enemies<note n="q" place="margin">Pſal. 35.14.</note>, ſometimes he ſpeakes of his vpright walking<note n="r" place="margin">Pſal. 18.23.</note>,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:183854:25"/> ſometimes of his holy talking<note n="ſ" place="margin">Pſal. 39.1.</note>, ſometimes of his zeale for Gods glory<note n="t" place="margin">Pſ. 119.139.</note>, &amp;c. Thus alſo did <hi>Iob</hi>
               <note n="u" place="margin">Iob 29. c. 31.</note>, <hi>Ezekiah</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Iſa. 38.3.</note>, <hi>Paul</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">2 Tim. 4.7.</note>, and others of the Worthies', whom the Scripture recordeth. And good cauſe why.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>1</label> For, firſt, God receiues much honour when wee ſpeake of the graces, which he beſtoweth vpon vs. Hence it is that wee ſhall finde <hi>Dauid,</hi> which reported ſo much of his owne graces, euer and anon, profeſſing his reſolution, to ſound forth the Lords prayſes.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>2</label> Secondly, ſometimes the wicked will rayſe ſlaunders of the godly, as though they were a great deale worſe then they are: and therefore to cleere themſelues from thoſe reproches, and ſo to vindicate the Goſpell from diſgrace, they <hi>may,</hi> yea, and they <hi>muſt</hi> make profeſſion of their integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and faith. What was it which moued <hi>Paul,</hi> to ſpeake ſo of his honeſtie, as he did; <hi>Wee haue renounced the hidden things of diſhoneſtie, not walking in craftineſſe, nor handling the Word of God deceitfully.</hi> 2 Cor. 4.2. But this, that (as it ſeemes) in the former Chapter, certaine falſe Apoſtles had ſlaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him to be a vaine-glorious fellow? Which imputation, to free himſelfe from, he ſpake ſo of his owne ſinceritie as he did.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>3</label> Thirdly, there are many occaſions giuen vnto Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, to haue hard conceits of their brethren, partly, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of ſome infirmities they <hi>ſee in</hi> them, partly, by reaſon of ſome troubles that <hi>fall vpon</hi> them. And therefore it is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and ſometimes needfull for them, to ſpeake of the good things that God hath wrought in them. If you aske, wherefore <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeakes to <hi>Timothy</hi> of his keeping the faith, and fighting a good <hi>fight</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">2 Tim 4.7.</note>,<note n="b" place="margin">Polan. Synt. Lib. 9. c. 8. Pag. 597.</note> One anſwereth it, becauſe the preſent trouble which he was in, by the meanes of <hi>Nero,</hi> might occaſion <hi>Timothy</hi> his Scholler, and others which had beene his hearers, to queſtion the foundneſſe of his faith, and honeſtie, which was ſo rewarded wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h affliction, and which faith of his was not like to procure ſuch temporall deliuerances at the hands of God, as formerly it had done. So then, partly, that Beleeuers may honour their God,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:183854:26"/> partly, free themſelues from euill reproches caſt vpon them by the wicked, and partly, prevent vncharitable conceits of themſelues in their godly brethren, they may lawfully ſpeake of their owne <hi>Spikenard,</hi> of that Faith and thoſe good Workes which the Lord hath beſweetned, both their hearts, and their lines withall.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> The conſideration of this, giues me iuſt occaſion, 1. to finde fault with thoſe Chriſtians which will euer be talking of their infirmities, that they haue no <hi>grace,</hi> no <hi>faith,</hi> no <hi>good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> at all in them. And yet their conſciences can tell them that ſuch and ſuch things the Lord hath inwardly ingrafted in them, ſuch and ſuch fruits the Lord hath enabled them outwardly to bring forth in their liues. They know that at ſuch and ſuch a Sermon, the Lord ſo and ſo affected their hearts, at ſuch a time gaue them victory ouer ſuch a temptation, at ſuch a time enabled them ſo and ſo to pray, yea, ſo and ſo anſwered their prayers, to teſtifie the accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blenes of the ſame; At other times, ſo and ſo accheered them with the aſſurance of his loue, ſo and ſo enliued them in the performance of ſuch and ſuch duties; yet becauſe (forſooth) it is not alwayes alike with them, and the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill tells them, they are diſſemblers, they cry out, <hi>I am an hypocrite, a naughtie packe, a wicked creature, nothing but euill lodgeth in me, no whit of goodneſſe dwell; in mee, I haue no faith, I haue no zeale, I haue no ſoundneſſe, no honeſtie, &amp;c.</hi> Is <hi>this</hi> to honour God <hi>with,</hi> and <hi>for,</hi> the good things he hath done <hi>for</hi> thee? wrought <hi>in</hi> thee? Nay, rather is it not to diſhonour him, in that thou doeſt not take notice of his graces, which he hath giuen thee? <hi>This</hi> is enough to expoſe the Goſpell to diſgrace amongſt the enemies of the truth. <hi>This</hi> is enough to make Chriſtians themſelues thinke more hardly of thee then there is cauſe. For, when as thou art ſo peremptory in it, that <hi>thou art an hypocrite, a varlet, a wretch.</hi> What will the world ſay of thee, and ſuch as make profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with thee? Even THIS; <hi>See, ſee, what arrant hypocrites theſe Goſpellers are, their owne conſciences accuſe them, their owne mouths condemne them, there is neuer an one of them ALL
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:183854:26"/> good.</hi> Thou art much too blame then, whoſoeuer thou art, that art ſo readie to take part with the Deuill againſt <hi>thy ſelfe,</hi> when yet the Lord in mercy, hath annoynted thy ſoule with the <hi>Spikenard</hi> of heaven, when both thy <hi>faith</hi> and <hi>inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gritie of life,</hi> haue ſent forth their ſweet ſauour to <hi>God,</hi> and to <hi>men?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> Let me perſwade thee to ſtriue againſt this euill, to <hi>take notice</hi> of, and (when God may haue any glory, others any good by it) <hi>make report,</hi> of what the Lord hath done for thy ſoule. Thou <hi>mayſt</hi> lawfully doe it, yea, (and if need require) thou <hi>must</hi> doe it. Yet with this caution, avoyding pride as much as may be. Not <hi>vaine-gloriouſly,</hi> as <hi>Peter</hi> did, when he ſayd, <hi>Maſter wee haue forſaken all, and followed thee, what therefore ſhall be giuen vs</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Mat. 19.37.</note>? For <hi>this</hi> is a thing God would be diſpleaſed with, and it is the propertie of worldlings and wicked ones ſo to ſpeake, <hi>viz.</hi> of that which indeed they <hi>haue</hi> not, and <hi>doe</hi> not.</p>
            <p>But firſt in humilitie, as acknowledging all to come from God.</p>
            <p>Secondly, with a deſire to vindicate the Goſpell from diſgrace, when euill mouthes falſely doe reproch thee.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, with a deſire to reioyce the hearts of thy godly brethren.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, to draw on others to a loue of <hi>that</hi> Word, whereby God hath wrought ſuch good in thee.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, to cleere thine owne <hi>innocency,</hi> when that is called into queſtion.</p>
            <p>After this manner, and to theſe ends thou mayeſt make profeſſion of thy graces; and with the Church. thy Mother here, tell it abroad to others; <hi>My Spikenard ſendeth forth the ſmell thereof.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:183854:27"/>
            <head>MYSTICALL MYRRHE.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The ſecond generall part of the Text.</note>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>OW commending to GODS bleſſing what hath beene ſpoken, touching the Commendation which the <hi>Bride</hi> giues her <hi>Spouſe</hi> from HIS <hi>Greatneſſe,</hi> I proceed to the prayſe of HIS <hi>goodneſſe,</hi> or <hi>ſweetneſſe</hi> in the next words.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Verſ. 12.</bibl>A bundle of Myrrhe is my well beloued vnto me, he ſhall lie <hi>(or lodge)</hi> all night betwixt my breaſts.</q>
            <p>IN which words, we haue two things to conſider, 1. What this ſweetneſſe <hi>is</hi> for the ſubiect matter. 2. What this ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe <hi>worketh</hi> for the ſubſequent effect. The <hi>thing it ſelfe</hi> is a <hi>bundle of Myrrhe,</hi> in the former part of the verſe; <hi>A bun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle of Myrrhe is my well-beloued vnto mee.</hi> The following ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect that it <hi>worketh,</hi> is a reſolution of the Church, to keepe this <hi>ſweetneſſe,</hi> in the clauſe of the Verſe; <hi>He ſhall lodge all night betwixt my breaſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let vs ſet vpon the firſt; <hi>A bundle of Myrrhe is my well be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued vnto me.</hi> Theſe words would well admit of a ſubdiui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, if it were needfull. But an Interpretation will ſerue our turne well enough: that therefore the kernell may appeare, let vs breake the ſhell by giuing the ſenſe.</p>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:183854:27"/>
            <p>
               <hi>That</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">R. Selo.</note> Author,<note place="margin">Interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> who expounds the former Verſe by the ſinne of <hi>Iſraell,</hi> in <hi>erecting,</hi> and <hi>worſhipping</hi> the golden calfe, and by the <hi>diſpleaſure</hi> that <hi>Iehovah</hi> conceiued at it, doth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound theſe words, by the Lords pacification, or being plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with <hi>Iſraell</hi> after this their ſinne. As imagining the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation of <hi>Iſraell</hi> to ſpeake thus; <hi>Though I the Synagogue of the Iſraelites, did caſt forth a ſtinking ſmell to the Lord by my I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry, in worſhipping the Golden calfe, yet NOW he is appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with me, become ſweet and gracious vnto mee, whereof a bun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle of Myrrhe is a ſymbole and ſigne:</hi> But this Expoſition is too Iewiſh.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>He</hi> that applyes the former Verſe to the times of King <hi>Aſa,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Brig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>stm.</note> and to the Vow that the Tribes made in the 15. yeare of his Raigne, doth apply theſe words to the times of <hi>Ieho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaphat, Aſa's</hi> ſucceſſor, according to the ſtorie written 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 17.7.8.9. &amp;c. And by the <hi>bundle of Myrrhe,</hi> he vnderſtands, the ſweetneſſe of knowledge, which abounded in the dayes of <hi>Iehoſaphat,</hi> by the care which <hi>that</hi> good <hi>King</hi> had to ſend Prieſts and Levites, with the booke of the <hi>Law,</hi> through the Tribes of <hi>Iudah,</hi> and <hi>Beniamin;</hi> as though <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> by the ſpirit of Propheſie ſhould foreſhew the <hi>Iſraeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh</hi> Church in <hi>Iehoſaphats</hi> time, to ſpeake thus to the prayſe of God;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the dayes of Aſa, I made a vow vnto thee, to ſerue thee, and for ſuch a King as HE was my Spikenard of Religion cast forth a ſmell vnto thee: But now thou haſt giuen me ſweeter times, more abundance of knowledge, in beſtowing vpon me ſo perfect, ſo vpright, ſo carefull a King as Iehoſaphat is, in ſo much that though I had ſweete dayes before, yet theſe that now I ſee, doe as much in meanes excell the former, as Myrrhe in ſweetnes doth excell Spikenard.</hi> This meaning doe I like of neither, as confining the Text.</p>
            <p>Others therefore (walking in a more ſpatious field) ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply it to the Church of euery age, or to euery particular be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuer: And amongſt <hi>them,</hi> ſome ſay <hi>one</hi> thing, ſome <hi>ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Soto. Maior.</note> 
               <hi>Some,</hi> by the <hi>bundle of Myrrhe,</hi> vnderſtand the <hi>death and paſſion of Chriſt,</hi> becauſe <hi>Myrrhe</hi> (as they ſay) was vſed
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:183854:28"/> in Burialls.<note n="*" place="margin">Genebr.</note> Others, the immortalitie of the ſoule, becauſe <hi>Myrrhe</hi> is an <hi>Embleme</hi> of incorruption.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The firſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, why by <hi>Myrrhe</hi> is meant iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication.</note>But I had rather vnderſtand, the <hi>benefit of Iuſtification.</hi> And that firſt of all, becauſe at <hi>this Center,</hi> the ſomewhat differing opinions of Interpreters doe meete; For when as <hi>ſome</hi> expound it of the <hi>death</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> doth not the Church ſmell the ſweetnes of his Death by the benefit of Iuſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? When as<note n="b" place="margin">As <hi>Merc.</hi> and <hi>Piſcator</hi> doe.</note> 
               <hi>others</hi> doe meane a moſt excellent and ſweet Odour which the Church doth draw from Chriſt, by the noſtrils of faith, is not Iuſtification the ground of <hi>this</hi> ſmell? yea, the aſſurance of Iuſtification is this ſmell it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>2</label> Beſides, I am ſure, <hi>Myrrhe</hi> doth ſymbolize and reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Iuſtification very fitly.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſcorid. li. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>67.</hi>
               </note>Firſt, <hi>Myrrhe</hi> diſtilleth from a tree full of prickes, much like the Egyptian thorne. And whence comes our righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe and juſtification, but from that tree of Gods eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall planting, Chriſt Ieſus, who was perſecuted, thorned, and pierced for our ſinnes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Impetigines purgat idem ibid.</note>Secondly, <hi>Myrrhe</hi> is of ſoueraigne vertue, to cleanſe the Leproſie of the body; ſo is Iuſtification to purge our Leprous and ſinfull ſoules.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Horrores diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutit, &amp;c. id. ib.</note>Thirdly, It is good againſt trembling, and the ſhaking of the ague; ſo is juſtification againſt a trembling heart, and horror of conſcience.</p>
            <p>Wee ſee then, what is meant by <hi>Myrrhe.</hi> And <hi>Bundle</hi> here, is as much as a ball of <hi>Myrrhe,</hi> or a bunch of <hi>Myrrhe; My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtically</hi> an <hi>Author</hi> of <hi>righteouſneſſe,</hi> or <hi>Iuſtifier, [is my well-be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued]</hi> that is, <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ſo ſtiled by a loue-title, which the Church giueth him, becauſe that he ſetteth his loue ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vpon her. <hi>[To me]</hi> that is, to me the Church militant;<note n="*" place="margin">Paraphaſe.</note> 
               <hi>I ſmell the ſweetneſſe of Iuſtification out of the bundle of his merits, who is my moſt louing and well-beloued Spouſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our concluſions from hence are theſe three. 1. <hi>That Chriſt alone is the Iuſtifier of the Church, his loue being the cauſe and ground of it.</hi> 2. <hi>That the Church alone is iuſtified by Chriſt.</hi> 3. <hi>That onely beleevers doe ſmell the ſweetnes of this benefit of iuſtification.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:183854:28"/>
            <p>The firſt of theſe points hath two parts.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Doct.</hi> That Chriſt in loue iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</note> 1. <hi>That Chriſtians are iuſtified by Chriſt Ieſus alone;</hi> 2. <hi>That it is from his meere loue:</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">1. Part of the <hi>Doct.</hi> proued.</note> 
               <hi>That Ieſus is the iuſtifier of the Church,</hi> is as euident as can be, as from hence, where the Church calleth him <hi>Her bundle of Myrrhe.</hi> So out of the writings of the Prophets; <hi>My righteous ſeruant ſhall iuſtifie many</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Iſa. 53.11.</note>. <hi>Their righteouſneſſe is of ME, ſaith the Lord</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Iſa. 54.17.</note>. Is it not the Angell <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that takes away from <hi>Ioſuah</hi> (the type of the Church) his filthy gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, <hi>that cauſeth his iniquitie to paſſe from him, and clotheth him with change of rayment.</hi> Euen with his owne righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, as <hi>Zachary</hi> ſheweth<note n="e" place="margin">Zach. 3.3.4.</note>? It is plaine alſo out of the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of the Apoſtle. <hi>By the obedience of ONE</hi> (meaning Chriſt) <hi>ſhall MANY</hi> (meaning the Church) <hi>be made righteous</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Rom. 5.19.</note>. <hi>He made him ſinne for vs, who knew no ſinne, that we might be made the righteouſneſſe of God in him</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">2 Cor. 5.21.</note>. <hi>If while we ſeeke to be iuſtified by Chriſt, we our ſelues are alſo found ſinners</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Gal. 2.17.</note>, &amp;c. And ſtill the Scripture runnes vpon this, that by <hi>Chriſt</hi> we are reconciled vnto God, cleanſed from ſinne, redeemed out of the handes of our enemies; He therefore is our Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fier, and none other: not excluding the Father,<note place="margin">A caueat.</note> or the holy Ghoſt, who haue a ſtroke in this Worke, as well as the Sonne.</p>
            <p>As for that other branch of the poynt,<note place="margin">The 2. part of the <hi>Doct.</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued.</note> 
               <hi>that his loue is the ground of this grace,</hi> the title <hi>Well-beloued,</hi> which the church here giueth him, will well carrie it, and els-where the holy Ghoſt confirmes it. <hi>By MERCY and truth is iniquitie purged</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Pro. 16.6.</note>, ſaith the Wiſeman. <hi>Being iuſtified freely by his GRACE, through the redemption that is in Ieſus Chriſt</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Rom. 3.24.</note>. <hi>That being iuſtified by his GRACE, wee ſhould be made heires according to the hope of eternall life,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle.</p>
            <p>Did not Chriſt <hi>alone</hi> ſatisfie the wrath of the Father?<note place="margin">The Reaſon of both the parts of the <hi>Doct.</hi> together.</note> did He not tread <hi>the Wine-preſſe</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Iſa. 63.3.</note> 
               <hi>alone?</hi> What earthly man holpe him in his <hi>Actiue</hi> obedience, to performe, a perfect, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plete, and entire, ſeruice to euery iot that the Law requireth? What mortall wight, nay, what creature in heauen or earth ayded him in his <hi>Paſſiue</hi> obedience; had the whole wrath of the Father, due to the ſinne of man, in full meaſure poured
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:183854:29"/> forth vpon him? Speaketh the Prophet of any els but Chriſt when he ſaith,<note place="margin">Iſa. 53.5.</note> 
               <hi>He was wounded for our tranſgreſſions, he was bruiſed for our iniquities, the chaſtiſement of our peace was vpon him?</hi> And would he euer haue vndergone this, endured this, had it not beene for <hi>loue?</hi> Doubtleſſe, He would not. Very well therefore doth the Church here, to acknowledge her <hi>Well beloued</hi> to be this <hi>Bundle of Myrrhe,</hi> and to giue to him,<note n="*" place="margin">Obiection. Anſw.</note> and his loue alone, the honour of her <hi>iuſtification,</hi> when as <hi>He</hi> alone payd the price to purchaſe it; and when as both the <hi>paſſion</hi> and <hi>compaſſion</hi> is his owne.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Fide ſola.</note>If any ſhall Obiect, that wee are iuſtified by Faith, or by Faith alone, therefore not wholly, not onely by Chriſt.</p>
            <p>It muſt be anſwered, that this is to be vnderſtood in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſence. Wee are iuſtified by <hi>faith,</hi> as by an <hi>inſtrumentall</hi> cauſe; by <hi>Chriſt</hi> as an <hi>efficient</hi> and <hi>fundamentall.</hi> For no more is <hi>faith</hi> the primary cauſe of my iuſtification, then my hand is the cauſe of the ſupply of my wants, by a piece of money, which the mercy of another furniſheth mee with. That propoſition;<note n="*" place="margin">Parae ad Heb. p. <hi>460</hi> Solafide, exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duntur vero no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cauſae ſuperio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, gratia Dei &amp; meritum Chriſti, ſed &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Wee are iuſtified by faith ALONE</hi> (a ſpeech much vſed by Orthodoxall Writers) doth not exclude the cauſes of Iuſtification <hi>without</hi> our ſelues, but it doth include onely but<note n="m" place="margin">Quotie dici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, Solafides iuſtificat, oſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditur ſolamfide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſſe vnicum ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gumentum, &amp; vnicam facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem quâ reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitur iuſtitia Chriſti. Selnec. Tract. <hi>3.</hi> de fid. &amp; Sacram. Theſ <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>one</hi> facultie <hi>in</hi> our ſelues, by which alone wee doe apprehend that righteouſneſſe of Chriſt, which the Lord doth impute vnto vs for our Iuſtification. Whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſaith one; <hi>By faith alone, are not excluded ſuperior cauſes, as, the grace of God, the merit of Chriſt, but middle cauſes, which are coyned by hypocrites, as, the ſtrength of free will workes, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, &amp;c.</hi> So that by <hi>faith</hi> wee are <hi>inſtrumentally</hi> iuſtified, by the obedience of Chriſt <hi>formally,</hi> as<note n="n" place="margin">Tom <hi>5</hi> in epiſt. ad Eph p. <hi>83.</hi> col. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Zanchius</hi> ſheweth. For in Iuſtification,<note n="o" place="margin">Bucer. in iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficatione fides nihil dat ſed tantum accipit, &amp; quod accipit, eo ipſo iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur.</note> 
               <hi>Faith giues nothing, but onely receiueth, and what it receiueth,</hi> (being Chriſt and his righteouſneſſe) <hi>by that very ſame thing are we iuſtified.</hi> So that it may very well be affirmed, that faith iuſtifieth alone, and yet be a truth too which (I am in hand withall) that by Chriſt alone wee are iuſtified.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> And for currant might this Doctrine goe through all Chriſtendome,<note place="margin">Againſt the Papiſts.</note> were it not for Antichriſt, and his Babylo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:183854:29"/> followers, of <hi>whom</hi> when I thought, there came to mind a wiſe ſpeech of a graue<note n="p" place="margin">Tertull. Apol. p. <hi>815.</hi> Niſi homini De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us plaeuerit, deus non erit, homo iam Deo propitiùs eſſe debebit. <hi>The Papiſts deny Chriſt to be our a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone</hi> iuſtifier <hi>three wayes. 1. By their blaſphemous Canons.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Father</hi> to allude to; <hi>God ſhould be God, if man would let him, God now belike muſt ſtand to mans curteſie for his ſuperioritie:</hi> So may I ſay of the Papiſts; <hi>Ieſus ſhould be Ieſus, if they would let him, the ALONE iuſtifier of his people, if THEY would permit him, and belike, He must ſtand to THEIR caruing for the honour of this Worke:</hi> For <hi>they</hi> are very bold to rob him of his glory which he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerues, and his <hi>Bride</hi> here giues him, and him <hi>alone</hi> for this grace. Neither let any ſay, I doe them wrong.</p>
            <p>For, firſt of all, doth not the <hi>Councell of Trent</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">In Decret. de iuſtif. Can. <hi>10.</hi> &amp;</note>, abſolutely lay downe this? <hi>If any ſhall affirme, that men are iuſtified by the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt formally, let him be accurſed.</hi> And im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately after;<note n="r" place="margin">Canon. XI. Si quis dixerit homines iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cari vel ſola imputatione iuſtitiae Chriſti, &amp;c. <hi>2. By attribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication to the dignitie of faith.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>If any man ſhall ſay, that men are iuſtified ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the imputation of Chriſts righteouſneſſe alone, or that the grace whereby we are iuſtified, is onely the fauour of God, let him be Anathema.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, doe they not aſcribe Iuſtification to the <hi>dignitie</hi> of faith? What meanes els that Poſition of theirs; <hi>That wee are prepared by faith to ſome meritorious act of loue, which act of loue doth informe faith, and ſo dignifie it, that then the perſon that hath it, deſerueth acceptance at Gods handes.</hi> And this Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion, they are very ſtiffe in,<note n="*" place="margin">Obiect.</note> alledging for it the Apoſtles wordes, <hi>To him that beleeueth on him that iuſtifieth the vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, is his faith accounted for righteouſneſſe</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">Rom. 4.5. <hi>Anſw.</hi>
               </note>, that is (ſay they) God accounts that faith which he findes in a ſinner, ſo <hi>wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy thy that it doth deſerue an habite of righteouſneſſe, by which the ſinner may be iuſtified.</hi> But (as the Proverbe is) <hi>An ill gloſſe corrupteth the Text.</hi> For this Expoſition holdes neither with the <hi>analogie</hi> of <hi>faith,</hi> nor with the ſcope of the place. Not with the <hi>analogie</hi> of <hi>faith,</hi> for it is directly againſt the Scripture, that a man may be a wicked man, and yet haue ſome thing in him worthy of iuſtification. Not with the <hi>ſcope</hi> of the <hi>place;</hi> For <hi>there</hi> the Apoſtles ayme is (being in diſputation about iuſtification) to ſhow, that there is an Antitheſis, or contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction betwixt the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt, and the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe of a man out of Chriſt; and not to ſhow, that faith
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:183854:30"/> informed by charitie, doth by condignitie, merit the iuſtify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the ſinner in the ſight of God.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">3. By main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation by Workes.</note>Thirdly, how peremptorily doe they ſtand for juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by Workes, abuſing for their purpoſe many places of Scripture: as,</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>1</label> Firſt, that of <hi>Iames,</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">Iam. 2.24. <hi>Anſw.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Yee ſee then how that by workes a man is iuſtified, and not by faith alone;</hi> when as (as it is well knowne) the drift of the Apoſtle is <hi>there</hi> to ſhow, that good workes <hi>declare</hi> a man to be iuſt before <hi>men,</hi> and doe not <hi>make</hi> a man iuſt in the ſight of <hi>God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>2</label> Secondly, they bring in <hi>that</hi> of the <hi>Pſalmiſt,</hi>
               <note n="u" place="margin">Pſal. 18.20.24.<hi>Anſw.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>The Lord rewarded me according to my righteouſneſſe, and according to the cleanneſſe of my handes hath he recompenced mee.</hi> But alas, to little purpoſe; For the Prophet in that place, as ſome ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue, doth not ſpeake of <hi>iuſtification,</hi> but<note n="*" place="margin">Certum eſt Dauidem hoc Pſalmo, nihil aliud canere de Deo, qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quòd per illum libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratus fit ab ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtibus &amp;c. Muſcul, ad loc.</note> onely of the <hi>deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance</hi> that God gaue him out of the hands of his enemies; which <hi>deliuerance</hi> alſo, he doth not attribute to the merit of his owne righteouſneſſe; (For <hi>that</hi> he diſclaimes, verſ. 19. ſaying; <hi>He deliuered me, becauſe he had a FAVOVR vnto me</hi>) but onely he acknowledgeth, that <hi>that</hi> deliverance was a teſtimony of his integritie, how <hi>naught</hi> and <hi>vniuſt</hi> ſoeuer his enemies falſely <hi>accounted</hi> and <hi>accuſed</hi> him to be.</p>
            <p>Many of the like places doe they thus abuſe; <hi>abuſe</hi> (I ſay) and whither I ſpeake right or no, I appeale not onely to S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul,</hi> whoſe drift is in the fiue firſt Chapters of the Epiſtle to the <hi>Romanes,</hi> to ouerthrow iuſtification by Workes; but alſo to <hi>one</hi> of their owne<note n="x" place="margin">Aquin, Super Gal. c. <hi>3.</hi> Lec <hi>4.</hi> Opera non ſunt cauſa quod ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis ſit iuſtus apud Deum, &amp;c.</note> Doctors, whoſe very wordes are theſe; <hi>Workes are not the cauſe that any man is righteous before God, but rather they are the fruits and declarations of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi> And indeed how can we be iuſtified by workes, when as by the confeſſion of the Papiſts<note n="y" place="margin">Caiet, in epiſt. ad Roman. c. <hi>3.</hi> fol. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> themſelues; <hi>the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe of Workes cannot blot out ſinnes, but leaues a man in the ſame.</hi> Thus while the Papiſts doe partly <hi>curſe</hi> thoſe that hold juſtification by the free mercy of God, and partly aſcribe it to the <hi>dignitie of Faith,</hi> and partly to the <hi>merit of good Workes,</hi> doe they not rob Chriſt of that praiſe which his great kindneſſe in iuſtifying a poore ſinner doth deſerue?
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:183854:30"/> Dealing with this bundle of ſpirituall <hi>Myrrhe,</hi> as ſome<note n="z" place="margin">Petrus de la Primaud. Franc. Acad. part. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>69.</hi>
               </note> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port the <hi>Arabian</hi> followers of <hi>Mahomet</hi> to deale with that corporall <hi>Myrrhe,</hi> which they bring to <hi>Alexandria</hi> to ſell, vſing a thouſand deceits to ſophiſticate it, and gull Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans with it, that buy it. So they (I ſay) adulterate this preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Doctrine with their owne deceipts and deuices, and would thruſt it for good ware, and ſound vpon the common ſort; But I pray God, they may neuer haue any vent for ſuch deceitfull <hi>Myrrhe,</hi> and counterfeit righteouſneſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs. I am ſure, the Church entertaines no ſuch ſtuffe <hi>here;</hi> but ſpeakes all to the commendation of her <hi>Beloued,</hi> admitting of <hi>no Myrrhe, no</hi> righteouſneſſe, but his owne, to prayſe him, and to commend by. But to leaue them as confuted, let vs come to our ſelues.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> I would to God, there were not ſome Popiſh Proteſtants amongſt our ſelues, who muſt haue ſome perfume in <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures</hi> garden to ſmell on, ſome <hi>naturall</hi> or <hi>morall</hi> plant of <hi>their owne,</hi> to put into <hi>this</hi> Bundle, to mingle with <hi>Chriſts righteouſneſſe,</hi> to iuſtifie them in the ſight of God. Some good <hi>deſires, deedes, devotions,</hi> which they much brag off, and ſtand vpon, for which God is forſooth bound to accept them, and to like of them. To whom I may ſay truely, as <hi>Elihu</hi> in another caſe to <hi>Iob; Behold, in THIS thou art not iuſt</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Iob 33.12.</note>. It may be thou art of a gentle nature, of a curteous be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauiour, ſomewhat diſpoſed to liberalitie out of a vaine-glorious humour, canſt not away with the company of the prodigall; muſt God of neceſſitie iuſtifie thee, like of thee for <hi>theſe</hi> things? Yes, that he muſt, and doth too, I would be ſorry els; I am ſure, he would not like of me, if I ſhould ſwill, and curſe, and ſteale, and quarrell, &amp;c. thats true; for he cannot away with theſe groſſe euills; the committers of them are abominable vnto him. Yet notwithſtanding, to conclude, that thy morall vertues can iuſtifie thee before him, is little differing from plaine Popery. And I tell thee in ſtanding vpon this thou doeſt Papiſt-like rob Chriſt of his glory, and deny him that prayſe which the members of the Church doe <hi>here</hi> giue him, as his due in this Text. They
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:183854:31"/> ſay not here, <hi>A bundle of Myrrhe is my Well-beloued, and my Spikenard vnto me, but my Well-beloued alone.</hi> They acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge all in the matter of juſtification, to come from Chriſt Ieſus, iſſuing and ſpringing from the fountaine of his free loue. They know, that the beſt righteouſneſſe in themſelues is (as the Prophet ſpeaketh) <hi>as an vncleane thing, and filthy rags</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Iſa. 64.6.</note>: and that in the beſt actions they doe, if their imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections be not couered in Chriſt, and ſweetned with the <hi>Myrrhe</hi> of his righteouſneſſe, there is more cauſe of <hi>damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> to be found in them then <hi>ſaluation.</hi> It is by <hi>grace</hi> that wee are iuſtified, not by <hi>Workes.</hi> The very faithfull them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues pleaſe God no otherwiſe then in Chriſt. Neither their <hi>loue,</hi> nor <hi>faith,</hi> nor <hi>good fruites,</hi> can for the dignitie of the ſame, deſerue abſolution before Gods tribunall. Now then if the <hi>graces</hi> that are <hi>inwardly</hi> wrought, and the <hi>Workes</hi> that doe <hi>outwardly</hi> appeare in beleevers themſelues, can procure no further acceptance at Gods handes, then their perſons ſtand iuſtified, and their ſinnes acquitted before GOD in Chriſt, then queſtionles (as God once told the idolatrous <hi>Iſraelites) neither thy Workes, nor thy righteouſneſſe will profit thee</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Iſa. 57.12.</note>, to iuſtification, that art but carnall, but ciuill. That then I may ceaſe to <hi>confute</hi> thee, &amp; be a <hi>counſeller</hi> vnto thee,<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Vſe</hi> 3. Exhortation to diſclaime our owne righteouſnes.</note> let me exhort thee, willingly to giue the <hi>Well beloued</hi> of the Church, the glory of this grace alone. Mingle not thy righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe with <hi>his</hi> in the matter of iuſtification; ſuch a mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ſuch a compoſition ſtinkes before the Lord. I finde in the old<note n="d" place="margin">Exod. 30.34.35.38.</note> 
               <hi>Law,</hi> how that the Lord commanded <hi>Moſes</hi> to make a ſweete perfume of <hi>Stacte, Onicha, Galbanum,</hi> and <hi>Franckinſence,</hi> and to temper it after the art of an <hi>Apothecary,</hi> holy and pure. Concerning <hi>which,</hi> he threatned that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer ſhould preſume to make the <hi>like,</hi> to ſmell thereto, that ſoule ſhould be cut off from the Lords people. And hath the Father commanded a greater then <hi>Moſes,</hi> euen his onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten Sonne, to temper an exact and moſt pure perfume of his owne righteouſneſſe and obedience for the <hi>Father</hi> to ſmell on, that he might be <hi>pacified</hi> with the <hi>Elect,</hi> for the <hi>Elect</hi> to ſmell on, that <hi>they</hi> might be iuſt before <hi>GOD.</hi>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:183854:31"/> And ſhall mortall, ſinfull, man (contrary to Gods charge) preſume to compoſe the like, out of his owne righteouſnes, and yet the Lord endure it, reckon that perſon amongſt the number of his owne people? No, no. The <hi>ciuilleſt</hi> perſon that liues vnder the cope of heauen, ſhall greatly diſpleaſe the Lord, if he preſumes to offer it. Didſt thou <hi>equall,</hi> nay <hi>excell</hi> the moſt vertuous <hi>moraliſts</hi> that euer were, in <hi>iuſtice, temperance, magnanimitie, affabilitie,</hi> and the like, yet thou muſt eſteeme all theſe as <hi>nought</hi> in compariſon of the <hi>righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> crucified. Learne therefore, learne, I beſeech thee, to diſclaime thine owne righteouſneſſe; Shuffle, oh ſhuffle not in the <hi>merit,</hi> the <hi>dignitie</hi> of <hi>any</hi> good <hi>deedes,</hi> or <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires</hi> of <hi>thine owne,</hi> into <hi>this</hi> bundle, leaſt like the mixture of <hi>Opocalpaſum</hi> with <hi>Myrrhe,</hi> it proue deadly to thy ſoule, as <hi>that</hi> to the body<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>As</hi> Mathiolus <hi>cites it out of</hi> Galen. Opocal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſum exitiale eſt, multoſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> nos ſorte quadam vidimus noſtrae aetatis de curſu mori quòd inſcij Myrrham, cui Opocalpaſum admiſtum erat, aſſumpſiſſent. Mathio. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. in Dioſ. li. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>67.</hi> Pag. <hi>77.</hi>
               </note>: and thou neuer ſmell the ſweetneſſe of the ſame, in aſſurance thou art iuſtified, to thy conſolation here, and ſalvation hereafter.</p>
            <p>Now to the end thou mayeſt learne to diſclaime thine owne righteouſneſſe indeede. This threefold Meditation will be very availeable.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Three medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vs in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claiming our owne righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe.</note>Firſt, that mans righteouſneſſe, cannot acquit him, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge him, before the Iudge.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that it breaketh <hi>euery</hi> way, that it can fulfill <hi>no</hi> way the Law of God perfectly, and entirely; it <hi>omitteth</hi> much good, it <hi>committeth</hi> much euill, that good which it doth, it doth not aright, that euill which it eſcheweth, is eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chewed for by-reſpects.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Meditate, that the worthieſt and holieſt of the Saints of God, haue cryed out of it, neuer looked to be iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified by it. As <hi>Dauid; In ſinne Lord hath my Mother concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued me</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Pſal. 51.5.</note>: and <hi>Iob; The Angels are vncleane before thee, how much more abhominable is man that is borne of a woman</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Iob 15.15.16.</note>. And <hi>Paul; I know that in me, that is, in my fleſh dwelleth no good thing</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Rom. 7.18.</note>.</p>
            <p>Theſe three things, I ſay, feriouſly and wiſely thought of, and pauſed vpon, will much further thee to thinke meanely of thine owne righteouſneſſe, beeſt thou neuer ſo
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:183854:32"/> ciuill: Wilt thou know how? I will ſhow thee. The firſt Meditation, will driue thee to ſpeake thus betwixt God and thy ſoule; <hi>Good Lord, cannot all my righteouſneſſe cleere me be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thy Tribunall? notwithſtanding my ciuilitie, my fidelitie in keeping my word, my gentlenes of nature, my abſtaining from the groſſe, and enormious vices of the times, doe I not ſtand diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged before thee the moſt vpright and vnpartiall Iudge? Lord, why ſhould I then ſtand vpon my righteouſneſſe? Oh, cauſe me to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre my ſelfe in duſt and aſhes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond Meditation, will driue thee to this? <hi>What? and for all my righteouſnes, doe I breake thy Law, tranſgreſſe thy Commandements, in the omiſſion of good, in the commiſſion of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, in the doing of good, and forſaking of euill, after a wrong manner? Lord, I perceiue then by this, that I cannot be iuſtified in thy ſight by my ſelfe; when as that righteouſneſſe which iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth before thee, muſt performe an exact obedience to thy most righteous Law, without ſweruing one iot from the ſame.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third Meditation will, by the grace of God, worke, in ſome ſuch wiſe, with thee as this is; <hi>Lord, haue the beſt that euer were cryed out of their owne filthineſſe, complained of their natiue vilenes, denied their owne righteouſneſſe? and ſhall I be puffed vp with an opinion of mine owne worth? Did ſo holy a man as</hi> Dauid <hi>was, ſo patient a man as</hi> Iob <hi>was, ſo good a man as</hi> Paul <hi>was, caſt downe their crownes before the Lambe, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge that in themſelues was nothing but ſinne, no cleanenes, no good thing? and ſhall I, a vile creature, farre inferiour to the leaſt of them, ſtand vpon my patience, my honeſtie, my goodneſſe? Lord, let it be farre from me, &amp;c.</hi> And when theſe Meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons haue brought thee to this paſſe, produced theſe effects; tell me whither then it can be poſſible for thee, to ſing any Song but this, in regard of thy iuſtification; <hi>None but Chriſt, none but Chriſt: His righteouſneſſe, his righteouſneſſe alone, to diſcharge me before the Iudge, to fulfill the Law for me, to cure my ſpirituall ſickenes, to couer my naturall filthineſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If theſe Meditations were but duely made vſe of by our ciuill <hi>Iustitiarians</hi> themſelues, they would vaile the Bonet, come downe a peg lower in their owne conceits, and runne
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:183854:32"/> altogether out of the garden of nature, into the garden of grace for this <hi>Myrrhe,</hi> and depend vpon Gods loue alone in Chriſt Ieſus for their iuſtification. But alas, alas, they medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate not vpon this, and hence it is, that they ſtand ſo much vpon their owne worthines, that the righteouſnes of Chriſt, is neither thought on, nor ſought for, by them, as it ſhould be.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>4</label> Laſtly, is Chriſt the alone Iuſtifier of the Church, and is his free grace, the ground of it?<note place="margin">Adviſe to Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuers, to be thankefull to their <hi>Iuſtifier.</hi>
               </note> how thankefull then ought this to perſwade Beleevers to be, and how carefull to ſing ſuch a Song as the Church here doth to the prayſe of their <hi>Well-beloued.</hi> We vſe to ſay, a Noſegay is worth thankes, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially, when it is giuen by a louer, as a token of loue; and is not this bundle, this bunch of <hi>Myrrhe,</hi> Chriſt his righteouſneſſe, worthy of praiſes, being giuen by him as a ſpeciall token of his fauour, to poore, miſerable, and ſinfull creatures? Did the<note n="i" place="margin">Luk. 17.16.</note> tenth <hi>Leper,</hi> returne thankes for the cleanſing of his body, and wilt not thou, whom Chriſt hath choſen as one out of ten, yea, of twentie, to purge thy ſoule, returne glory to his name? <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Luk. 7.47.</note> loued Chriſt much, after He had forgiuen her much: <hi>Dauid</hi> reſolu'd with himſelfe, that, on condition the Lord according to the multitude of his mercies, would doe away his iniquities, and purge him with Hyſop, which was an Embleme of his cleanſing, and cloathing with Chriſts righteouſneſſe, <hi>his tongue ſhould ſing aloud of his righteouſneſſe</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Pſal. 51.2.7.14. verſes.</note>.</p>
            <p>It is reported of <hi>Alexander,</hi> ſirnamed, <hi>The Great,</hi> that he acknowledged himſelfe to <hi>owe</hi> more to <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> his Maſter, then to <hi>Philip</hi> his Father, becauſe, from his Maſter he recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued his <hi>Well being,</hi> whereas from his Father he had but his naturall <hi>being</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Pet. Mart. in lib. <hi>1.</hi> Ethic. Ariſt. p. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note>. In like manner (I dare boldly ſay) thou that art a true Chriſtian, oweſt more to Chriſt thy Maſter, yea, thy elder brother, for giuing thee through the merit of his owne righteouſneſſe, a ſpirituall being in grace, then to thy naturall Father or Mother, by whom thou haſt thy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in nature. Oh, therefore (owing ſo much) pay him much, I meane, loue him much, be much thankefull vnto
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:183854:33"/> him for this his kindneſſe. Let thy thankefulneſſe to him know no limits; ſet no bounds to thy obedience; let not much water quench the flame of thy loue, thy zeale; let not the very fire it ſelfe deterre thee, ſcare thee, from ſacrifice, from his ſeruice. Propoſe the bleſſed Martyrs for thy pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne. The ſweetneſſe of this bundle haue ſo affected <hi>them,</hi> that rather then they would any way ſhow themſelues vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratefull, they haue not ſpared to be prodigall of their very liues. Take, oh take then, the cup of ſaluation, and bleſſe his holy name, vow ſeruice, vow obedience to him, vnto the very death; for his free mercy, in iuſtifying of thee, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires no leſſe, deſerues no leſſe at thy hands. Leauing this, I come now to the next poynt; which is</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That as Chriſt alone is the Iuſtifier of the Church,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Doct.</note> 
               <hi>ſo the Church alone is iuſtified by Chriſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The true Church alone is iuſtified by Chriſt.</note> Iuſtification is a benefit belonging onely to the true members of the Church, and to none elſe. <hi>TO MEE,</hi> in my Text, implies as much; <hi>To me the Church alone, not to you daughters of Ieruſalem,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Except you be Eloct.</note> 
               <hi>not to you aliants and ſtrangers to the Common-wealth of Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell is my Beloued a bundle of Myrrhe, a bringer of righteouſneſſe.</hi> Aske <hi>Paul,</hi> whom he ſpeakes of, when he ſaith; <hi>In grace HE</hi> (that is God) <hi>hath made VS accepted in the Beloued</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Ephe. 1.6.</note>; (that is, <hi>iuſtified through Chriſt</hi>) and he will anſwere, that he mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth <hi>VS, who are choſen in Christ, before the foundation of the world; VS, who are predeſtinated to the adoption of children</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Verſes 4.5.</note>; intimating, none to be capable of iuſtification but ſuch. The ſame thing, the ſame Apoſtle proueth in the eight of the <hi>Romanes; Whom he predeſtinated, them alſo he called, and whom he called, them alſo he iustified</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">Rom. 8.30.</note>. Now who are predeſtinated, who are the called of God, but the members of the Church?<note n="p" place="margin">Verſ. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Who ſhall lay any thing to the charge of Gods Elect? It is God that iuſtifieth,</hi> that is, <hi>it is God that iustifieth the Elect</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">Zanch. ad Eph. c. <hi>2.</hi> p. <hi>8.</hi> Tom. <hi>5.</hi> i. e. Electosfolos.</note>. Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinkes, that of S. <hi>Iohn</hi> in his <hi>Reuelation,</hi> is very fit for this purpoſe, where he ſaith, <hi>not</hi> that he <hi>ſaw the</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Apoc. 13.1.</note> 
               <hi>BEAST with ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen heades, and ten hornes</hi> (that is, the enemies of the Church, who vſe their wit and authoritie againſt it) <hi>cloathed with the Sunne,</hi> that is, with Chriſts righteouſneſſe, but a<note n="ſ" place="margin">Apoc. 12.1.</note> 
               <hi>WOMAN
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:183854:33"/> ſo cloathed,</hi> that is, the Church alone, or the company of the faithfull.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>
               </label> The reaſon is plaine, for faith which apprehendeth juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication by Chriſt, is a gift proper and peculiar to the Church, and none elſe, for which cauſe it is ſtiled, <hi>The faith of Gods ELECT</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">Tit. 1.1.</note>. Now if none haue faith but the Church, then it muſt needes follow, that none are iuſtified, but the members of the Church.</p>
            <p>How full of terror is this truth, vnto all thoſe that are out of the Church, I meane, not onely thoſe who ſtand ſunning themſelues in the Church-yard, that ſit ſwilling in Alehou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, fulfilling their fleſhly pleaſures, following their worldly profits, while the Word is Preaching, and people are pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vpon the LORDS day. I meane (I ſay) not onely them, who are thus out of the materiall Temple, which is made of Bricke and Stone<note n="*" place="margin">And yet I include them alſo, for right Chriſtians dare not doe as they doe.</note>, but alſo all others, that are no true members of Chriſts <hi>mysticall</hi> body, who, though they heare the Word, receiue the Sacraments, &amp;c. yet are voyde of ſauing grace, are no ſpirituall ſtones of the ſpirituall buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, no<note n="u" place="margin">Cant. 1.17.</note> 
               <hi>Cedar</hi> beames in Gods houſe, that is, no<note n="*" place="margin">For <hi>Cedar</hi> was vſed in cleanſing, <hi>Levit.</hi> 14. Notes of the falſe Church: Propounded by the way, to ſhew whom this terror be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to.</note> puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, no ſanctified ones in Gods familie. To all of them, to euery one of them, here is (I ſay) a ground of terrour. For (ah poore creatures) they are not iuſtified, they haue no ſhare <hi>in,</hi> no benefit <hi>by,</hi> the righteouſneſſe of <hi>Christ.</hi> This bundle belongs not to them; It is peculiar to thoſe whom they (for their Religions-ſake) hate, ſcorne, and maligne. It appertaines not to thoſe daughters of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> ſpoken of in the fift verſe of this Chapter, who ſeeme to be of the Church, who brag they are of the <hi>Iſraell</hi> of God, and yet are not.<note n="*" place="margin">1. Particular loue of falſe teaching and teachers.</note>
               <hi>Thou</hi> therefore that delighteſt in falſe <hi>Doctrine,</hi> and caſteſt the <hi>Word of God behind thy backe</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Ier. 8.9.</note>; <hi>thou</hi> that with <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hab,</hi> hadſt rather heare an hundred falſe Prophets, then one ſound <hi>Michaiah</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">1 King. 22.</note>; and with <hi>Ieroboam</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">1 Kin. 13.4.</note>, wilt not hearken to the faithfull meſſengers of the Lord of Hoſts;<note n="*" place="margin">2. Neutrali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in religion.</note> 
               <hi>thou</hi> that with the ſame <hi>Ieroboam</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">1 Kin 12.28.29.</note>, art readie to change thy Religion, and manner of worſhip, inſtituted by God himſelfe;<note n="*" place="margin">3. Defence and ripnes of ſinne.</note> 
               <hi>thou</hi> that with the people in <hi>Ieremies</hi> time, wilt palliate and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:183854:34"/> thy ſinnes, profeſſing thou walkeſt not after <hi>Balaim,</hi> when <hi>as yet the Lord ſees thy abhomination in the Valley</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Ier. 2.23.</note>, <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing pure in thine owne eyes, when as yet thou art not cleanſed from thy wickedneſſe</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Prov. 30.12.</note>;<note n="*" place="margin">4. Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my.</note> 
               <hi>thou</hi> that with the couetous, whom <hi>Dauid</hi> ſpeakes of,<note n="d" place="margin">Pſal. 10.3.</note> 
               <hi>bleſſeſt thy ſelfe and blaſphemeſt God,</hi> and with <hi>Goliah,</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">1 Sam. 17.9.10.</note> 
               <hi>curſest</hi> God and his people:<note n="*" place="margin">5. Contempt of authoritie.</note> 
               <hi>Thou</hi> that with the <hi>ſonnes</hi> of <hi>Belial</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">1 Sam. 10.25</note>, contemneſt the powers that be ordained of God:<note n="*" place="margin">6. Vaine confidence.</note> 
               <hi>Thou</hi> that truſteſt with <hi>Goliah</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">1 Sam. 17.45.</note>, in <hi>thy</hi> ſword and buckler; with the wicked of <hi>Dauids</hi> time, in the<note n="h" place="margin">Pſal. 49.6. Pſal. 52.7.</note> multitude <hi>of thy riches;</hi> with the<note n="i" place="margin">Iſa. 43.14.</note> 
               <hi>Chaldeans,</hi> in <hi>the treaſures thy ſhippes</hi> bring in by Sea; with the old <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> in <hi>thy pleaſant pic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Iſa. 2.16.</note>, that is, in thy houſhold furniture and riches<note n="l" place="margin">So <hi>Scultet.</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounds plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant pictures.</note>:<note n="*" place="margin">7. Hypocriti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calnes.</note> 
               <hi>Thou</hi> that canſt the <hi>Art</hi> of diſſembling, hauing <hi>Butter in thy mouth, and warre in thy heart</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Pſal. 55.21.</note>; that canſt <hi>bleſſe with thy mouth, but curſe with thy heart</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Pſal. 62.4.</note>:<note n="*" place="margin">8. Loue <hi>to</hi> &amp; defence <hi>of</hi> bad company.</note> 
               <hi>Thou</hi> that <hi>louect the compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the vngodly</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">Pſal. 1.1.2.</note>, and <hi>magnifiest the wicked, which forſake the Law</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">Pro. 28.4.</note>:<note n="*" place="margin">9. Malice to the Saints.</note> 
               <hi>Thou</hi> that with the enemies of Gods <hi>Iſrael,</hi> treadeſt downe <hi>the inheritance of the Lord</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">Iſa. 63.18.</note>, circumventing them as the <hi>Sodomites</hi> did <hi>Lots</hi> houſe<note n="r" place="margin">Gen. 19.</note>, ſpreading Net; for their <hi>feet</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">Pſal. 140.</note>, <hi>reioycing at their hurt</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">Pſal. 35.15.</note>, drawing out <hi>the ſword,</hi> &amp; bending <hi>the bow, that thou maieſt ſuddenly hit them that are vpright in heart</hi>
               <note n="u" place="margin">Pſal. 37.14.32.</note>:<note n="*" place="margin">10 Carnall ſecuritie.</note> 
               <hi>Thou</hi> (finally) that art at eaſe in <hi>Sion,</hi> drowned in the depth of carnall ſecuritie, <hi>thinking thou ſhalt neuer be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moued</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Pſal. 10.6.</note>; who haſt <hi>made a couenant with death, and art with hell at agreement,</hi> thinking that <hi>when the ouer flowing ſcourge ſhall paſſe through, it ſhall not touch thee,</hi> and ſo making <hi>lies thy refuge,</hi> and <hi>vnderfalſhood hiding thy ſelfe</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Iſa. 28.15.</note>: Thou, I ſay, that carrieſt of all theſe, or any of theſe blacke brandes of the falſe Church, theſe <hi>non euidences</hi> of the true Church, heare thou this word of terror, thou art not iuſtified by the Lord Ieſus and not to be iuſtified by him, deſperate and fearefull muſt thy condition needes be: yea, ſo fearefull, that neither can my capacitie reach it, nor my tongue relate it. For be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the abſence of thoſe admirable ſoule rauiſhing effects, ſpringing from iuſtification, which thou ſhalt reade off af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards<note n="y" place="margin">Page. 67.</note>, it is an argument of Gods diſpleaſure conceiued againſt thee, it doth prognoſticate, wrath abiding for thee:
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:183854:34"/> inſomuch, that if the <hi>Beloued of the Church, be not this bun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle of Myrrhe, TO THEE, TO ME,</hi> and become our <hi>Righteouſneſſe,</hi> the ſtinch of our ſinnes, will daily prouoke the Lord; the ſmell of our courſes, will daily diſtaſt him; the ſauour of our very Sacrifices, are a burthen vnto him: neither are our ſinnes remitted, nor our ſutes receiued, nor our perſons reſpected, nor our good deedes rewarded, nor can our ſoules (if wee ſo continue) be eternally ſaued. Iudge thou then whither this poynt (as ſweete as it is to the godly) doth not bring (if thou beeſt not altogether hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe and helpeleſſe) a ſound of terror to thy eares: and oh, that it might but be a meane to produce an holy trembling in thy ſoule, vpon the thought of thy great miſery.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> Secondly, this is not ſo terrible to the wicked, but it is as comfortable to the godly. Is it their peculiar to be iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Chriſt? Doe they alone participate of that righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, which many thouſands in the world, neither haue, nor are like to haue, any ſhare in? What bountie, what loue is this from Chriſt to them? <hi>Myrrhe</hi> it ſelfe ſhould not more refreſh the ſmell, then the conſideration of this accheere their ſoule. And accheere them it doth at ſometime or other, let the Deuill doe his worſt, as the next Doctrine ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, which without any longer delay, I come vnto: And this it is:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That as the Church alone is capable of Chriſts righteouſnes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Doct.</hi> Chriſtians a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone haue the ioy of iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</note> 
               <hi>ſo ſhee onely is ſenſible of the ſweetneſſe of the ſame.</hi> Onely Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuers doe truely reioyce in the aſſurance of free iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by Chriſt. What ſaith <hi>Dauid</hi> to this purpoſe? <hi>The RIGHTEOVS ſhall be glad in the Lord, and all the VP<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RIGHT in heart ſhall glory</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">Pſal. 64.10</note>. What ſaith the Prophet <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay</hi> alſo? <hi>The RANSOMED of the Lord ſhall returne, and come to Sion with Songes, THEY ſhall obtaine ioy and gladneſſe, and ſorrow and ſighing ſhall flie away</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Iſa. 35.10.</note>. Againe, <hi>My SERVANTS ſhall reioyce, my ſervants ſhall ſing for ioy of heart. I create IERVSALEM a reioycing, and HER people a ioy</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Iſa 65.14.15.18.</note>. Of whom ſpeakes the Church when ſhe ſaith; <hi>We will be glad in the Lord, and reioyce in his ſaluation</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Iſa 25.9.</note>; <hi>I will
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:183854:35"/> greatly reioyce in the Lord, my ſoule ſhall be ioyfull in my God, for he hath cloathed me with the garments of ſalvation, he hath couered me with the robes of righteouſneſſe</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Iſa. 61.10.</note>. Of whom (I ſay) ſpeakes the Church there, but of her ſelfe? I confeſſe that <hi>literally</hi> thoſe ſpeeches of the Prophet, are to be referred to the reioycing of the <hi>Iewes</hi> at their returne from captiuitie. But myſtically they are to be interpreted, of the ioy which beleeuers <hi>alone</hi> conceiue vpon their returne from <hi>ſpirituall</hi> bondage, and vpon their iuſtification by the merits of Chriſt, and free mercy of the Almightie. Wherefore it was not without cauſe, that Chriſt ſayd to the Man ſicke of the Palſey; <hi>Sonne, be of good cheare, thy ſinnes are forgiven thee</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Mat. 9.2.</note>. And <hi>Elihu</hi> in <hi>Iob; He that can ſay, I haue found a Ranſome</hi> (eſpecially ſuch as Chriſts righteouſneſſe hath procured) <hi>ſhall ſee Gods face with ioy</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Iob. 33.24. 6. compared <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ogether.</note>.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>1</label> That which was the ground of the former poynt, may be the firſt ground of this alſo. Chriſtians onely haue faith. Now faith is not onely an <hi>Hand,</hi> to plucke this <hi>Myrrhe,</hi> the meanes to apprehend the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt, that it may become ours; but alſo it is the <hi>Noſtrills,</hi> to ſmell the ſweetneſſe of this <hi>Myrrhe:</hi> Looke as the noſtrills doe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uey ſweete odours to the braine, to refreſh the animall ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, which are <hi>there,</hi> ſo doth faith conuey the aſſurance of iuſtification, to the rauiſhing, and delighting of the ſoule. If the Church <hi>alone</hi> then hath the noſtrills of faith, no wonder is it, if ſhee <hi>alone</hi> be ſenſible of the ſweetneſſe of Chriſts righteouſneſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>2</label> Secondly, Chriſt Ieſus onely lodgeth and dwelleth in them, whom he hath iuſtified, but where Chriſt lodgeth, there muſt needes be great ioy.<note n="g" place="margin">Nonne vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is cum amicu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lomi quiſpiam <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ccipit quom <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>raeſe ferat <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>atitiam? &amp;c. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hryſ. in Iohan. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>1.</hi> Hom. <hi>19.</hi>
               </note> Doe you not ſee if a man doth but receiue an ordinary friend into his houſe, how ioyfull he is? how much more joyfull then muſt wee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue them to be, who haue teſtimony in their conſciences, that the Lord of glory hath come in by their gates, and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken vp his lodging in their ſoules?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> As the former, ſo this Doctrine alſo ſerues, 1. to lay open the miſerable and wretched eſtate of all carnall and vnre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:183854:35"/> ones, who are no members of the true Church. For no ſound ioy belongs vnto them. Their abundance of wealth, their places of honour, their great friends, their mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry companions, &amp;c. may peradventure giue them ſome kind of contentment and delight, but alas, it is but for a moment, and<note n="*" place="margin">Nam<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> mal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> quanquam in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terdu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> gauder<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> videtur: Aeſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> at ipſe tamen medijs vt ſtro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gylos vndis. Marcell. Arie l. <hi>1.</hi> p. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> mingled many times with much heauineſſe and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row; That joy which ſprings from Iuſtification is too ſweet, too excellent for them to attaine to; <hi>There is no peace to the wicked, ſayth my God</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Iſa. 57.21</note>. <hi>That, that</hi> (I ſay) is <hi>Sions</hi> peculiar. An vngodly man, may indeed heare the promiſes, haue the ſweet Doctrine of iuſtification, by the free loue of Chriſt, ſounded in his eares, and abuſe the ſame he may (as thoſe that make an idoll of Gods mercy) to further himſelfe in his deſperate diſeaſe of ſecuritie, or a kinde of<note n="i" place="margin">Mat. 13.20</note> hypocriticall ioy he may haue, which a temporall faith may afford him: but to draw out the right ſweetneſſe of this heauenly Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, to the true comfort of his ſoule, he wants noſtrills, he hath no true iuſtifying and ſauing faith. Let then an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regenerate perſon (be he what he will, or can be, for wit, learning, wealth, friends, dignitie, &amp;c.) come and put forth that Queſtion, which <hi>Ioram</hi> put forth to <hi>Iehu; Is it peace Iehu, is it peace?</hi> It may be anſwered him, as <hi>Iehu</hi> anſwered <hi>Ioram; What peace, ſo long as the Whoredomes of thy Mother</hi> Iezebell, <hi>and her witch-crafts are ſo many</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">2 Kin. 9.22</note>. <hi>What peace ſo long as thy luxurious fruits, thy couetous fruits, extortions, oppreſſions, vſuries, deceitfull tricks, thy oathes, lyes, enuyings, backbitings, Sabboth breakings, neglects of Gods worſhip in the Temple, in the familie, in the cloſet, contempts of Gods ſeruants, and Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, contentments with thy meere ciuill courſes, &amp;c.</hi> are ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny? What peace, I ſay, appertaines vnto thee, ſo long as theſe things remaine in thee, as ſo many teſtimonies againſt thee, that thou art not yet a true member of Chriſts Spouſe the Church? <hi>Thou</hi> man, <hi>thou</hi> woman, art like thoſe whom the Lord complaines of by the Prophet;<note n="l" place="margin">Iſa. 65.11.</note> 
               <hi>Yee are they that forſake the Lord, and forget mine holy Mountaine.</hi> Thou haſt playd the Harlot, and runne away from Chriſt, and haſt<note n="m" place="margin">Verſ. 12.</note> 
               <hi>choſen that wherein the Lord delighted not;</hi> And therefore
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:183854:36"/> muſt I conclude (to the terror of thee, and all ſuch as thou art) with that ſentence which the Lord denounceth by the ſame Prophet;<note n="n" place="margin">Iſa. 65.13.14.</note> 
               <hi>Behold, MY SERVANTS ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce, but YE ſhall be aſhamed. Behold, my ſervants ſhall ſing for ioy of heart, but YE ſhall cry for ſorrow of heart, and ſhall howle for vexation of ſpirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> Againe, ſtill we ſee comfort to flow out of this Text, to the people of God, by occaſion of this point alſo. They may peraduenture haue heauie hearts, drouping ſpirits, and goe mourning all the day long, and by reaſon or outward croſſes, or inward diſtreſſes, they may with <hi>Rachell</hi> refuſe to be comforted, becauſe their comforts are not, and in their owne apprehenſion, haue no being, no exiſtence; but let them be of good cheere. The ioy that ſpringeth from the roote of iuſtification, belonges vnto euery member of the Church; As ſure as can be, <hi>light is ſowen for the righteous,</hi> and <hi>ioy for all them that are of an vpright heart.</hi> As they haue this bundle of <hi>Myrrhe,</hi> this ſweet-ball of Chriſt his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, in free mercy beſtowed vpon them, ſo the Lord in his due time, will open the noſtrills of their faith, and make them ſenſible of the ſweetneſſe of the ſame, and the time ſhall come when in the ſence and ioyfull perſwaſion of the ſame, they ſhall be able with all confidence and boldnes, to ſay, as the Church here doth; <hi>A bundle of Myrrhe is my Well-beloued vnto mee, now I know it, finde it, and feele it.</hi> Stay thy ſelfe with this then, thou mourner in <hi>Sion;</hi> and goe thy wayes, <hi>Eate thy bread with ioy,</hi> and <hi>drinke thy wine with a merry heart, for God</hi> now <hi>accepteth thy Workes</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">Eccleſ. 9.7.</note>. Being a mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Church, thou art acceptable to God in Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, and being acceptable to him, He will reveale his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable preſence vnto thee, be thy diſtreſſe what it can be. And let this ſuffice thee againſt deſpayre, that though <hi>heaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe may endure for a night, yet ioy ſhall come in the morning.</hi> Such ioy is thy portion, ſuch ioy ſhalt thou get into thine owne poſſeſſion, when God ſees fit. Waite therefore for it on the God of thy ſaluation, and be not like a comfortles creature.</p>
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:183854:36"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>3</label> Thirdly, Hence we ſee how the world is deceiued, who thinke Chriſtians to be melancholy perſons, whom no mirth, no comfort, belongs to; imagining, that of all others, they are the ſaddeſt and heauieſt creatures; What ſayd I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued? yea, groſſely deceiued. For there are none vnder heauen, haue more cauſe of ioy then they haue, nor are more ſenſible of true ioy then they are, when God comes to lift vp the light of his countenance vpon them. The ioy that the couetous man hath in his bags, the ambitious man in his honours, the voluptuous man in his pleaſures, are but ſorrow and vexation of ſpirit, in compariſon of that ſweete content, that a poore honeſt ſoule findeth in his Chriſt, in his Sauiour. How can his life be a melancholy life, that was condemned to death, but is now reſtored to life; that had loſt heauen, but hath it now purchaſed for him; that was the heyre of damnation, but is now the heyre of ſaluation; that was naked, and abhominable in the eyes of God, but is now cloathed, and acceptable vnto him? How can this life (I ſay) be altogether vncapable of comfort, of conſolation? If thou thinkeſt it is (when as Chriſtians haue this priuiledge, to reioyce in the aſſurance of their iuſtification) thou thinkeſt amiſſe, and art in a groſſe er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror.</p>
            <p>LET vs now paſſe on to the effect which the ſence <hi>of,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The ſecond branch in the ſecond part of the Text.</note> and ioy <hi>from,</hi> this ſweetneſſe of iuſtification worketh, in the deſires and vowes of the Church. And that is a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of this benefit, in theſe words; <hi>He ſhall lodge all night betwixt my breaſts:</hi> or (as ſome reade) <hi>It ſhall lodge all night betweene my breasts:</hi> or (as others) Optatiuely. <hi>Oh, that he would</hi> (that is, <hi>oh, that my Beloued</hi>) or, <hi>oh that IT may,</hi> (that is, this bundle of <hi>Myrrhe</hi> may) <hi>lodge all night betwixt my breaſts.</hi> Howſoeuer the wordes be read, I take the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to ſtand thus; <hi>It is the reſolution of mee the Church, that this ſweet bundle ſhall,</hi> or, <hi>It is my heartie deſire, that my belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued Chriſt, and the ſweetneſſe which I ſmell in his righteouſneſſe, may abide with me ſo long as I am in the might of this world.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="66" facs="tcp:183854:37"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The reaſon of the <hi>Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſe.</hi>
               </note>For <hi>lodging,</hi> is a ſymbole of continuance, and <hi>breaſts</hi> doe note out the will and affections, and ſo by conſequent, the reſolution and deſire; and <hi>night,</hi> the world. Therefore by <hi>lodging all night betwixt the breaſts,</hi> is meant, the abiding of Chriſt as a <hi>Iuſtifier,</hi> with the ſweetnes of his righteouſneſſe, in the deſires and reſolution of a Chriſtian, ſo long as he is in this world.</p>
            <p>I could obſerue from hence, thus much; <hi>That they, that are once iuſtified by Chriſt, are for euer iuſtified.</hi> Proue it I could out of <hi>Iſa.</hi> 32.17. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2. towardes the latter end. <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.29. And by occaſion of this, I could tell the doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and perplexed <hi>ſoule,</hi> to its ſingular conſolation, that though it be in the night of tribulation, and temptation in this world, yet Chriſt Ieſus will neuer forſake it, but will <hi>pernoctare, lodge with it all night,</hi> nothing ſhall ſeperate it from the loue of God in Chriſt Ieſus. But there is another maine thing I driue at; and this it is.</p>
            <q>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>6</label> That it is the reſolution, and deſire of the true members of the Church, to retaine and keepe all their life long, that ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe which they ſmell in the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt, that ioy which they haue from their aſſurance of being iuſtified freely by Him.</q>
            <p>This was <hi>Dauids</hi> reſolution; <hi>I will reioyce and be glad in thy mercie</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Pſal. 31.7.</note>. Marke, he contents not himſelfe to ſpeake in the time preſent, <hi>I DOE reioyce,</hi> but he ſpeakes in the Future tenſe, <hi>I WILL reioyce,</hi> ſhewing what his minde and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe was. This was alſo the DESIRE of that holy man;<note n="c" place="margin">Pſal. 24.7.</note> 
               <hi>One thing haue I DESIRED of the Lord, that I will ſeeke after; that I may dwell in the houſe of the Lord, all the dayes of my life, to behold the beautie of the Lord.</hi> And euer and anon, you ſhall finde that Prophet, crying; <hi>Lord lift thou vp the light of thy countenance vpon mee, and then I ſhall be ſafe,</hi> that is, <hi>then I ſhall haue what I would haue</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Pſal. 4.</note>. <hi>Reſtore vnto mee the ioy of thy ſalvation</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Pſal. 51.</note>, <hi>that the bones which thou haſt broken may reioyce</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">V.</note>. Hence it is, that the ioy of Gods people, is called an euerlaſting ioy<note n="g" place="margin">Iſa. 61.7.</note>. The complaints of Chriſtians, in the
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:183854:37"/> time of ſpirituall <hi>deſertion,</hi> doe euidently ſhow this. For looke as <hi>Iob</hi> in the time of his adverſitie, did bewayle the loſſe of his former proſperitie, in theſe termes;<note n="h" place="margin">Iob. 29.2.3.6.</note> 
               <hi>Oh, that I were as in moneths paſt, as in the dayes when God preſerued me: when his candle ſhined vpon my head, and when by his light I walked through darkeneſſe. When I waſhed my ſteps in butter, and the rockes poured ryvers of Oyle.</hi> So complaine Beleeuers, when they are inſenſible of thoſe inward comforts, and ſweete internall ioyes they were wont to haue; <hi>Oh, that it were with me as in times paſt, as in the dayes when God refreſhed mee, when the candle of his bright countenance ſhined vpon mee, when by the light of his ſweet comforts, I did walke ioyfully through the darkeſt temptations: Oh, that it were with me as it was when the rocke, Chriſt Ieſus, poured out rivers of ioy vnto mee, to accheere me in the aſſurance of iuſtification by his owne blood.</hi> Now what doth this kinde of complaint intimate vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, but that the Church is deſirous to retaine that ioy which ariſeth from the aſſurance which ſhee hath of ſharing in the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>
               </label> Neither need wee marvaile at it, for why, this <hi>ſweetneſſe,</hi> this <hi>ioy,</hi> which ſpringes from this roote, is one of the moſt infallible teſtimonies of the loue of Chriſt; but choyce loue-tokens (as wee know) are moſt deſiredly kept and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained. Let a Wooer beſtow vpon his Loue, but a Noſegay or Muske-ball, as a teſtimony of his loue; and (if ſhee takes it ſo) whatſoeuer ſhee be careleſſe of els, ſhee will be very carefull to keepe <hi>that,</hi> and ſtill be deſiring to recreate her ſelfe with the ſweetneſſe of <hi>that.</hi> Inaſmuch therefore as ioy in the holy Ghoſt, is a ſpeciall token of the Church her be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loueds good will vnto her, ſhee muſt needs be carefull to keepe <hi>that</hi> (except ſhee be very much out of tune) and ſtill haue <hi>that</hi> bundle betweene her breaſts, in the very night time, that is, <hi>that ſweetnes in her deſires, euen in the dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt, and darkeſt affections.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> Firſt of all, doe Chriſtians deſire to keepe that ioy which the aſſurance of their free iuſtification by Chriſt doth effect in them? then this ſhowes, that ſound and ſolid ioy, is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manent,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:183854:38"/> and durable. It is not <hi>flitting,</hi> like the ioy of the <hi>worldling;</hi> it is not <hi>vaniſhing,</hi> like the ioy of the <hi>hypocrite;</hi> it is not <hi>periſhing,</hi> like the ioy of the <hi>Epicure. In Gods preſence is fulneſſe of ioy, and at his right hand</hi> (ſaith <hi>Dauid</hi> in a Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall ſtrayne of Chriſt) <hi>are pleaſures for euermore</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Pſal. 16.</note>. Now if in His <hi>GLORIOVS</hi> preſence, there be fulneſſe of ioy, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting pleaſures; then the ioyes of his <hi>gracious</hi> preſence muſt needs be <hi>durable</hi> alſo, being the <hi>taſt</hi> and <hi>beginning</hi> of the <hi>glorious.</hi> I deny not, but that there is a mixture of ſorrowes with their ioyes, becauſe it is fit, and needfull, that ſo it ſhould be; yet this doth not <hi>nullifie</hi> the <hi>perpetuitie</hi> of them, becauſe it doth not anibilate the <hi>eſſence</hi> of them. Though Chriſtians haue not alwayes a <hi>feeling</hi> of them, yet they haue alwayes the <hi>being</hi> of them. <hi>Myrrhe,</hi> betweene a mans breaſts, hath a ſweetnes in the night time, though whiles he ſleepes, he ſmells it not: So, aſſurance of iuſtification is in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuers heart, and the ſweetneſſe of it in his ſoule, though while he ſlippes into ſinne, and is in ſome ſleepie fits of car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſecuritie, he be not ſenſible of the ſame. To thinke then that the ioy of Gods people, is a fading or tranſitorie ioy, is a groundles conceite, and a wrong done the honour of Gods mercy, which is the fountaine of it. For <hi>what</hi> God giues his children an hearty deſire continually to keepe, <hi>that</hi> will <hi>HE</hi> keepe continually for them.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> Secondly, this is of vſe, to exhort and ſtirre vp all them that want this ioy,<note place="margin">Exhortation to vnbeleeuers to get this ioy.</note> to ſeeke after it, and to endeuour to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine it. Such earthly things as are moſt permanent in their owne kinde, are moſt deſired by them that enioy them, euery one will labour after them. <hi>This</hi> ioy is euer durable: They that haue <hi>this</hi> ioy, doe reſolue and deſire euer to keepe it. Labour therefore, oh, labour (I ſay) with might and mayne to get it, you that want it. And to helpe you hereto, you muſt not thinke, that it can be <hi>gotten for gold,</hi> or <hi>that ſiluer ſhall be weighed for the price thereof</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Iob. 28.15. Helpes to true ioy.</note>. But by theſe meanes.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, by a godly ſorrow for ſinne. <hi>Mary Magdalene</hi> was fayne to ſtand <hi>behinde Chriſt weeping,</hi> and <hi>to waſh his feete
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:183854:38"/> with her teares,</hi> before he had her <hi>Goe in peace</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Luk. 7.38.50.</note>. <hi>Peters</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts were <hi>pricked in their hearts,</hi> before they <hi>could eate their meate with gladnes</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Act. 2.37.46.</note>. The laylor <hi>trembled</hi> before he <hi>reioyced</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Act. 16.26.</note>. They are the <hi>bleſſed ones which mourne,</hi> that <hi>ſhalbe comforted</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">Math. 5.4.</note>. Let not <hi>them</hi> thinke euer to come to <hi>this</hi> ioy, who driue out of their owne hearts, all conſideration of their <hi>owne ſinnes,</hi> which they haue <hi>committed;</hi> of <hi>Gods iudgements,</hi> which they haue <hi>deſerued;</hi> of <hi>Gods iuſtice,</hi> which is <hi>prouoked;</hi> of <hi>Gods ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie,</hi> which is <hi>offended;</hi> that their <hi>hearts</hi> may feele no <hi>ſmart,</hi> their <hi>ſoules</hi> may be affected with no <hi>ſorrow,</hi> for their tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions. For if euer thou haſt read the <hi>Pſalmes</hi> of <hi>Dauid</hi> through, thou haſt found <hi>this</hi> to be true, that <hi>they which ſow in teares, ſhall reape in ioy</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">Pſal. 30.6.</note>. Oh, you hard-hearted, and impenitent ones then, who could neuer yet mourn for your ſinnes, heare what Saint <hi>Iames</hi> ſaith, and be adviſed by him. <hi>Be afflicted, mourne, and weepe, let your laughter be turned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to mourning, and your vaine ioy into heauineſſe</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">Iam. 4.9.</note>: that ſo mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, you may be comforted, and (as they, who after they haue endured many a ſore tempeſt by Sea, come to <hi>Arabia,</hi> where <hi>Myrrhe</hi> growes, get it, gather it, and ſmell on it) ſo you, after your ſoules haue beene truely humbled within you, may apprehend the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt, and be ſpiritually rauiſhed with the ſweetneſſe of it, in ſuch wiſe, that you may both reſolue, and deſire, neuer to let it goe.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">2. Helpe to get true ioy.</note>Secondly, Get a good conſcience; for <hi>that</hi> (as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith) <hi>is a continuall feaſt.</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Pro. 15.15.</note>. Well ſpake an <hi>Ancient</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">Aug. ad Fr. in Erem Ser. <hi>10.</hi> Ad ſpirituale gaudium hodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erno die in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendo, &amp;c.</note> to this purpoſe; <hi>I intend, brethren, this day to inuite you to a feaſt of ſpirituall ioy, which ioy neither the plentie of riches, nor the glory of the world, nor greatneſſe of poſteritie, nor health of body procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, but onely puritie of conſcience.</hi> And no marvaile; for if an <hi>euill conſcience begets a timorous and trembling heart</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">Mala conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entia cor tabeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cens, &amp; trepi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dans gignit, Muſcut. in Pſal. <hi>18</hi> p. <hi>182.</hi>
               </note> then a <hi>good conſcience</hi> muſt needes produce a <hi>ioyfull</hi> and <hi>merrie</hi> heart. Now how to get a <hi>good conſcience,</hi> I direct elſe-where<note n="u" place="margin">Court of conſcience. pag. 50.51. &amp;c.</note>.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">3. Helpe to true ioy.</note>Laſtly, becauſe worldlineſſe is a great enemie to this ioy, therefore <hi>take heed and beware of couetouſneſſe</hi>
               <note n="¶" place="margin">Luk. 12.15.</note>. Stop thy no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrills
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:183854:39"/> full of earth, and the ſweeteſt Odours cannot affect the ſmell; So, let a man heare the ſweeteſt Doctrines of the Goſpell, euen of <hi>free iustification by Chriſt, &amp;c.</hi> he can ſmell no ſweetneſſe in them, he can feele no comfort by them, if his heart be ſtuffed, and inordinately affected with the things of this life. As therefore thou wouldeſt reioyce in the aſſurance of <hi>Gods loue,</hi> make not the world thy <hi>God</hi> to loue.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>3</label> Laſtly. Doth the Church here giue an example to all her ſonnes and daughters, in reſoluing that this ſweetneſſe <hi>ſhall,</hi> in deſiring that this ſweetneſſe <hi>may,</hi> abide in her conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually? Then this ſhould teach all thoſe members of the Church, who haue taſted of the ioy of Gods ſaluation, to endeuour to keepe and maintaine the ſame. The deſires of a good Mother, in good things (eſpecially ſeconded with care and induſtry) muſt be the patterne of the Childrens endeuours. If our Mother the Church hath deſired, and endeuoured in ALL ages to keepe this ioy; then WEE, (members of her bodie) in this age, muſt be carefull not to come behinde her in ſuch deſires and endeuours. With how holy a vehemency doth <hi>Paul</hi> enforce this vpon the Church her children, both at <hi>Philippi,</hi> and <hi>Theſſalonica; Reioyce in the Lord alway, againe, I ſay reioyce</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Phil. 4.4.</note>. <hi>Reioyce euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">1 Theſ. 5.16.</note>. <hi>In this ioy as a man cannot be too exceſſiue</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">Pet. Mart. Eth. l. <hi>1.</hi> p. <hi>100.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aec iocunditas <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>itioſum ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſſumpati non <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oteſt.</note>, for the meaſure, ſo he cannot be <hi>too long,</hi> for the time.</p>
            <p>Our Sauiour tells his Diſciples, that he would haue <hi>His ioy REMAINE in them</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Ioh. 15.11.</note>. Say therefore of this thy ioy (thou Chriſtian ſoule) as <hi>Iob</hi> of his innocencie; <hi>I will not let it goe vntill death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now that thou mayeſt haue ſome directions in this caſe, theſe Rules will be vſefull for thee.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">How to keepe ſpirituall ioy. 1. <hi>Rule.</hi>
               </note>Firſt, maintaine thy ioy in the Word, let <hi>that</hi> be the very ioy and reioycing of thy heart. Let neither the pleaſures of the fleſh, nor the profits of the world, nor the companie nor counſell of carnall friends, make thee giue ouer thy private reading, ſtudie, and meditation, in <hi>that.</hi> Let neither the foulnes, nor coldneſſe of the weather, nor the length of
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:183854:39"/> the way, nor the ſhortnes of the dayes, coole thy forward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, or quayle thy diligence in the <hi>hearing</hi> of <hi>that.</hi> I am perſwaded, that <hi>Dauid</hi> did ſo much <hi>reioyce</hi> in the <hi>favour</hi> of God, becauſe he did ſo much <hi>delight</hi> in the <hi>Word</hi> of GOD. So much he ſeemes to teſtifie in that 27. <hi>Pſalme.</hi> verſ. 4. <hi>I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to dwell in the houſe of the Lord all my dayes, that I may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the beautie of the Lord;</hi> As if theſe words were (after a ſort) ſpoken of purpoſe, to ſhow, that if wee continue our <hi>delight</hi> in <hi>Gods Temple,</hi> wee ſhall continue our <hi>ſight</hi> of <hi>Gods beautie,</hi> ſhining vpon vs continually to refreſh vs. In the <hi>Word,</hi> wee ſhall meete with ſuch ſweete ſentences, ſuch gracious promiſes, as will ſtrengthen our ioy, as will rayſe vs vp out of our heauie and diſconſolate fits, as will ſhew Chriſt vnto vs, as will reveale the vnſpeakeable goodneſſe of God vnto vs. Experience in the Church of Chriſt, proues, that many a man and woman, hath gone with a trembling ſpirit, with a perplexed conſcience (becauſe their ioyes were not as they were wont to be) to the hearing of many a Sermon, about the reading of many a Chapter in the Bible, or of ſome other ſweete paſſages in good Bookes; and they haue met with that <hi>conſolation,</hi> that <hi>ſatisfaction,</hi> that they would not for any thing haue miſſed off. Let but thy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light then in the <hi>Word</hi> of God <hi>abate,</hi> and I dare boldly tell thee, thou ſhalt finde as much to doe to maintaine thy ioy in thy iuſtification, as he, to continue the refreſhing of his brayne with ſweete flowers, that cares not to come into thoſe Gardens where they grow, or, that, hauing gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red them alreadie, ſtops them in ſome corner farre from his noſtrills. Be ſure therefore ſtill to reioyce in the garden of the Scriptures, and be ſtill plucking and ſucking the ſweetneſſe of them, by private ſtudie, and publique hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring.</p>
            <p>Againe, a ſerious and frequent Meditation, vpon the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellence of the benefit of <hi>free iuſtification by Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Rule.</hi> To keepe ſpirituall ioy.</note> is a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond help for a CHRISTIAN to maintaine his ſpirituall ioy. The deeper a man diues into the nature of a thing, the more knowledge ſhall a man haue of the value of that
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:183854:40"/> thing, and ſutable to his ſight of the worth of it, will his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in it be. The more ſweete flowers are <hi>rubbed,</hi> the more fragrant Odour is extracted from them; yea, though theſe flowers ſeeme ſomewhat dead, yet by <hi>rubbing,</hi> the ſmell of them is revived; So, could but our faith euer and anon, be rubbing out by divine Meditation, the marrow and ſpirits (as it were) of this bundle of <hi>Myrrhe,</hi> of this priuiledge, of <hi>partaking</hi> freely in the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt Ieſus, it is admirable to thinke what abundance of <hi>ſweetneſſe,</hi> wee ſhall draw out of the ſame, to the continuall accheering and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhing of our ſoules.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
               </label> Yea, but how muſt I by Meditation rubbe out this ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> I anſwere, thou muſt make, the <hi>effects</hi> of <hi>Iuſtification,</hi> the <hi>Obiect,</hi>
               <note place="margin">How by me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation to pull ſweetnes out of Iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, <hi>viz.</hi> by meditating on the effect of Iuſtification. 1. <hi>Effect.</hi>
               </note> of theſe thy <hi>Meditations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt of all therefore thinke oft with thy ſelfe, what an excellent thing it is, <hi>of an enemie of God, to be made a friend of God; of one that Once wert at oddes with him, to be ſet at one with him:</hi> but by vertue of the <hi>righteouſneſſe of Chriſt,</hi> thou art <hi>at one</hi> with God, as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh; <hi>Being iuſtified by faith, wee haue peace with God, through Ieſus Christ our Lord</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Rom. 5.1.</note>.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Effect.</hi>
               </note>Secondly, meditate what a rare thing it is, that, <hi>whereas thou wert once tyed to a moſt ſtrict obedience to the Law of God (euen in thine owne perſon) inſomuch that for thy fayling in the leaſt tittle of that obedience, then ſhouldeſt haue ſmarted for it for euer, now thou art freed from that rigour, Chriſt hath per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed that perfect obedience for thee, and that Evangelicall o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, which now thou performest</hi> (being ſincerely reſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue to all the Commandements) <hi>is acceptable through Chriſt Ieſus.</hi> But this alſo is an effect of juſtification, as the ſame Apoſtle teſtifieth, when he ſaith; <hi>When the fulneſſe of time was come, God ſent forth his Son, made of a woman, made vnder the Law, to redeeme them that were vnder the Law</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Gal. 4.4.</note>. That is,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:183854:40"/> they that haue ſhare in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>his</hi> righteouſneſſe, they are redeemed from the rigour of the Law.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, thinke with thy ſelfe, what an excellent benefit it is to be <hi>freed from the curſe of the Law</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Gal. 3.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>3.</note>, <hi>to be redeemed from condemnation, and from the wrath that is to come.</hi> But this benefit belongs to them that are iuſtified. <hi>Being now iuſtified by his blood, wee ſhall be ſaued from wrath through Him</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Rom. 5.9.</note>.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Meditate how great a priviledge it is to be <hi>freed from the ſting of a tormenting conſcience, which once thou didst vnder goe; What a libertie thou haſt now euer what thou hadst then, when the Arrowes of the Almightie did drinke vp thy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; and a reſtleſſe, terrified, ſoule was within thee; and what great oddes there is betwixt thine eſtate now, and thy caſe then.</hi> But this freedome from terrors of conſcience, comes from <hi>iuſtification,</hi> as the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſignifieth in the 41. Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of his Prophecie, the latter part of the tenth verſe, being compared with the firſt part of the foureteenth, where <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob, who is vpheld with the right hand of Gods righteouſneſſe, is wiſhed</hi> (by the Lord) <hi>not to feare, nor be terrified;</hi> as giuing vs to vnderſtand, that terrors of conſcience doe not belong <note n="*" place="margin">That is, as they did to <hi>Cain,</hi> and doe to Reprobates to driue them to deſpera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> to them that are iuſtified. And in another place of that Booke, they that are <hi>trees of righteouſneſſe, of the planting of the Lord.</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Iſa. 61.3.</note>, or that are the <hi>righteous people</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Iſa. 60.21.</note>, are promiſed to haue (by Chriſt their Iuſtifier) <hi>their broken hearts bound vp, to haue beautie inſtead of aſhes, the oyle of ioy in ſtead of mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and the garment of gladneſſe inſtead of the garment of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uineſſe.</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Iſa. 61.1.3.</note>.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, Meditate what a ſingular prerogatiue it is to <hi>haue hope in death, and that, whereas they that teare and weare out their dayes in ſinne are like to die, either ragingly and diſconlo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tely, as,</hi> Saul, Iudas, <hi>and</hi> Iulian <hi>did; or elſe blockiſhly, like a ſtone, as</hi> Naball <hi>did; thou ſhalt die quietly, goe to thy graue in
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:183854:41"/> peace, and although it ſhould be thy portion, to haue ſharpe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counters with the Tempter, yet that thou ſhalt haue victorie, and confidence in the greateſt extremitie.</hi> But this ſpringeth alſo from <hi>iuſtification,</hi> as the Wiſe-man ſpeaketh; <hi>The righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> (or the iuſtified man) <hi>hath hope in death</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Pro. 14.32.</note>.</p>
            <p>Sixtly, Thinke oft what a priviledge it is to haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in the middeſt of afflictions, and <hi>that, whereas outward troubles and croſſes, are tokens of Gods wrath and diſpleaſure to the wicked, they are ſignes of his loue and favour towardes thee.</hi> But <hi>this</hi> alſo thou haſt by the <hi>righteouſneſſe</hi> of <hi>Chriſt. Being iuſtified by faith</hi> (ſaith Paul) <hi>wee glory in tribulations, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that tribulation worketh patience, patience experience, expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience hope, and hope maketh not aſhamed, becauſe the loue of God is ſhed abroad in our hearts by the holy Ghoſt, which is giuen vs</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Rom. 5.1.3.4.5.</note>.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, conſider ſeriouſly, what an ineſtimable bleſſing it is to haue euerlaſting bliſſe in the life to come; And, <hi>that, (whereas Reprobates ſhall haue that fearefull ſentence, denoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced against them, Goe yee curſed, &amp;c.) thou art like to heare that ſweet voice, ſpeaking to thee; Come thou bleſſed, inherit the kingdome prepared for thee from the beginning of the world.</hi> But this is another fruit of ſharing in the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt, if S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> may be beleeued; <hi>Whom he hath iuſtified, them alſo hath He glorified</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Rom. 8.30.</note>; <hi>That as ſinne hath raigned vnto death, euen ſo might grace raigne through RIGHTEOVS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NES vnto ETERNALL LIFE, by Chriſt Ieſus our Lord</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Rom. 5.21.</note>.</p>
            <p>Meditate vpon theſe things, thou man or woman <hi>great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beloued</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Dan. 10.11.19.</note>. I tell thee Chriſtian, for want of this meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, thou art much thine owne enemie. Thou ſpendeſt many a day vncheerefully, many an houre vncomfortably, becauſe thou doeſt not ſo ſearch into the <hi>worth</hi> of <hi>this bun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle of Myrrhe,</hi> by ſuch <hi>Meditations</hi> as thou ſhouldeſt. Can the often ruminating on this, <hi>that,</hi> (by vertue of
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:183854:41"/> Chriſts righteouſneſſe) <hi>thou art at peace with God, freed from the rigour of the Law, redeemed from the curſe of the Law, quiet, truely quiet in thy Conſcience, that thou haſt right to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in afflictions, to hope in death, to perfection of bleſſedneſſe at the day of iudgement;</hi> Can (I ſay) can this chuſe, but pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue in thee, that ſpirituall ioy the Lord hath implanted in thy ſoule? <hi>Giue heed</hi> therefore, <hi>giue heed</hi> to theſe privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, and againe and againe thinke vpon them. So much for the ſecond Rule.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, A Chriſtian ſhall preſerue his ioy,<note place="margin">3. Helpe to preſerue ioy.</note> by preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing his <hi>faith. Faith</hi> is the noſtrill of the ſoule (as I told you) which ſendeth this ioy to the heart, from the appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of <hi>Chriſts righteouſneſſe,</hi> looke therefore how <hi>that</hi> is enfeebled, ſo will the <hi>ioy</hi> be extenuated. They,<note place="margin">A Similie.</note> that would haue ſweet ſmells haue free paſſage to the braine, to refreſh the animall ſpirits that be there, muſt haue a care to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent Vlcers from breeding in the noſtrills, by drying and ſtrengthening the head, that no ſuperfluities (which are the cauſe of ſuch Vlcers) flow out of the head into the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrills. So thou that wouldeſt haue the ſweetneſſe of this <hi>Myrrhe,</hi> the ioy of iuſtification to haue paſſage by the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrills of faith alwayes to thy ſoule; <hi>Keepe thy heart with all diligence, watch, and obſerue that,</hi> that the excrements and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluities of <hi>vnbeliefe, doubtings, diſtruſt in Gods prouidence, fleſhly eaſe, giuing way to the loue of earthly things,</hi> like ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Vlcers, may not breed in thy <hi>faith,</hi> and <hi>breath</hi> our ſuch an vnkinde and ſtinking Odour, as may ſtop the paſſage of thoſe comforts to thy ſoule, with which once thou wert wont to be refreſhed.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Take heed of ſinne againſt conſcience.<note place="margin">4. Helpe.</note> The <hi>getting</hi> of a good conſcience, is (as hath beene ſhewed) a meanes to <hi>come by ioy.</hi> And the <hi>keeping</hi> of a good conſcience is a meanes to <hi>conſerue</hi> ioy: How did <hi>Dauid</hi> eclipſe <hi>his</hi> ioy, and <hi>Peter his,</hi> when as the <hi>one</hi> defiled himſelfe by <hi>adulterie</hi> and <hi>murther,</hi> and the <hi>other</hi> denyed his <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>Maſter, both</hi> againſt the light of their owne conſciences.</p>
            <pb n="76" facs="tcp:183854:42"/>
            <p>And wherefore is it, that ſome Chriſtians, who were once wont to reioyce in the ſauing health of the God of <hi>Iacob,</hi> come to be plunged into deepe fits of diſtreſſe, our of which they cannot ſo ſoone, and eaſily recouer themſelues, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are ſomewhat more bold with their conſciences then it is fit, on lawfull. If thou wouldeſt walke then <hi>conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually</hi> with the white garments of <hi>gladneſſe</hi> vpon thy ſoule, beware thou doe not wound thy ſoule, by giuing way to any ſinne, but endeuour to keepe <hi>a cleere conſcience before God,</hi> and <hi>towardes men, holding</hi> (as the Apoſtle adviſeth) <hi>the myſterie of faith in a pure conſcience</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">1 Tim. 3.9.</note>.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">5. Helpe.</note>To conclude all. In the laſt place, becauſe a worldly, and carnall ioy, is a great enemie to the ſpirituall, and ſith it is as impoſſible for a man to <hi>reioyce</hi> (as worldlings doe) <hi>in the world, and the Lord, as to ſerue two Maſters</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">Aug de verb. Dom. Ser. <hi>37.</hi> Sicut non poteſt homo duobus dominis ſerui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, ſic &amp; nemo in hoc ſeculo poteſt gaudere et in Domino.</note>: therefore take heed of a <hi>carnall</hi> and <hi>worldly</hi> ioy.<note n="*" place="margin">A caution.</note> Not that I would haue a Chriſtian, not take comfort in the outward bleſſings that God hath lent him; For, as he hath <hi>beſt right</hi> vnto them, ſo he hath <hi>moſt</hi> cauſe to take ſome <hi>comfort,</hi> in them: And not to doe <hi>ſo, Salomon</hi> calls a <hi>vanitie vnder</hi> the <hi>Sunne</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">Eccleſ. 5</note>. But not onely to reioyce in <hi>impietie</hi> againſt God, in <hi>iniquitie</hi> againſt man (as profane ones doe) but alſo to reioyce in the <hi>outward</hi> good bleſſings of God <hi>exceſſiuely</hi> or <hi>carnally,</hi> is <hi>that</hi> which I adviſe euery beleeuer to beware of. If a man ſhould mingle a bunch of <hi>Wormewood</hi> with a bundle of <hi>Myrrhe,</hi> you cannot make me beleeue, there will be ſo ſweet a ſmell, as the <hi>Myrrhe</hi> alone would yeeld; Euen ſo, he that admits any tranſitorie, and worldly thing, at any time, as an equall Obiect of his ioy, with this tranſcendent treaſure of juſtification, let him tell mee (be he neuer ſo deare in the eyes of God) whither he depriues not his ſoule (for the preſent) of that abundance of comfort, which once the thought of his diſcharge by Chriſt, did conuey vnto him. When therefore thou art to ſolace thy ſelfe with the vſe of the creatures, let thy ioy know a meaſure, leaſt the
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:183854:42"/> vnmeaſurableneſſe of thy worldly ioy, leſſen the meaſure of thy ſpirituall ioy, which this Bundle of <hi>Myrrhe,</hi> the righteouſneſſe of CHRIST IESVS is the ground of.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the Rules by which thou mayeſt obtaine thy ioy in juſtification. Thinke on them, make vſe of them. And <hi>heauens</hi>-bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing make them beneficiall vnto thy ſoule.</p>
            <closer>AMEN.</closer>
            <closer>LAVS DEO.</closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:183854:43"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
